<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A practical discourse upon humility wherein is shewn the nature, reasonableness, and usefulness thereof : together with the ways of expressing and increasing it / by Edward Pelling ...</title>
            <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 244 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 108 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53960</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1087</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38182</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17202860</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17202860</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106212</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53960)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106212)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1621:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A practical discourse upon humility wherein is shewn the nature, reasonableness, and usefulness thereof : together with the ways of expressing and increasing it / by Edward Pelling ...</title>
                  <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 198 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Crooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imperfect: cropped, with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Humility --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106212:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106212:1"/>
            <p> A Practical Diſcourſe UPON HUMILITY. Wherein is ſhewn, The
<hi>Nature, Reaſonableneſs,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefulneſs</hi> thereof. Together With the Ways of <hi>Expreſſing</hi> and <hi>Increaſing</hi> it.</p>
            <p>By EDWARD PELLING, D. D. Chaplain in Ordinary to Their
<hi>Majeſties,</hi> and Rector of <hi>Petworth</hi> in
<hi>Suſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Crooke,</hi> at the
<hi>Green Dragon</hi> without <hi>Temple-Barr,</hi> 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:106212:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106212:2"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>THE Introduction.</hi> Page 1</item>
               <item>CHAP. I. <hi>Of the Nature of Humility.</hi> 5</item>
               <item>CHAP. II. <hi>The Lovelineſs of Humility.</hi> 16</item>
               <item>CHAP. III. <hi>The Reaſonableneſs of Humility.</hi>
23</item>
               <item>CHAP. IV. <hi>The Uſefulneſs of Humility, in reſpect of the Peace of Mind it brings.</hi> 40</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:106212:3"/>
               <item> CHAP. V. <hi>The Uſefulneſs of Humility, in reſpect of our Proficiency in Vertue.</hi> 63</item>
               <item>CHAP. VI. <hi>The Uſefulneſs of Humility, in reſpect of the many Evils it preſerves us from.</hi> 79</item>
               <item>CHAP. VII. <hi>The Suitableneſs of Humility to the Mind of Chriſt.</hi> 93</item>
               <item>CHAP. VIII. <hi>How Humility is to be expreſs'd, as by ſerving the Honour of God.</hi> 112</item>
               <item>CHAP. IX. <hi>How Humility is to be expreſs'd, by not making our own Eſteem the End of our Actions.</hi> 134</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:106212:3"/>
               <item> CHAP. X. <hi>How Humility is to be expreſs'd, by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging our Faults.</hi> 144</item>
               <item>CHAP. XI. <hi>How Humility is to be expreſs'd by doing all good Offices, tho' ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mean, and by ſubmiſſion to our Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours.</hi> 151</item>
               <item>CHAP. XII. <hi>How Humility is to be expreſs'd, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contented with ſuch things as we have.</hi> 166</item>
               <item>CHAP. XIII. <hi>How Humility is to be expreſs'd, by keeping an Even Temper in a State of Proſperity.</hi> 179</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Concluſion.</hi> 189</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:106212:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106212:4"/>
            <head>THE INTRODUCTION.</head>
            <p>I AM now entring upon the Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of a Vertue, which is in a manner proper and peculiar to the Chriſtian Religion: 'Tis called
<hi>Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility,</hi> or <hi>Lowlineſs of Heart.</hi> A Vertue to which even the wiſeſt of the old <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gans</hi> were for the moſt part ſtrangers: For, though they diſcourſed well againſt Pride, and of the Unreaſonableneſs and Folly of it; yet were they to ſeek, as to the Notion and Nature, and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as to the Practice of Humility. In <hi>fact</hi> they were generally Proud; only ſome of them were more addicted to that Vice, than others were: As 'twas ſaid of <hi>Diogenes,</hi> when he went into
<hi>Plato</hi>'s fine Houſe, and with rudeneſs and inſolence trod upon his rich Carpets; <hi>That he tram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled upon</hi> Plato'<hi>s Pride, and yet himſelf was much the proudeſt of the two.</hi> Theſe Men ſpake many good things of Sobriety, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, and moderation of Mind; and of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106212:5"/> the government of Mens Deſires; which may be applied to this Vertue by way of accomodation; but I do not find that they hit rightly upon this moſt amiable perfection, Humility. So far from it, that they uſed thoſe words in a bad Sence, which both in the <hi>Greek</hi> and
<hi>Latin</hi> Languages ſignifie an humble Heart: They meant by thoſe expreſſions, an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject Mind, weakneſs and littleneſs of Spirit, Puſillanimity; a ſervile, ſlaviſh and cowardly Diſpoſition; a degenerous and mean Temper; a low, ſordid Spirit that ſinks preſently, when a Man meets with any Calamity or Diſappointment; a pitiful, ſneaking Mind, that upon any Diſcouragements makes a Man to Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatize from himſelf; to fall from his Conſtancy, and behave himſelf after ſuch a poor manner, as unbecommeth a wiſe Man. Theſe are wrong Notions of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility; and thoſe Philoſophers expreſs'd their Notions by words that are too good for them; but the reaſon was, becauſe they did not well underſtand the Vertue it ſelf; and, perhaps, were not very willing to underſtand it; becauſe they themſelves were guilty of an epidemical Vice to which it ſtands in direct oppoſition. The Lord Jeſus, who brought Life and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality to light, did in his own Perſon <pb n="3" facs="tcp:106212:5"/> give the World a moſt lively Idea of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility; and hath made the Practice of it the diſtinguiſhing Mark of his own true Diſciples: So that he is none of his, who has not, as he had, an humble Mind: He may be a Philoſopher, but he cannot be a Chriſtian. To this purpoſe ſome learned Criticks have obſerved out of that place, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 5. where the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle bids us to <hi>be cloathed with humility,</hi> that the <hi>Greek</hi> word (which we render <hi>cloathed</hi>) ſignifies a ſervile Habit, a ſhort little Garment, white but very courſe, that the meaneſt Servants were formerly wont to wear about their Shoulders, as a particular token of their poor and low Condition; a mark of their Servitude, like a Badge or a Livery, to diſtinguiſh them from others. Thus the Alluſion is very elegant, and the Sence plain, <hi>viz.</hi> That Humility is the peculiar Note of Chriſt's Servants; a far better Ornament than a Philoſopher's Pall, under which a faſtidious Mind was wont to lurk; the true Livery of a Chriſtian indeed; the Badge of thoſe that belong to the Lord Jeſus, how deſpicable ſoever it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to the Men of this World; the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhing Mark of ſuch as ſerve him, who took upon himſelf the form of a Servant; and came into the World, not <pb n="4" facs="tcp:106212:6"/> to be miniſtred unto, but to miniſter even his Heart Blood for the Life of the World.</p>
            <p>In diſcourſing upon this admirable Chriſtian Vertue, I ſhall obſerve my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer plain Method; and conſider with what brevity I can conveniently, theſe Three things as General Heads of the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Diſcourſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. Wherein the true Nature of Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity doth conſiſt.</item>
               <item>II. What Motives and Arguments there are to inforce the Practice of it.</item>
               <item>III. After what Manner and Way we are to expreſs it.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:106212:6"/>
            <head>A Practical Diſcourſe UPON HUMILITY.</head>
            <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Of the Nature of Humility.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>FIRST as touching the true Nature of Humility. It is, in ſhort, a modeſt and ſlender Opinion of a Man's own ſelf, whatever his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowments or his Circumſtances are. An <hi>Opinion,</hi> I ſay; firſt, becauſe the proper Seat of Humility is in the Mind. A low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Heart, an humble Soul; that is the thing which God values. He looketh not, as we poor Creatures do, at things outward: He judgeth not of Men ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to appearance; by dejected <pb n="6" facs="tcp:106212:7"/> Countenances; by lugubrious Looks; by a fordid or homely Dreſs; no, nor by thoſe ſemblances of Humility which ſome expreſs, when they call themſelves the greateſt of Sinners, the vileſt People, and by a great many other hard Names, which they will not endure their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to give them. For all theſe exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior ſemblances and ſhews of Humility may very eaſily conſiſt with a conceited and proud Mind. A
<hi>Lucifer</hi> may be hid under ſuch diſguiſes. All this may be nothing but a ſort of Oſtentation; an art of gaining Eſteem and Applauſe; the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of Pride, and a means of ſerving the Ends of it; the profeſſions and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malities of profligate Hypocrites. The hidden Man of the Heart is the true Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament: Humility is that of the Spirit, the <hi>caſting down of imaginations, and of every high thing that exalteth it ſelf againſt God, and the bringing into captivity every thought to the obedience of Chriſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 10. 5. Pride is properly an elation of the Mind, an high and lofty Conceit; the Sin of the Devil, and the Original Cauſe of thoſe Miſchiefs which have made the World miſerable, ſince the Devil in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected our firſt Parents with the Diſeaſe: And the office of this Vertue, Humility, is to cure and clear all our Minds from <pb n="7" facs="tcp:106212:7"/> the Contagion; to bring us by Methods of Revulſion to a right Opinion of our own ſelves; and to lay us low in our own Thoughts, under a due ſenſe of what we really are.</p>
            <p>THIS Opinion of our ſelves therefore muſt be, Secondly, very modeſt and ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: For it muſt needs be very mean, if it be a due eſtimation of our ſelves; no more than what is juſt and proportiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to our true value; exactly according to our intrinſick worth, as we ſhall ſee hereafter, when we come to conſider what little reaſon any Man in the World hath to be proud. <hi>I ſay, through the grace given unto me, to every man that is among you, not to think of himſelf more highly than he ought to think, but to think ſoberly according as God hath dealt to every man the meaſure of faith,</hi> Rom. 12. 13. Nothing hinders but that a Man may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem himſelf; provided, that his thoughts be fair and equal; that he eſteem him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf juſt as he is, and juſt as he hath of his own. The ſin is when he rates himſelf above his real Dignity; when he over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valueth his Deſerts; when he thinks more, and higher, and greater things of himſelf than he ought. For ſo every proud Man doth: He inhaunceth his own
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106212:8"/> Price: He raiſeth himſelf beyond the true Standard: His Pride and Vanity, his Folly and Sin lie in his overweening Conceit; in pretending to Excellencies which he hath not, and to higher things than he really deſerves: In belying him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf after a moſt hateful manner: In fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſying and boaſting himſelf to be ſome Body; in giving out, and ſetting himſelf off, like <hi>Simon</hi> the Sorcerer, to be ſome great thing, when he is nothing at all; nay, when he is worſe than nothing, a miſerable fooliſh and very wicked thing of a Man; much the more fooliſh for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Proud; and much the more miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and wicked for being like the Devil. I ſay therefore to every Man among you, <hi>not to think of himſelf more highly than he ought to think; but to think ſoberly;</hi> that is, according to the meaſures of Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; to think ſo as to be modeſt; not to ſet up any airy and high-flown Conceits, but to furl their Sails, to contract their Thoughts, and to ſhrink them within their due limits and ſcantling.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith St.
<hi>Chryſoſtom;</hi> the Apoſtle here calls Humility by the name of
<hi>Sobriety:</hi> And he gives us the Etymology of the word too, to ſhew that proud Men have <pb n="9" facs="tcp:106212:8"/> quite loſt their ſober Senſes, if ever they had any. They are no longer Men of ſound Underſtandings and Judgment, but things beſide themſelves; mere toys and phantaſtical Creatures, with their Heads all puff'd up, as if they had nothing in them but Bladders and Bubbles. There are divers overweening Conceits, which plainly argue all proud People to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried away with Wind and Vapours; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that the things they value them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon came not altogether from God; but chiefly, if not ſolely, from themſelves, and are the effects of their own Wit and Induſtry: or, if from God, yet that they were beſtowed as a juſt Reward of their ſingular Merits and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: That their Portion is much grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than other Mens: That they know much better than others what to do with their Acquiſitions: That in all, or in moſt reſpects, they are more excellent than their Neighbours, and that hardly any thing can be too much for them, if they can but get it. And what is all this but wild Imagination? Pride without any bottom? Folly which they themſelves could not but be aſham'd of, did they ſeriouſly and ſoberly conſider, from what Hand every Man of us receives his All; and for what purpoſes; that all of <pb n="10" facs="tcp:106212:9"/> us are but Stewards in our ſeveral Places and Vocations: And that the things com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to our Truſt, are no other than Debts and Burthens; things we owe, and things we are accountable for; and things which Men of reaſon will think as impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for them to value themſelves upon, as it is to be proud of Incumbrances or Poverty.</p>
            <p>THEREFORE, to bring our hearts down to a true level, we muſt be very careful to baniſh out of our Minds all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due and flattering Opinions of our own worth, and to reduce our ſelves to <hi>David</hi>'s temper,
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 131. <hi>Lord, I am not high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded: I have no proud looks: I do not exerciſe my ſelf in great matters, which are too high for me; but I refrain my Soul and keep it low; like as a Child that is weaned from his Mother; yea, my Soul is even as a weaned Child.</hi> Which puts me in mind of the method our bleſſed Saviour uſed with his Diſciples, when they diſputed among themſelves, which of them ſhould be the greateſt. Some of them would have been his chief Favourites, the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Officers in that glorious Kingdom, upon Earth, which they expected he would one day ſet up. To cure this their ambitious Humour, he took up a little <pb n="11" facs="tcp:106212:9"/> Child in his Arms, and propos'd the Child to them as an emblem of Humility; with this ſolemn declaration, that very nearly concerns us all, <hi>Except ye be converted, and become as little Children, ye ſhall not enter into the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> Mat. 18. 3, 4.
<q rend="inline margSglQuotes">Men die (ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi>) in a worſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition than they were born in; becauſe Nature did not bring us out of the Womb with that Pride, and Vanity, and Ambition of mind, which afterwards becomes the reproach of Manhood, and of our riper Years.</q> Though indeed the ſeeds of theſe Vices be in us naturally, yet 'tis our own fault that they grow up with us; and the deſign of Chriſt's Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is, to bring our Souls to an Infant ſtate of Innocence and Humility, that we may go out of the World as well (at leaſt) as we came into it; Children the ſecond time; Children as to all Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, as to all guile, as to all airy and bloating conceits of our own excellencies. We can never be truly humble as we ſhould, and as we muſt be, in order to our entrance into the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, till we leave exalting of our ſelves above meaſure. Pride, we may be ſure will keep us out of God's Preſence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it would not ſuffer Angels them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſtay in it. Their original Sin <pb n="12" facs="tcp:106212:10"/> conſiſted, in admiring exceſſively the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Perfections of their Nature, and the Glory of their State. Hence follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a ſtate of Envy at the more eminent Condition of thoſe Orders of Angels that were placed above them: This grew into direct Hoſtility againſt them, and againſt God himſelf, the Maker and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſer of them all. This Hoſtility in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed into open Apoſtaſie; and all ended by God's juſt Judgment in their final and eternal Damnation, and ſo of Glorious Angels they became Helliſh De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils.</p>
            <p>SINCE which time, their ſole buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs hath been to propagate their Envy and Malice, and Apoſtaſie from the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of us all; and ſo to involve Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind under the ſame Condemnation: But their chief Artifice, and that which by their own ſad Experience they have found to be the ſureſt way, is to accele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate our ruine by propagating their Pride; that is, loftineſs of Opinion, and haughtineſs of Heart, the firſt Sin that ever was in Heaven; and the firſt Sin thoſe Devils brought upon the Earth. So they made our firſt Parents believe, that they ſhould <hi>be as Gods, knowing good and evil,</hi> Gen. 3. 5. And the ſame Sin
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106212:10"/> which coſt thoſe Angels their Celeſtial Paradiſe, did preſently coſt our Parents and Us the Earthly one. Ambition and ſelf-conceit began the War between God and his Creatures: It was made the firſt Example of God's Vengeance, and 'tis that which God will purſue with Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to all Eternity. <hi>He reſiſteth the proud, but giveth grace to the humble,</hi> James 4. 6. This then is true Humility, and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom alſo, not to think our ſelves to be better or greater than we are, but to rate our ſelves according to our juſt value; which cannot but be very low, if we would but inquire into our ſelves im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially. But this is one great fault, and the cauſe of a great many more, that every Man is apt to overlook himſelf, while he prieth narrowly into the ſtate of others: Whereas, did we duly apply our Hearts to find out and underſtand our own Condition, our Follies, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merits, the mere Vanity of Pride would in a little time make the Sin a ridicule, and dethrone its dominion, by expoſing it to contempt and ſcorn. Its credit and prevalency proceeds from our neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects at home, becauſe we are ſuch ſtrangers to our own ſelves; with whom we ſhould have the cloſeſt, and might have the ſafeſt intimacy. We ſtill take it for <pb n="14" facs="tcp:106212:11"/> granted, That we really are, what we willingly believe our ſelves to be. Ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we look not into our ſtate at all, or elſe take a very tranſient and falſe view; paſſing over the diſcovery of thoſe flaws and humbling Idea's, which ſhould have been the principal Object; and perhaps fearing too, leſt upon a ſtrict Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we ſhould ſee ſomething to be aſham'd of. By this means we ſcarcely judge ſo much as by appearance; but bring our ſelves into a miſtaken Reputation with our own over-credulous Hearts; and go on in the Error, till we are paſt making Righteous Judgment, and are quite out of the reach of Self-condemnation.</p>
            <p>OUR firſt care therefore muſt be, to have as perfect a knowledge as we can of our ſelves, what we are indeed, and what we deſerve upon a true eſtimate: For till the Account be juſt which we take, it will be impoſſible for us to be deliver'd from that opiniatry, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitedneſs of Mind, which is as different a thing from true Humility, as that <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee</hi> was from the poor <hi>Publican,</hi> Luke 18. His Prayer was all Heraldry, and Oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, while the other ſtanding at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance would not ſo much as lift up his Eyes to Heaven, but ſmote upon his <pb n="15" facs="tcp:106212:11"/> Breaſt, ſaying, <hi>God be merciful to me a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: This man,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>went down to his houſe juſtified, rather than the other: For every one that exalteth himſelf, ſhall be abaſed; and he that humbleth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſhall be exalted,</hi> verſe 14.</p>
            <p>2. HAVING thus briefly ſhewed wherein the Nature of Humility doth conſiſt, <hi>viz.</hi> In a modeſt and ſlender Opinion of ones own ſelf; I proceed now, according to the Method propoſed, to conſider the Motives which render this great Chriſtian Vertue practical, and the Arguments which ſerve to inforce the practice of it.</p>
            <p>WHERE divers things will fall under our Meditations; which I ſhall endeavour to put together into a little room; but muſt not wholly omit any of them: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſE the Vertue I now treat of, is of ſuch neceſſary and great Concernment, that there is no fear of ſaying too much; hardly indeed a poſſibility of ſaying e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, to recommend it to our Hearts.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:106212:12"/>
            <head>CHAP. II. <hi>The Lovelineſs of Humility.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. THE Native Beauty and Loveli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this Vertue; perhaps a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Rivalry of any other. This is one great reproach and infamy to Pride, That neither God nor Man can endure it. Seven things God hates after a more particular manner; as <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <hi>Prov.</hi> 6. <hi>A lying tongue; hands that ſhed innocent blood; a heart that deviſeth wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed imaginations; feet that be ſwift in run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to miſchief; a falſe witneſs that ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth lyes; him that ſoweth diſcord among brethren:</hi> But chiefly, and in the firſt place <hi>a proud Look,</hi> or
<hi>haughty Eyes.</hi> And one main reaſon is, becauſe where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Diſcord is ſown, 'tis this medling Vice that finds the Seed, prepares the Soil, and hath an Eye upon the Harveſt. <hi>Only by pride cometh contention,</hi> Prov.
13. 10. 'Tis the only prolifick, natural Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which is continually in travail with that Evil, which is ſo hateful to the God of Love and Peace. For theſe baſe Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, and for the natural turpitude of <pb n="17" facs="tcp:106212:12"/> the Vice it ſelf, it is of all others the moſt hateful to Mankind alſo: So that though in many caſes People generally love communion and ſociety in Sin; yet in this they abhor it; for proud Wretches are deteſted by all; and moſt of all by thoſe who are as proud as they; till the emulation riſeth like that between <hi>Caeſar</hi> and <hi>Pompey;</hi> the one could not indure a Superior, nor the other an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual. All this while Humility carrieth irreſiſtable Charms with it. It is a moſt graceful Vertue, that wins the Eſteem and Affections of every beholder; not excepting the haughty Perſon himſelf. As it is the moſt Chriſtian, ſo it is the moſt becoming Vertue to ſet any one off; and we may deſervedly give it the ſame Character (at leaſt) which St. <hi>Peter</hi> gives <hi>of a meek and quiet ſpirit; an orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of great price,</hi> 1 Pet. 3. 4. An hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Spirit, naturally quickens us to thoſe Actions which affect Men with Pleaſure: It doth not things that are harſh or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obliging: It is not capricious, or ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful: It lieth not upon the catch: It ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not unjuſt or ſevere conſtructions: It is not an Enemy to Charity or Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, nor to any the moſt homely Offices that are good: It is no diſturber of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Peace: It is not void of Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <pb n="18" facs="tcp:106212:13"/> or Compaſſion: It needs no Lure, but the Love of God and Man to make it ſtoop: It reſents not every Peccadillo, nor magnifies Infirmities beyond their due meaſure; much leſs doth it falſifie for Reputation or Intereſt ſake: It is not rough, nor is it wont to threaten, or oppreſs, or to ſcare People after an inſolent manner, like that weak and haughty Prince, <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> 1
<hi>Kings</hi> 12. where we ſee a remarkable inſtance of a proud Temper, and ſuch an account of the End and Folly of it, as, I think, is hardly to be parallell'd in the whole Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; unleſs it be the Story of
<hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar</hi>'s being turned out among the Beaſts.
<hi>Rehoboam</hi> coming young to the Throne of his Father <hi>Solomon,</hi> all <hi>Iſrael</hi> beſought him, in ſome meaſure, to eaſe them of their former Burdens: And his wiſeſt and honeſteſt Counſellors adviſed him to treat the People after a kind, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, and reſpectful manner, as the only ſure way of preſerving their Affections. <hi>If,</hi> ſaid they, <hi>thou wilt be a ſervant unto this people this day, and wilt ſerve them, and anſwer them, and ſpeak good words to them, then they will be thy ſervants for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</hi> But this method pleaſed not
<hi>Reho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam:</hi> He was willing rather to hearken to thoſe raw Counſellors, who knowing <pb n="19" facs="tcp:106212:13"/> his rough and imperious Diſpoſition, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed him according to his own Mind; though it was to the ruine of his Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. So he uſed the People with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and Menaces, frightning them with an arrogant Anſwer, That his <hi>little finger ſhould be thicker</hi> (or heavier) <hi>than his father's loins;</hi> that he would
<hi>add to their yoke;</hi> and that whereas his Father had chaſtiſed them with Whips, he himſelf would chaſtiſe them with Scorpions. And what did this turn to in the end? Why, the People could not bear his Pride and Inſolence, and threatnings of Oppreſſion. It preſently alienated their Minds; and that of courſe brought on an open de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection from him. <hi>What portion,</hi> ſaid they, <hi>have we in David? Neither have we inheritance in the ſon of Jeſſe: to your tents, O Iſrael: now ſee to thine own houſe, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid.</hi> And <hi>ſo Iſrael departed unto their tents,</hi> and rebelled, all but the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> againſt the Houſe of
<hi>David,</hi> and ſet up <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> a King of their own. I will not diſpute here about the Juſtice or Injuſtice of this act of theirs. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings were Natural enough (which is all I would obſerve from the Story) becauſe nothing doth more naturally and powerfully tend to ſowre Mens Minds, to alienate their Affections, and <pb n="20" facs="tcp:106212:14"/> to eſtrange their Hearts, than Pride doth.</p>
            <p>ON the other hand; every Body loves an humble Perſon, becauſe Humility is naturally amiable; and the more amia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, becauſe it is attended with many ſuch other Graces, as win and endear the Hearts of all Mankind, with a power that is uncontroulable, and attractive, like the faculty of a Magnet. Where true Humility is, there is Meekneſs, Charity, Candour, Affability, Courteſie, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, a ſerene Brow, kind Intreatings, and the like; nor is it poſſible but ſuch grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Endowments muſt meet with kind entertainment, and be beloved every where.</p>
            <p>WHEN <hi>Ageſilaus</hi> of <hi>Lacedaemon,</hi> who was ſo eſteemed for his great Wiſdom, was deſired to give his Opinion how a Man ſhould do to get all Peoples Love; he told <hi>Socrates, That the ſureſt way would be, to ſpeak well, and to do better.</hi> And this is one part of an humble Man's bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs; to give others the kindeſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters he is able, and to do them all the Good he can: And ſuch offices, offices of Love, return into his own Boſom; he receives himſelf, as a Reward of them,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106212:14"/> a certain retaliation of good Nature; like the skilful Apothecary that prepares for others precious Ointments and Aro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks, which in the very preparing per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume and enrich his own Shop.</p>
            <p>BEFORE <hi>Honour is Humility,</hi> ſaith <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> Prov. 15. 33. Humility is the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; ready way to it. Though a good Name be far from being his Aim or End, yet it will be an humble Man's Lot, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he will or no; and, notwithſtanding his own Deſires, or Endeavours to the contrary, he becomes Popular for the beſt reaſons. For all Mankind deſire to be well uſed: It is a Principle never to be rooted out of humane Nature; and when they find theſe their innocent Appetites anſwered, they cannot but love and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the Hand that dealeth ſo well with them: It is as Natural as it is to deteſt the thick and heavy Finger that holds out nothing but
<hi>Whips and Scorpions,</hi> as <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoboam</hi>'s did.</p>
            <p>WERE there then nothing elſe to be conſidered, the Rules of Wiſdom and Prudence are ſtrong Arguments to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man to be of an humble Mind; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it carrieth with it ſuch a Ruling Power, as is beyond all the Grandeur in <pb n="22" facs="tcp:106212:15"/> the World; which may keep People in ſome little awe, and that for a little time, but cannot command their Affections. There is indeed an outward ſtate, that is neceſſary to preſerve Order and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the World; an external Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Splendor, ſuitable to that high Rank and Quality wherein it pleaſeth God to place ſome far above others. Nor is this inconſiſtent with Lowlineſs of Mind: For the more and greater God's Bleſſings are, the deeper ſhould the ſenſe of them be; and, God be thanked, many times is; ſo that few, if any, are of more hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Minds, than ſome whom the Divine Providence hath dignified with the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Honours. In the midſt of Pomp they can conſider what infirm Pedeſtals they ſtand on; nor are they ſo eaſily ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled of their Vertues, as thoſe whoſe ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did Birth, and illiberal Education, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth them the more to the Devils Snares. Few ſuch, God knows, keep the Humility of <hi>Job,</hi> after they are once rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from the Dunghill. But where ever this Grace grows, whether in the more barren, or in the richeſt Soil, it is always lovely to the Eye; and the more Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful, becauſe it reſembles him, who is ſtiled, <hi>the Lily of the Valley,</hi> Cant. 2. 1. We ſhould all learn of him, who was <pb n="23" facs="tcp:106212:15"/> lowly in Heart; who gained as many Admirers by his Humility, as by his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Miracles; and whoſe Example is a ſufficient Comment upon his Directions, That to ſit down in the loweſt Room is the beſt for us, the ready way to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced higher, and to have <hi>worſhip in the preſence of all,</hi> Luke 14. 10.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. III. <hi>The Reaſonableneſs of Humility.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="2">2. I CONFESS this is comparatively a very low Conſideration; becauſe we muſt not ſeek for Honour of Men, no more than the Lord Jeſus did; nor may we make uſe of Vertue, (eſpecially the Vertue of Humility) as an Art for it. Let us therefore in the Second place conſider the great Reaſonableneſs of this Matter; which will not only invite, but oblige us to the Practice of it.</p>
            <p>NOW here we ſhould conſider, whence we came, what we are, and what we have,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:106212:16"/> FIRST we ſhould reflect upon our Originals; becauſe People are apt to be aſhamed of their baſe beginnings; like the haughty <hi>Simon</hi> in <hi>Lucian,</hi> who being advanced to Honours, from a very mean, obſcure Condition, pull'd down the Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage which had been the place of his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, that Paſſengers might not point to it and ſay,
<hi>Here was Great</hi> Simon <hi>born.</hi> The Son of God, by dignifying a Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, hath indeed taken away all ſuch ſhame from us: But yet he left us e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, when he ſaid, <hi>Before Abraham was I am.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE Father of the Faithful was once nothing. And the production of every one of us, was out of nothing. The Being we have, we are beholding for it to the Power of God, who of his own Pleaſure raiſed us out of Inanity, that our whole Life might be a ſtate of Low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, the better to diſpoſe us for entire Obedience, Submiſſion, and Reſignation of our Selves to his Divine Will.</p>
            <p>The Fleſh we conſiſt of, and pamper ſo, what is it but
<hi>next</hi> to nothing? A Structure of Clay and Rottenneſs, a Lump provided for Worms; an heap of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, <pb n="25" facs="tcp:106212:16"/> that yields nothing but a noi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Atmoſphere, which we are fain to correct with Spices and Odours, that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry gathers out of the Fields, and are brought us from far by long and charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Adventures?</p>
            <p>AS vile and deſpicable things as we are, the God of Power vouchſafeth to ſupport us: We daily depend on him; and by his Law all his
<hi>Creatures,</hi> are forced to lend us their helping hands, each doing its part for us, according to its Kind and Capacities, and all at the ſame time upbraiding us with our depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant and beggarly Condition. The Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens beſtow their Light upon us, and put us in mind of that great Obſcuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which wrapped us up in our Mother's Wombs. The Earth under our Feet, however we trample upon it, doth the kind office to afford us, firſt our Nurſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and at laſt our Lodging. The thin Air we breathe in, how ſoon do we drop to the Ground, like untimely Fruit, when it is ſhut out of our Noſtrils? The Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters help to quench our thirſt, as it helps the wild Aſſes, and other Beaſts of the Field, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 104. 11. Poor Animals and Vegetables of infinite ſorts, are fain to be the Proveditors and Guardians of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106212:17"/> our Life. Our Nakedneſs is hid by the contribution of dumb Creatures, whoſe Backs we are neceſſitated to ſtrip, that we may cover our <hi>own;</hi> and all this for the preſervation of that Body, which in its beſt ſtate is ſubject to variety of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes: And which, when Death and Rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenneſs hath ſeiz'd upon it; we our ſelves cannot endure the very ſight of. Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Creature is God's Almoner, to relieve and ſuccour us whilſt we live in this World: And when we are going out of it, we have nothing to depend on, but his infinite Mercies, <hi>in whom we now live, and move, and have our being,</hi> Acts 17. 28.</p>
            <p>LORD! what is Man? That poor, wretched, contemptible thing, Man? What is Man, that he ſhould ſwell and be bloated with a proud Opinion of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who can never retire into his own true ſelf, till, like a Snail that creeps in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to its Shell, he humbleth himſelf in Duſt and Aſhes?</p>
            <p>DUST we are; and to Duſt ſhall we all return, like the Beaſts that periſh. And, as for that nobler part of us, the <hi>Soul;</hi> tho' it be a Ray of Divinity, a Spirit endued with the Powers and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties of an Angel; yet, upon due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flectons, <pb n="27" facs="tcp:106212:17"/> it will find more and greater Reaſons for Humility, that may be drawn from within it ſelf, than it ſees by view<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing its poor and frail habitation.</p>
            <p>THERE are in every one of us two Prime Faculties, which are connatural to the Soul: A Faculty of knowing and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning, which is called the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> and a Faculty of Acting, a Power of Chuſing or Refuſing, which is called the <hi>Will:</hi> And each of theſe Powers doth miniſter to us many humbling Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations.</p>
            <p n="1">1. FIRST: For the Intellectual Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or Underſtanding. Tho' Knowledge be a very excellent Endowment, that which People generally covet with gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs, and are too apt to value them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon; yet <hi>in much wiſdom is much grief; and he that increaſeth knowledge, increaſeth ſorrow,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> Eccl. 1. 18. And yet, God was pleaſed of his Bounty, to give <hi>Him</hi> an extraordinary Portion;
<hi>exceeding much underſtanding and large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of heart, even as the ſand that is on the ſea-ſhoar:</hi> His <hi>wiſdom excelled the wiſdom of all the children of the eaſt-country, and all the wiſdom of Egypt: For he was wiſer than all men,</hi> ſaith the Scripture, 1
<hi>King.</hi> 4. <pb n="28" facs="tcp:106212:18"/> It is not without great toil and trouble of Mind that <hi>we</hi> get the Knowledge we have at laſt; and even
<hi>that</hi> is very little; conſiderable, only becauſe it coſteth us dear; nothing indeed, in compariſon of that infinite number of things Natural, Moral, and Divine, which we are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of. The further we ſearch, the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtill we are to ſeek, and the more ſenſible of our great wants. And that which we pretend to be Maſters of, is rather conjecture than certainty, unleſs it be bottom'd upon Divine Revelation. Nor are our few Notions without a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Miſtakes, and a great many Doubts and Difficulties, which diſquiet the Mind, becauſe we are not able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve them. So that after many Years ſtudy and travel, we come juſt thus far, to know enough to make us very hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p n="2">2. AS for the other Faculty of the Soul, which is the Principle of Action; we find there ſo much Guilt, as we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſufficiently humbled for all the days of our Life. For, it is the
<hi>Will</hi> that committeth Sins; 'tis this Faculty that chuſeth and conſenteth to a ſinful Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that makes it our Crime. The Underſtanding dictates and propoſes the <pb n="29" facs="tcp:106212:18"/> thing; but ſtill it is in the Power of the Will, whether to do it, or no: And the more the Will conſents to the Sin, the more ſinful it is always. No Man can be forced to do any evil thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Will, if he be obſtinate. There may be Allurements, and ſtrong Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but there can be no Compulſion. All Conſent and Compliance is from with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in; and for that reaſon wicked People are juſtly liable to Puniſhment, becauſe they chuſe to do that, which they might avoid: They <hi>tranſgreſs without cauſe,</hi> as the Expreſſion is, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 25. 3. Now, how can any Man think of his Sins, and be proud? Eſpecially ſince Pride is the moſt accumulative Sin of all, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves Hell the more, becauſe it is after a peculiar manner the very Devil's Sin? 'Tis ſtrange that any one ſhould value himſelf for being in a ſtate of Damnation: And yet that is the ſtate every wicked Man is in, without true Repentance, or Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Life; Sins acted againſt an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Being, muſt needs be of infinite demerit; and, conſequently, obnoxious to infinite Puniſhment. Becauſe there is a God, there muſt be an Hell too, for God to puniſh wicked People in ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly: And is it poſſible for us to be truly ſenſible of this, and at the ſame <pb n="30" facs="tcp:106212:19"/> time not to be caſt down under the Sence of our ſad Deſervings; and of that moſt miſerable Condition, which nothing can ſave us from but the mere Mercy of God? Such Reflections as theſe, could not chuſe but be very humbling, if vain Men would not think it beneath their Spirits to admit and entertain them. It is both the Folly and Wickedneſs of haughty People, that they baniſh from them Thoughts of this Nature, and mind on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly trifles and things imaginary; quite over-looking thoſe Crimes, which (if at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentively conſider'd) would make them <hi>abhor themſelves, and repent in duſt and aſhes,</hi> as <hi>Job</hi> ſpake, Job 42. 6. People who really believe that they deſerve eternal Damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and that without God's infinite Clemency they ſhall receive it, can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be ſo very inconſiſtent with themſelves, as to ſwell with a vain Conceit of any <hi>other</hi> Merits. An evil Conſcience, and a true Senſe of Guilt, is enough to lay the loftieſt Spirits low. And this is one reaſon for which Pride is concluded, by all conſiderate Men, to be ſuch a
<hi>fooliſh Vice;</hi> Becauſe haughty People value themſelves upon things which are not valuable, not conſidering what they <hi>juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> deſerve; but throwing aſide many me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholy. Thoughts, which are in truth
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106212:19"/> moſt proper and fit for Criminals. The only thing worth our eſteem is <hi>Vertue;</hi> or, that gracious diſpoſition of Soul, whereby <hi>the righteous is</hi> (indeed) <hi>more excellent than his neighbour,</hi> Prov. 12. 26. Thoſe Moral Habits which are apt to cleanſe us from all filthineſs of Fleſh and Spirit, have an intrinſick Dignity in them. For they are noble Perfections of our Nature, and ſuch reſemblances of the Divine Being, as <hi>are in the ſight of God himſelf of great price,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 4. But yet even theſe excellent Endowments are arguments for our Humility; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are not the Productions of Nature, but the Fruits and Effects of the Holy Spirit's Operation. It is by his free and gracious Energy, that we are made the Children of Grace, and are tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in the renewing of our Minds. Without Chriſt's aſſiſtance, by the Holy Spirit, <hi>we can do nothing,</hi> John 15. 5.
<hi>It is he that worketh in us, both to will, and to do of his own good pleaſure,</hi> Phil. 2. 13. Upon this account our Spiritual Graces are reaſons for our Thankfulneſs; but not for our Pride; becauſe we ſtand in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted to the mere Goodneſs and Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of God for them. <hi>Who maketh thee to differ from another?</hi> (ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle,) <hi>or what haſt thou that thou didſt not <pb n="32" facs="tcp:106212:20"/> receive? Now if thou didſt receive it, why doſt thou glory, as though thou hadſt not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 7. Debtors are not wont to be proud of the Obligations and Bonds they are forced to lie under. Poverty carrieth ſuch ſhame with it, as ſerves to debaſe Men, when hardly any thing elſe will. And though <hi>God giveth to all men liberally and upbraideth not,</hi> Jam. 1. 5. yet the Senſe of our neceſſitous and miſerable condition by Nature, and of our dependance upon God for the mend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our Fortunes, is a very powerful Motive to humble all of us; eſpecially before that infinite Being, to whoſe Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Goodneſs we owe all that we have, and all that we are.</p>
            <p>THE ancient Moraliſts. among the Heathen thought it a Fundamental Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of all Vertue, for a Man to know and underſtand himſelf rightly. I am ſure it is the Principle and Source of this Vertue, Humility. For there is very lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle (if any thing) in us, or about us, but what teacheth us to deſpiſe our ſelves: And it is for want of due and juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection, that People are great in their own Eyes. <hi>I know that in me, (that is in my fleſh) there dwelleth no good thing,</hi> ſaith St.
<hi>Paul,</hi> in the Perſon of an unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate <pb n="33" facs="tcp:106212:20"/> Man,
<hi>Rom.</hi> 7. 18. There is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a vile Body, a ſinful Soul, a corrupt Mind, a vain Imagination: There is a weak, mortal, neceſſitous Nature: There is fooliſhneſs, and wretchedneſs in great variety: There is enough and abundance of <hi>ſuch</hi> things, for him to boaſt of, if it be worth his boaſting, (ſuch glorying would be in One's ſhame.) And, as for thoſe bleſſed Principles of Vertue, which by the ſweet and kindly inſinuations of Chriſt's Spirit, the Soul of every regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Perſon is endow'd with; they are ſo many borrowed Talents, for which the holieſt Man living ſtands beholding to our great Creditor, the Lord of all. And tho' we ought to rejoyce, that God is pleas'd to communicate his Riches to us, yet conſidering that they are precarious Loans, for the obtaining whereof our chief bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs was to beg, and receive with all Humility; we have as little reaſon to be proud of them, as a ſervile Steward hath of a Truſt for which he muſt give a ſtrict Account.</p>
            <p>IF the things I have mention'd ſerve to keep us from all Aſſumings, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of thoſe <hi>outward</hi> Matters, which the Scripture calls <hi>the things, and the faſhion of the world,</hi> muſt needs help <pb n="34" facs="tcp:106212:21"/> to take down our Minds the more ſtill. For, tho' the Children of this World are wont to mind theſe things moſt, and are apt to be elated moſt of all by them, yet there is hardly a plainer Argument than this is, of the great Weakneſs of humane Nature, and of the Folly it is ſubject to; that Men are ſo ſwollen in their Minds, becauſe their temporal Fortunes are bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ky, becauſe they are Richer and Greater than others: I mean, as ſome count Riches and Greatneſs, who ſpeak the Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of the World, and conſider not what it is to be Rich and Great
<hi>indeed.</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las! theſe external Matters are of a very mean, trifling, and contemptible Nature, phantaſm and colour only; like the Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the
<hi>Athenian</hi> Bird, which help to give it face, but do not make it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or weightier than a Bird of a plainer Plume. Beſides, <hi>riches</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>certainly make themſelves wings, they flee away as an Eagle towards heaven,</hi> Prov. 23. 5. And this they do by the juſt Judgment of God in Heaven; becauſe Men <hi>ſet their Eyes on that which is not, and ſet others at nought for that which is but vanity.</hi> When they forget God and themſelves after this manner, it is a very Righteous thing for the Judge of all the Earth, to humble them, by making
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:106212:21"/> the Neſt that was ſet on high empty; and by leaving it to the mercy of the Fire; or, of the Extortioner, which in effect is the ſame thing. Thirdly, tho' theſe external Fortunes ſtay with us, and we with them, yet 'tis moſt unreaſonable for our Hearts to be lifted up by the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of them, becauſe they are far from being an argument of God's Love to any. <hi>No man knoweth either love or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred by all that is before them,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> Eccl. 9. 1. That is, none can cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly tell by his preſent worldy Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, whether he be in God's Favour or no. For, ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> verſe 2. <hi>All things come alike to all; there is one event to the righteous, and to the wicked; to the good, and to the clean, and to the unclean; to him that ſacrificeth, and to him that ſacrificeth not; as is the good, ſo is the ſinner; and he that ſweareth, as he that feareth an oath.</hi> Which words yield us thus much; That, ſince this wretched World is not a place for us to receive our Rewards, generally Men ſhare alike, and without diſcrimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the Fortunes of the World. The Divine Providence ſcatters them promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcuouſly, and with an indifferent Hand; which plainly ſhews, that in God's Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count they are ſuch very inconſiderable things, that it is no matter how, or upon
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:106212:22"/> whom they are thrown away. But, Fourthly, if any thing may be concluded from the affluence of theſe poor tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Enjoyments, it is rather a ſad argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the great Danger the Men of this World are in, than a ſignification of God's Love to them. For all Mankind being God's Creatures, and having for that reaſon ſome ſort of Title and Right to his Providence, God is pleaſed to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribute the Glories and Felicities here below, as he ſends his Rain and Sun-ſhine, <hi>upon the evil as well as upon the good.</hi> Nay, becauſe evil Men can have no ſhare of the Felicities of a future ſtate, God doth uſually give them a more liberal allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of That which they count the great Happineſs of This. And hereby God ſhews the great Juſtice of his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, in making ſome ſort of equality in his Diſtributions, ſuch an equality as the Nature of the thing admits of; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all Men by this means take their reſpective turns in the ſeveral ſtates of Happineſs and Miſery; they have their reſpective ſhares, ſuitable to their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Conditions and Capacities. Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Wretches have their turn ſerved in this preſent ſtate; their Cup is fill'd here, ſuch a Cup as it is; and they muſt thank hemſelves that there is not a better laid <pb n="37" facs="tcp:106212:22"/> up in ſtore for them. <hi>They have their portion in this life,</hi> ſaith
<hi>David,</hi> Pſalm 17. 14. So in our Saviour's Parable of the rich Man, in
<hi>Luke</hi> 16. <hi>Abraham</hi> told that glorious Epicure, repreſented there to be in Hell; <hi>Son, remember that thou in thy life-time receivedſt thy good things, and likewiſe Lazarus</hi> (his) <hi>evil things,</hi> verſe 25. But obſerve what follows; <hi>Now Lazarus is comforted, and thou art tormented.</hi> It was but juſt, that both the one and the other ſhould have his Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and, ſince it is ſo ominous to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a large Portion in this World, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly none have greater reaſon to be humble than they,
<hi>whoſe bellies God filleth here with his hid treaſures,</hi> as the expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 17. 14. Such Treaſures as vain Wretches bury here in their Bowels, and in the Earth. But, laſtly, the indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent diſtribution of theſe outward temporal matters, is a very ſtrong argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a future Judgment, which will be according to the Rules of exact righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs. Becauſe in the preſent Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of Affairs, the greateſt Lot ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times falls to evil doers; and the Men of this World run away with the greateſt ſhare of its Wealth, Pleaſure and Honours; it is very rational to conclude, That there will be a day for an after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reckoning,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:106212:23"/> when all things ſhall be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſted, and all Manking ſhall receive ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to what they have done, whether it be good or evil. Then, we may be ſure, there will be no reſpect of Perſons; no diſtinction between rich and poor, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween high and low; for all muſt ſtand upon the ſame level, and the only dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference will be between the juſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt. And what a terrible warning is this to the greateſt Men on Earth, not to be high minded, but to fear; becauſe their neglecting thoſe opportunities they have of doing Good is more heinous, their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude much more ſcandalous, their evil Actions more viſible, their Examples more influential, their Injuſtice more hurtful, their Yokes more heavy, their Oppreſſions more intolerable; and, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently their Guilt, Condemnation and Torment will be much greater, than we may ſuppoſe thoſe to be capable of incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, who paſs through the World in a manner deſticute and naked, as they dropd into it. Of all People in the World, none have greater reaſon to be humble, than they who are in danger; nor are any in ſuch a dangerous conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as flouriſhing Wretches; ſuch as
<hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſpeake of, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 73. <hi>I was</hi> (ſaith he)
<hi>grieved at the fooliſh, when I ſaw them in <pb n="39" facs="tcp:106212:23"/> ſuch proſperity; for they are in no peril of death; but are luſty and ſtrong. They come in no miſfortune, like others; nor are they plagued, like other men.</hi> And this is the cauſe that they are ſo holden with Pride, and overwhelmed with Cruelty. <hi>Their eyes ſwell with fatneſs; and they do even what they luſt. Lo, theſe are the ungodly; theſe proſper in the world, and theſe have riches in poſſeſſion.</hi> 'Twere impoſſible for ſuch Men thus to ſwell in their Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, did they ſadly conſider <hi>David</hi>'s ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, (which we ſee verified every day,) <hi>O! how ſuddenly do they conſume, periſh, and come to a fearful end,</hi> verſe 18. <hi>Haman</hi> hanged after all his Greatneſs and Inſolence, <hi>Eſther</hi> 7. The preſuming Fool ſnatch'd away while he was build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his capacious Barns, to ſtow up his many years Wealth in, <hi>Luke</hi> 12. The rich Man, I ſpoke of before, caſt out of his Purple and fine Linen into Hell tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, <hi>Luke</hi> 16. <hi>Herod</hi> ſmitten ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on his Throne, and in his Royal Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, <hi>Acts</hi>
12. Theſe, and infinite Inſtances more, ſhew what Dangers the loftieſt Men are ſurrounded with, and what ſlip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery Ground they ſtand on, how great ſoever their Preſumptions are, that they ſhall never be moved.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:106212:24"/> AND, if the common danger of ruine in this World, be a reaſon to humble the haughtieſt Spirits, the moſt aſſuming and confident Minds, certainly the proſpect of a final Judgment, and an irrevocable doom to everlaſting and infinite Miſery, muſt (if duly entertained) caſt ſuch a damp upon the vain Thoughts of Men, <hi>as is enough to ſtain the pride of all glory,</hi> as the Prophet ſpeaks,
<hi>Iſaiah</hi> 23. 9.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>The Uſefulneſs of Humility, in reſpect of the Peace of Mind it brings.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Reaſonableneſs of Humility be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus conſidered, the next thing that falls under our Meditations, and ſerves to make it practical, is the great Uſefulneſs of this Vertue, during our paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage through this vain, deceitful World. Now there are many great Advantages which attend the ſincere and conſtant Practice of this Vertue: And more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially theſe Three:</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:106212:24"/>
               <item> I. AN humble Mind brings that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Peace and Satisfaction, which is ſo much deſired by all wiſe Men.</item>
               <item>II. IT mightily promotes Ones Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs and Perfection in Vertue.</item>
               <item>III. IT is an excellent Preſervative from many great Evils and Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies, which commonly happen in this our Militant State.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. FIRST, An humble Mind brings that inward Peace and Satisfaction, which is ſo much deſired by all wiſe Men. This tranquillity of Soul is indeed the moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirable thing we are capable of on this ſide Heaven; for it is the great Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this Life; the Happineſs where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto the Practice of Religion tendeth; the Happineſs that is a fore-taſte of the Comforts above; a Specimen of that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting Reſt, which is reſerved for all that love the Lord Jeſus in ſincerity. This is ſo plain, that we need not the help of any Philoſophy to prove it. Now, of thoſe Vertues which are inſtrumental and operative in order to this Happineſs, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility is one of the chiefeſt; becauſe it it ſets the Heart upon a Baſis, where it <pb n="42" facs="tcp:106212:25"/> reſteth quietly; ſafe and free from thoſe impetuous Paſſions, which work violent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon proud Spirits; like a Tempeſt that breaks the Cedars of <hi>Lebanon,</hi> but flies over the low Ground, without doing any hurt, or making much noiſe. There are ſeveral things which are apt to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſe and ruffle Mens Minds in this frail, mortal Condition: And from all theſe an humble Heart is a great ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity.</p>
            <p>AS, Firſt, The guilt of Sin. This is a thing that carries a very quick Senſe with it, which naturally and deſervedly diſquiets Criminals; nor is any thing ſo painful as an evil Conſcience, when once it beginneth to rage. Humility will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve you from this guilt; and, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, from the torment that would attend it, if you will but learn to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit your ſelves to God, to his Laws, and Pleaſure in all things, as the due Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of your own Meanneſs muſt needs incline you to do. An humble Heart is not apt to be lifted up againſt its Maker, nor to reſiſt and diſobey his Commands; becauſe it is conſcious of God's Greatneſs, Power, and Authority over us all; and, of that infinite Diſtance which is between his Glorious Majeſty <pb n="43" facs="tcp:106212:25"/> and us poor Creatures, who are Worms, Earth, Vanity, nothing in compariſon. Obedience doth naturally ſpring from ſuch lowly Thoughts; and ſo that Peace and Comfort which is the Fruit of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, muſt ſpring in the Mind too. In ſhort, it is that Spiritual Refreſhment and Eaſe, which our Bleſſed Saviour hath promiſed to his followers, and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſuch as follow the Example of his great Humility; <hi>Learn of me, for I am meek and lowly in heart, and ye ſhall find reſt unto your ſouls,</hi> Matth. II. 29.</p>
            <p n="2">2. ANOTHER thing that is wont to diſcompoſe Mens Minds, is a Senſe of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpect; we are too ready (God knows) to entertain very kind Thoughts of our own ſelves; and to expect that others ſhould think as we do, and ſhould ſhow that deference, which we fanſie to be due from abroad, becauſe we are fond of making the firſt payment of it at home. When vain Men find themſelves diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, Lord! What pain and anguiſh are they in preſently! Impatient and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected, like <hi>Haman,</hi> who was ſo mortifi'd by failing of one Ceremony, as if all his Enjoyments lay at
<hi>Mordecai</hi>'s Feet. This is one great reproach of Pride, That 'tis always ready with a Rack, for thoſe <pb n="44" facs="tcp:106212:26"/> who never think themſelves high enough: Nor are any ſo crucify'd as they who are moſt in love with this Tyrant Vice.</p>
            <p>EVERY thing that looks like con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, is a nail that createth freſh Torture in them: Whereas a Spirit of Humility delivers one from pains of this Nature; becauſe ſuch a Man conſiders whoſe face it was that was ſpit upon, before he endured the Croſs; and if the Son of God was ſo patient under the greateſt indignities, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly a poor ſinful Man hath reaſon when the right Cheek is uſed Contumeliouſly, to turn the left alſo, though the diſgrace be never ſo provoking. But in this caſe an humble Perſon finds not ſufficient <hi>cauſe</hi> of diſturbance, becauſe he is ſuppoſed to be deſpicable in his own Eyes; and if he thinks his Eyes do not deceive him, how is it a provocation that he is ſo in the Eyes of others too? Their agreement in the ſame opinion is matter not of trouble, but of complacency rather, becauſe each Party believes his opinion to be right. If to expoſe thee, People proclaim ſome of thy faults, do not ſtand upon thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence (ſaith <hi>Epictetus</hi>) as if they did thee wrong; but ſay only, they are ignorant People; for if they knew all thy faults, they would not have mentioned theſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. <pb n="45" facs="tcp:106212:26"/> By ſuch a modeſt turn of the hand 'tis eaſie to wipe off the fouleſt Spittle, before it ſinks into the breaſt. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the Humble Man conſiders what Mouth it came from: For, Applauſe from ſome Mens lips may be conſtru'd as a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel; and many times we may well be jealous, as
<hi>Socrates</hi> was wont to be, that he had done ſomething amiſs, when he was reſpected and commended by ill Men: The deſpitefulneſs of ſuch brings this great comfort with it, <hi>That there is no preſent danger of that woe, which we have reaſon to be afraid of, when all Men ſpeak well of us,</hi> Luc. 6. 26.</p>
            <p>FURTHER yet; Whoever the Men, whatever the Diſreſpect be, and what impreſſions ſoever it makes, it ſits the eaſier upon an Humble Man's mind, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he takes it as a means of making him the more Humble ſtill: For lowly hearts are apt to miſtruſt, that they are never lowly enough; and therefore, when any thing happens, which helps to abaſe them, whether it be deſerved or no, it is not unwelcome, becauſe it is of very good uſe, and may have been miniſtred by the hand of God for the good Man's parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular advantage. Thus <hi>David</hi> took it when <hi>Shimei</hi> curſed him, and threw ſtones <pb n="46" facs="tcp:106212:27"/> at him: <hi>So let him Curſe, ſaid the King, becauſe the Lord hath ſaid unto him, Curſe</hi> David, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. 10. And when we make ſuch a Religious conſtruction of Affronts and Contumelies, as things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for our good; and ſuch a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious uſe of them, as to be better'd and made more Humble by them, they muſt needs loſe that Acrimony and Gall which is ſo very diſtaſtful and grievous to proud Men who want the Divine Art of altering the Waters of <hi>Marah,</hi> ſo as to deſtroy their bitterneſs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A third thing that too often diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets Mens minds, is the great Proſperity of others as to their outward Fortunes; becauſe in the diſtribution of theſe Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Bleſſings, the Divine Providence doth not obſerve the Rules of exact Equality: People whoſe condition is much lower than their Neighbours, look upon thoſe above them with an evil Eye, grow impatient, fretful, and querulous, becauſe (forſooth) the ſame liberal and open hand is not extended unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Such greedy and reaching deſires can never be without great vexation of Spirit, eſpecially when Induſtry and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition have made many unſucceſsful at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts to get higher. In which caſe, <pb n="47" facs="tcp:106212:27"/> nothing certainly can be ſuch a ſpeedy and effectual relief to the Soul to give it. Peace and Reſt, as true Humility. The firſt thought that is naturally incident to an Humble Man, is, That as all Right is in God, the great and ſole Proprietary, who hath an indiſputable Power to do what he <hi>pleaſeth with his own,</hi> Matth. 20.
15. So the greateſt Title we can pretend to, is that of Uſufructuaries; Tenants at Will in every reſpect (though in this caſe the Tenure be for Lives too, as precarious a Tenure as the other) and for ſuch en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire dependants to be envious at the Divine oeconomy, is the moſt impious unthankfulneſs, when we have all of us as little reaſon to murmur, as we have capacity to Pay, or power to Demand. Again, as we depend upon God for all that we have, ſo we muſt acknowledge, that whatſoever that be, is more than we deſerve. And this humble conſideration that God is our abſolute Soverign, but not our Debtor, is another ſtrong reaſon for us to acquieſce, and be content with our Portion; becauſe, though it be not as great as other Mens, yet it is enough to make us not only ſatisfied, but thankful. <hi>Lord,</hi> ſaid Jacob, <hi>I am not worthy of the leaſt of all the Mercies, which thou haſt ſhewed unto thy Servant: With my Staff I
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:106212:28"/> Paſſed over Jordan, and now I am become two bands,</hi> Gen. 32. 10.</p>
            <p>THIRDLY, Humility teacheth us to conſider, that whatſoever our Condition is, it is that which is beſt and fitteſt for us. Of this, indeed, we our ſelves are not competent Judges, becauſe our Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings are as weak as our Deſires are unreaſonable; and were our For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes in our own hands, our partiality and ignorance would make us the very worſt Carvers of them; God knows beſt what we moſt need; and that alone is proper, which he ſees to be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and convenient: And therefore the mere Light of Nature directed <hi>Socrates</hi> when he prayed, to implore the Divine Goodneſs in general terms, leaving it to God to chuſe for him, how, and when, and what to beſtow upon him; belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it to be a Man's ſafeſt courſe to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit always to the Wiſdom and Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of God. But you will ſay, Was not <hi>David</hi> envious at the Proſperity of the wicked? Yes; he tells us himſelf that he was ſo, and that in his diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſullen humour, he muttered, as if he had cleanſed his Heart in vain, and had waſh'd his Hands in Innocency, (to no purpoſe;) but he tells us too, that in all <pb n="49" facs="tcp:106212:29"/> this he behaved himſelf very fooliſhly, <hi>and like a beaſt,</hi> Pſalm 73. 22. The truth is, this is one of the moſt affecting Caſes, when we ſee thoſe whom we take to be very ill Men, to thrive at a mighty rate, and to grow great and powerful in the World. Nevertheleſs, Humility teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us in all Caſes, not to take Example by any, ſo as to be Uncharitable or Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious. The humble Man's Rule is that, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 3. <hi>In lowlineſs of mind, let each e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem other better than themſelves.</hi> I know the Apoſtle's meaning to be, That we ſhould behave our ſelves to others, <hi>as if</hi> they were better, whether they be really ſo, or not. Such a Judgment of the Mind is not always required; and, if ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times we think it impoſſible too, for the humbleſt Perſon in the World, to think all others better, it is yet inconſiſtent with Humility to judge them worſe; for God alone is the ſearcher of the Heart: That is in too cloſe a Repoſitory for One's next Neighbour to penetrate into; and therefore to make wrong judgment of
<hi>others,</hi> is too facil a thing, even for good Men, who are apt to take falſe eſtimates of <hi>themſelves,</hi> with whom they ſhould be far better acquainted. Such humble Thoughts as theſe do naturally prompt Men, evermore to make very charitable <pb n="50" facs="tcp:106212:30"/> Judgments; and, conſequently, to reſt ſatisfied in their Minds, when the Divine Providence doth multiply and heap up the good things of this life upon the Heads of others. But to put the Caſe at the very worſt; Suppoſe the Men, thus judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and cenſured, to be wicked indeed, (I mean, wicked in the ſtrict Scripture<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; guilty of great, ſcandalous, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous Sins:) This is, in truth, an Argument for our Prayers, and charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Admonitions; but not for Envy; nor are any People in the World more to be pitied than ſuch.</p>
            <p n="4">4. BY this ſhort Account it appears, what an uſeful Vertue Humility is, to rid our Minds of all fooliſh impatience, and to compoſe them into a ſerene and calm ſtate, how invidious ſoever the Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Circumſtances of others may be. Let us conſider now, Fourthly, the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage it brings an humble Man, how perplexed ſoever his own Condition is. There are many croſs, calamitous Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents in this life, which we cannot digeſt under any one General Head ſo well as under the common name of <hi>Afflictions;</hi> ſo called, becauſe they give very painful <hi>blows</hi> to the Hearts of ſuch People, as are not in ſome good meaſure improved <pb n="51" facs="tcp:106212:30"/> and perfected by the Diſcipline of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. And theſe Afflictions are of two ſorts; ſome that are actually felt; and others that we fear: Both are dolorous; for though preſent Afflictions yield the quickeſt ſenſe, yet many times future ones create the moſt melancholy pain; nay, the bare apprehenſion and proſpect of them, when at ſome diſtance uſually makes longer and deeper impreſſions up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Mens Minds, than when they are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged and wreſtling with them in a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Conflict. In each of theſe Caſes, Humility affords the beſt Auxiliaries; ſo that how lowly and ſubdued ſoever One's
<hi>Heart</hi> is, he can lift up his <hi>Head</hi> in the day of diſtreſs.
<hi>Firſt,</hi> As to preſent Afflictions: There are theſe Four Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, which naturally ſerve to make every humble Chriſtian very eaſie (if not chearful) in his own Mind.</p>
            <p n="1">1. THAT though ſecond Cauſes be the immediate inſtruments of Affliction, yet the Hand of God doth ſo order, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern and direct them, that we are ſtill under his management in all Conditions. And ſince it is ſo, what can ſo well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a lowly Mind, as that modeſt reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation which old <hi>Eli</hi> expreſs'd, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3. 18.
<hi>It is the Lord, let him do what ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth <pb n="52" facs="tcp:106212:31"/> him good.</hi> Doeſt thou well to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry? As the great Governor of the World was pleaſed to argue with <hi>Jonah,</hi> when he was in his ſullen fits; firſt, becauſe <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neveh</hi> was not deſtroy'd, and then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his friendly Gourd was ſmitten with a Worm, <hi>Jonah</hi> 4. By which mild Expoſtulation God ſhews, that whether he ſpares, or deſtroys, ſtill
'tis our Duty to acquieſce in his Divine Pleaſure; and that it is the
<hi>fooliſhneſs of man, which makes his heart fret againſt the Lord, as Solomon</hi> obſerves, <hi>Prov.</hi> 19. 3. <hi>Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> Whether God afflicteth Men by the Hands of others, or with his own Hands, and by his immediate Providence, it muſt be acknowledged, that the Judge of all the Earth doth ſtill do Right. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the ſcandalous Provocations which are given by ſome, the heinous, though ſecret Crimes which are acted by others, the Faults which the beſt are guilty of, and the Corruption of Heart which is in all, none can reaſonably expect to ſteal out of this World without a Rod upon his Back; or, at leaſt without ſome Thorn or other in his Fleſh: (You know, a Sword was to pierce through the Soul of the bleſſed Virgin her ſelf, <hi>Luke</hi> 2. 35.) The humble will conſider this; and the due Conſideration of it muſt needs ſtop <pb n="53" facs="tcp:106212:31"/> his Mouth, and quiet his Mind, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to God's Proceedings, becauſe he cannot but be ſenſible, that his Sufferings are the conſequent of his Offences, and that too which falls ſo very. ſhort of them, that if we will put both into the Scales, and then judge by weight, the burden that is in one Scale, how heavy ſo ever it may ſeem, is really very light, hardly any thing in compariſon of thoſe Demerits which by a vaſt preponderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on bear and keep down the other. Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility directs us in all Caſes to reflect not ſo much upon our Grievances, as our Guilt: And, if People in Affliction would take this ſafe and prudent courſe, there would be no room nor reaſon for any ſorrow of Heart, beſides that which worketh Repentance unto Salvation. <hi>Wherefore doth a living man complain? a man for the puniſhment of his ſins?</hi> ſaith <hi>Jeremy,</hi> Lam. 3. 39.
<hi>Thirdly,</hi> In viſiting Mens Offences with a Rod, God doth not act purely as a Judge, but rather with the Wiſdom and Tenderneſs of a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; either to keep his Children ſtill within the limits of their Duty, or to reclaim them from their Aberrations. Outward Eaſe is naturally apt to corrupt good Manners, as fulneſs and idleneſs is apt to vitiate the Blood, and to ruine <pb n="54" facs="tcp:106212:32"/> One's whole Conſtitution. Therefore, to exerciſe the Soul, and thereby to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it in the right ſtate, God doth commonly uſe ſuch a meaſure of ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as he knows we ſtand in need of; and when a Man makes an application of this to himſelf, after an humble manner, he cannot but be ſatisfied with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle's argument, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.
9, 20. <hi>If we have had fathers of our fleſh which corrected us, and we gave them reverence, ſhall we not much rather be in ſubjection to the Father of Spirits, and live? For they verily, for a few days chaſtened us after their own plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; but he for our profit, that we might be partakers of his holineſs.</hi> For this graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous purpoſe ſake, they who are conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to themſelves of their Deſerts and Wants (as all humble Perſons are) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but poſſeſs their Souls in Patience under the Hand that correcteth; and with Thankfulneſs too, for ſtripes which are thus profitable and advantageous to them; not only hearing the Rod, as the Prophet ſpeaks, <hi>Micah</hi> 3. 9. but kiſſing it alſo, becauſe there is Honey on the end of it, as there was on the top of <hi>Jonathan</hi>'s Rod, 1
<hi>Sam.</hi> 14. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> and laſtly, St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives this Character of Temptation, (meaning Affliction) <hi>that it is cammon to man,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 13. And <pb n="55" facs="tcp:106212:32"/> conſidering that it is a general Lot, the humble in Soul will ſit down quiet, and well contented to have a ſhare: <hi>For how,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>am I better than my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours?</hi> Indeed, it is no comfort to good Nature, to ſee others in miſery; yet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Man's Grief is much the leſs, when Diſcipline is adminiſtred impartially; and of all others, the humble Man's ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction is the greateſt, when comparing his Sins and his Sufferings with other Mens, he findeth ſo vaſt a diſproportion; as if God were particularly merciful to him, in viſiting more, and (as he thinks) more
<hi>heinous</hi> Offences, with fewer and leſs-afflicting Stripes. It is one great cauſe of Murmurs and Impatience, that we look at the Proſperity, not at the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes of other People; at leaſt, that we do not lay them equally to Heart: Their glittering Condition ſtrikes the tendereſt Side, and there makes the deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt impreſſions. The ſenſe of their Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions goes off with an eaſie, and too often with a pleaſant ſlide; eſpecially where Nature is too hard for Religion. But were our Humility commenſurate to St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s, when he owned himſelf <hi>leſs than the leaſt of all Saints,</hi> Epheſ. 3. 8. nay, <hi>the chiefeſt of ſinners,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. 15. 'Twere impoſſible for us to be very uneaſie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <pb n="56" facs="tcp:106212:33"/> our Affictions, could we be able to give in ſuch a large Regiſter of them, as he gives of his own, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> II. In the midſt of which we find him ſtill rejoycing. In ſhort, he that is vile and worthleſs in his own eſtimate, cannot but learn in what ſtate ſoever he is, therewith to be content; unleſs he will be ſo falſe to himſelf, as to condemn his own Opinion, and reverſe his own Judgment. Which ſufficiently demonſtrates, what an ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable Bleſſing Humility is to the Soul, amidſt all the various and troubleſome incumbrances of this Life. At once it poliſheth our Nature, and refreſheth us with Delights; that is, it doth us all the Good that we are capable of enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a mortal ſtate. There is ſuch an indiſſoluble Union between this Vertue and Felicity, that it is impoſſible for a Man to be truly Humble, but he muſt, in ſpight of Fortune, be very Happy too.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I told you before, That of all Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, thoſe which we pretend to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern aloof off, do many times affect the Mind with the greateſt Anguiſh: And at the cloſe of this Conſideration, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that Peace and Comfort wherewith Humility endues the Heart, it will be
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:106212:33"/> neceſſary to obſerve, how advantageous this Vertue is, when a Calamity threatens and looks terrible at a diſtance. In this Caſe there are three things eſpecially which Humility ſuggeſteth to our Minds, for the eaſe and ſatisfaction of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. FIRST, Our whole dependance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the Care of that infinite Being, who is the Governor and Diſpoſer of all things, we may be ſure, that nothing can befal us contrary unto, or without his Pleaſure: So that tho' we are little, contemptible things of our ſelves, yet conſidering whoſe Creatures we are, and whoſe Hands we are in, it is our Duty in all ominous Circumſtances to commit our ſelves to God, with ſuch reſignation and recumbency as becomes the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of poor, ſhiftleſs Beings, that are left entirely to him, and hang every mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nute upon his Providence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. SECONDLY, God being infinitely Wiſe, Governing and Ordering every part of the Univerſe with conſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the Whole, it is our Wiſdom to acquieſce in our Lots, as God ſhall pleaſe to diſpenſe them, and to make his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Will our Choice; in regard that we our ſelves are ſo very ſhort-ſighted and <pb n="58" facs="tcp:106212:34"/> partial, that we are not fit to be our own chuſers, becauſe we do not know what we <hi>ſhould,</hi> but crave only for what we <hi>would</hi> have.</p>
            <p n="3">3. THIRDLY, However Events prove, it is not out of our power to make an Honeſt and Religious uſe of them; and then all things ſhall
<hi>work together for good to them that love God,</hi> Rom. 8. 28. Theſe humble Conſiderations muſt needs miniſter great Reſt and Comfort to One's Soul, tho' future Contingencies carry with them a terrible aſpect; and thereby the reaſonableneſs and excellence of our Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty appears, of taking no anxious, carking Thoughts about to morrow. Becauſe God prefideth over all, many things which we preſage, do not happen (Clouds uſually drop before they advance over our heads) and how can the humble Man anſwer it to his own mind, to crucifie himſelf before-hand, for that which, for ought he knows, may never come to to paſs? Becauſe God is infinitely Wiſe and Good, who can tell certainly what is within the Cloud? Or, whether many
<hi>Bleſſings</hi> may not fall down together with the Storm? It is inconſiſtent with Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to pry into God's Counſels after a diſtruſtful manner; and, conſequently, <pb n="59" facs="tcp:106212:34"/> to perplex One's Heart with a grievous apprehenſion of accidents, which perhaps may be for his great advantage: Or, ſay it be a <hi>real</hi> Calamity that is coming, it is an humble Man's part to leave God to his own time, and to wait God's leiſure, without going forward to meet an Evil, which he is bound to be patient under, but not to anticipate. <hi>Sufficient unto the day is the evil thereof,</hi> ſaid the humble Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. 34.</p>
            <p>TO enforce the practice of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as to this particular, I cannot but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve what Religious Principles ſome Heathen Moraliſts went on, who placed Happineſs in the ſtudy and exerciſe of Vertue, becauſe it is the only thing which bleſſeth a Man's Soul with Satisfaction and Tranquillity. By the Light of Nature they diſcover'd three great Truths, which they proved too, and urged the belief of them, as abſolutely neceſſary to a Man's Happineſs.</p>
            <p n="1">1. THAT there is a God; or, (as they themſelves mean) a Sovereign, Incorporeal, Intellectual Being, that is Uncompounded, Independent, Self-exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent, Self-moving; the moſt Abſolute and Perfect Good, the Supreme and firſt Cauſe of all things.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:106212:35"/> 2. SECONDLY, That as God exactly knoweth all the things he hath made, and hath a Power over all, ſo he taketh care of the whole Univerſe, and the ſeveral parts of it, the meaneſt Creatures not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted.</p>
            <p n="3">3. THIRDLY, That God doth not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inſpect the World, but doth moreover adminiſter and govern all Affairs, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſtrict Rules of Goodneſs and Righteouſneſs. From which Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples thoſe wiſe Philoſophers concluded, That as it is our Duty to honour and worſhip God, ſo we muſt ſet our ſelves to Obey him, to ſubmit to his Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, to follow his Conduct with chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, to be well-pleaſed with what he doth, as being the Reſult of his Divine Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Providence. If you do no diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe your Minds thus, your Lives (ſay they) will be not only Irreligious, but full of Sadneſs and Miſery too: Whereas, if you reſign your Wills to God's, and be contented with Events, as God ſhall pleaſe to order them, you will be happy. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<hi>Socrates</hi> was wont to ſay, <hi>If God will have it thus, then thus let it be.</hi> And <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pictetus</hi> his Prayer was, <hi>Lead me, O God,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:106212:35"/> according to thy Will, and I will readily o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey, and ſubmit to thy Providence. For</hi> (ſays <hi>Arrian</hi>) <hi>every good Man who believes there is a Deity and a Providence, will ſubmit his own Mind to God's Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, the Governour of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſe, as good Citizens ſubmit to the Laws of the City they live in.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Concerning all this ſee <hi>Epictetus, cap.</hi> 38, 77, 79.
<hi>Arrian</hi> on <hi>Epictet.</hi> lib. 1. <hi>c.</hi> 12. and eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<hi>Simplicius</hi> his Comments 38. <hi>per totum.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>THESE were great Notions for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens to entertain; ſuch a complexure of good Divinity and Morality together, as one would think were the Sence of a Chriſtian. And the reſult of the whole matter is this; That as all the Happineſs of this Life is lodged in Vertue; ſo this Vertue of Humility doth contribute to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it after a more eſpecial manner, and in a ſingular degree; becauſe it reſigneth up the Soul to God's Wiſdom and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in all Conditions; ſo that in all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicting Circumſtances, whether actually felt, or apprehended only, the truly hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Perſon poſſeſſeth his Soul in Patience, and is bleſs'd with Tranquillity in as great meaſures, as a frail Nature is capable of receiving. Such as are ſo proud, that they care not for the Almighty, and think themſelves too big for his Rod, in times of trial and diſtreſs, aggravate <pb n="62" facs="tcp:106212:36"/> the ſmart from without, by being their own tormentors within, and the moſt inhumane tormentors, becauſe the Pains they inflict are hardly curable, and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom intermitting. Every odd chance is magnified into a great Affliction; and every Affliction gnaws and eats, as if it were an affront to their ſingular Merits, and an argument of Injuſtice and Partia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity in the Divine Providence. And thus the Spirits of ſuch vain Wretches breed Worms, which like thoſe engendred in a dead Carcaſe, never leave till they have devoured their Parent; and all at laſt produce the Worm which dieth not.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:106212:36"/>
            <head>CHAP. V. <hi>The Uſefulneſs of Humility, in reſpect of our Proficiency in Vertue.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HITHERTO I have conſider'd the Uſefulneſs of Humility, in reſpect of that Contentment and Serenity of Mind, which is the bleſſed Fruit of it. Let us proceed now to the next thing, and obſerve how inſtrumental it is, in order to our Progreſs and Perfection in Vertue: Now there are very many ways, whereby it helpeth to promote this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable Advantage: But it will be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for me to take notice of theſe Four ways following.</p>
            <p n="1">1. FIRST, By obliging us to reſt in the Authority of Divine Revelation. This is the Foundation of our Faith and Hopes, and of thoſe Religious Endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, we are encouraged to uſe, that we may receive the end of them: All is bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom'd on this Principle, That the things we believe and look for, are certain, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath revealed them; and 'tis Humility that concurs with right Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon <pb n="64" facs="tcp:106212:37"/> to ſettle our Souls upon this Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, how dark and doubtful ſoever ſome things may ſeem to humane Apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The daily Senſe which all humble Men have of the weakneſs and fallaciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their own Underſtandings, is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to convince them, that Carnal Reaſon is not to be truſted Univerſally, and with Confidence in things pertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing unto God; and that it is our Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom as well as Duty, to take God's Word for all, however the Word ſpoken may ſound in our Ears. This is a great Fault in ſome pretenders to Reaſon, that they will not allow us to believe Doctrines, unleſs they
<hi>appear</hi> rational as to all the Parts and Modes of thoſe Matters which are propoſed to our Belief; and unleſs they captivate our Faith, by ſuiting with our Capacities, and by carrying with them a plain Evidence,
<hi>How</hi> thoſe things can be. This proceeds from Spiritual Pride, and Self-conceit, and is the ready way to make Reaſon not an Aſſiſtant, but an Idol, for the <hi>Holy Bible</hi> to be offer'd up unto. Humble Men will tell you, That many things in Religion are and ought to be cover'd with a Veil; that it is not Modeſty to pry without Light, or without Leave, or beyond the reach of our finite Faculties; that Myſteries <pb n="65" facs="tcp:106212:37"/> ought to be let alone, and ſuffer'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main Myſteries; that <hi>ſecret things belong unto the Lord our God; and that thoſe things which are revealed, belong unto us, and to our children for ever,</hi> Deut. 29. 29. And thus our Faith will be infallible and unſhaken, our Hope firm, and our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs in a courſe of Religion will be ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, which otherwiſe may be fatally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted by our turning aſide into mazes and labyrinths, with a deſign to diſcover things, which God in his Wiſdom hath purpoſely hid from us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. THAT in this courſe of Religion we may not travel with a Tympany, full of hopes that will at laſt deceive, and make us aſhamed; we are taught, that beſides a modeſt Faith, univerſal Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Divine Will is neceſſarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired; and this is another improvement that comes by an humble Mind; it diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth the Soul to perfect Holineſs in the fear of God; and not only to rely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Veracity, but to have an Eye al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to the Authority of God; that tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent Authority which is ſtamped up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Laws. Conſidering that he is our Supreme, Abſolute, and only Wiſe Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſlator; that we were all made for his Glory; that we have no urgent buſineſs <pb n="66" facs="tcp:106212:38"/> in the World, but to glorifie him; that he is glorifi'd in our Happineſs, and that his Laws are intended to fit and prepare us for it; what other Thoughts can an humble Mind ſuggeſt, but that it is at once our Duty and our Intereſt to ſerve God in true Holineſs and Righteouſneſs before him all the days of our lives? Such lowly Thoughts are apt to be ſeconded with ſuitable Reſolutions; and thence proceed thoſe various acts of Godlineſs, Righteouſneſs, and Sobriety, which are anſwerable to the Commands of the Lord and Saviour of the World. For which reaſon the Ancients in their Encomiums of Humility, frequently ſtyle it, <hi>The Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, the Original, the Root, the Mother of all Vertue, and the great Preſerver of it:</hi> Becauſe a ſubmiſs diſpoſition of Soul is naturally pliant, and never more obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ential than when the Pleaſure and Will of God is to be done. The adoring Senſe of the glorious Nature, Attributes, and Works of God, on the Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whereof the humble Man's Mind is fix'd; the apprehenſion of his infinite Greatneſs and Majeſty; the thoughts of his Abſolute Power and Authority over all; the amazing and profound Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of his free Goodneſs and Love, eſpecially in Redeeming our miſerable <pb n="67" facs="tcp:106212:38"/> Souls from eternal Ruine, and in beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on us ſuch Spiritual and Divine Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, as are Arguments of our Adoption, the Preparatives and Earneſt of a moſt bleſſed future Eſtate: Theſe things car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuch a charming Power over a meek and lowly Heart, as is productive of the moſt chearful and affectionate Obedience to the Mind and Pleaſure of God in all things.</p>
            <p n="3">3. THIRDLY, As Humility fits us for an entire and hearty compliance with God's Commands; ſo it poſſeſſeth us with a genuine ſence of our own Defects and Wants; which is another way whereby it helpeth our progreſs and perfection in Vertue. For this is neceſſary to all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Improvements, that we ſee firſt wherein we are defective. That Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of <hi>Seneca, That many might be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wiſe in time, but that they fooliſhly think themſelves wiſe enough already,</hi> will hold true in all Caſes: Men might eaſily be better Artiſts, better Scholars, better Chriſtians than they are, if a falſe Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Accompliſhments did not ſuperſede their Induſtry. And this is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently the miſchievous effect of Pride, That it ſhuts a Man (as it were) out of himſelf; makes him uncapable of find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <pb n="68" facs="tcp:106212:39"/> out that blind ſide, and ugly tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which requires help, but admits of none for want of diſcovery. And the reaſon is, becauſe ſuch Men take not a clear and fair view; they overlook thoſe manifold faults which deſerve their Eye, and contemplate only thoſe glittering Objects which dazle it. Hence it comes to paſs, that a great many flaws within them eſcape their obſervation; and they are no Proficients, becauſe they are not properly Teachers, but Admirers of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, only; lifted up with the Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Confidence of thoſe our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our pointed to who truſted in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>that they were righteous, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed others,</hi> Luke 18. 9. That humble Apoſtle who confeſt his Sins to the whole World, and proclaimed himſelf the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of Sinners, counted all things but loſs for the Excellency of the Knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus: And tho' he ſpake as if he were blameleſs, as touching Righteouſneſs which was by the Law, yet he threw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide all that Righteouſneſs of his own; not conceiving that he had already at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, or was already perfect, but fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing after, (ſtretching and ſtraining hard, like thoſe that contended of old in the famous <hi>Agoniſtical</hi> Combats) for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting thoſe things which were behind, <pb n="69" facs="tcp:106212:39"/> he reached forth unto thoſe things which were before, preſſing <hi>towards the mark, for the prize of the high calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Phil. 3. As many as are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly humble, will be thus minded; thus zealous to run and to finiſh their courſe well. Becauſe they are conſcious of their former Miſcarriages, of their preſent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, Defects, Unworthineſs, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbrances, and natural proneneſs to Slip and Fall; they know the better what Care to take, what Temptations they are to avoid, what Weights they are to lay aſide, what aids of Grace they are to pray for, and what Supplies are moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for them. They are always jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous over themſelves with Godly Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie; ſtill fearing leſt as the Serpent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiled Eve, through his Subtilty, ſo their Minds ſhould be corrupted from the Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity that is in Chriſt. They think their Sins can never be mortified enough, nor their Hearts be clean enough, nor their Repentance fruitful enough, nor their Devotion ardent enough, nor their Charity great enough, nor any other acts of Religion worthy enough of his graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Acceptance, who loved them, and gave himſelf for them. Theſe are ſo far from being Diſcouragements, that they are great Motives to a courſe of Profici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency. <pb n="70" facs="tcp:106212:40"/> For tho', when we have done all, we muſt acknowledge our ſelves unpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Servants, and come ſhort of our Duty, tho' our Minds and Endeavours be ſincere; yet conſidering, that not ſo much as a Cup of cold Water loſeth its Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and conſidering the great Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Lord Jeſus, who is pleaſed with what we are able to do, (as he ſaid of that Woman who anointed his Head, <hi>Mark</hi> 14. <hi>She hath wrought a good work on me: She hath done what ſhe could;</hi> conſidering this, I ſay) the meaneſt Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances muſt afford ſuch a comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Proſpect, as will invite the humble to proceed from Vertue to Vertue, while all the Pomp of proud Men, with their ſtiff Necks and inflexible Hearts, ſerves only to alienate their Minds from Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion by degrees, till they come to that high pitch of Inſolence which <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks of, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 10. 4. <hi>The wicked through the pride of his countenance will not ſeek af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God: God is not in all his thoughts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. FOUR THLY, An humble Mind helps Men on in their Chriſtian Progreſs, by preparing and inclining them to uſe the
<hi>means</hi> of Holineſs.</p>
            <p>THE means of Holineſs I now ſpeak of, are Prayer, Sacraments, and Inſtruction.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:106212:40"/> 1. FIRST, For Prayer: It is a great Inſtrument of Grace. <hi>If any of you lack wiſdom</hi> (ſaith St.
<hi>James</hi>) <hi>let him ask of God, that giveth to all men liberally and upbraideth not, and it ſhall be given him,</hi> James 1. 5. And this may be one rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, why the ſame Apoſtle tells us, <hi>Chap.</hi> 4. 6. <hi>God giveth grace to the humble;</hi> that is, more Grace, greater meaſures of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Aſſiſtance, than he gives to others; becauſe they are of a more devout Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, more ready for any opportunities of Praying, more conſtant, and fervent, and importunate at their Devotion. The want of this pious Diſpoſition proceeds, not more from an earthly, heavy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, than from a ſecret Principle of Pride; from a faſtidious Mind in People, which makes Religion hang ſo looſe about them, that every puff of Wind carries it away?
'Tis a ſign they have contemptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Thoughts of God, who make ſo ſlight of his Service, as if to honour him, to worſhip him, and to bow down be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, were a precarious matter. To fold our Arms in a ſoft Bed, when we ſhould be proſtrate in our Cloſets; to rove about, when the Church wants us; or, to be buſie about many things at home, when we ſhould repair to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, <pb n="72" facs="tcp:106212:41"/> and take a ſhare with thoſe who chuſe the better part: This looks as if we thought Almighty God behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to us for our Service. And ſo, an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different ſort of carriage <hi>in</hi> the Houſe of God, when we meet together for Prayer, a wandring Eye, impertinent Talk, a ſtiff Knee, an irreverent Geſture: This looks as if we counted our bare attendance in the Church, Civility and Favour rather than Obedience: I am ſure it is not ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Temper of thoſe humble Souls, who reckon no Ground too vile, no Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture too lowly, no Thoughts too awful, no Adoration too profound in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of that Great God, who
<hi>ſearcheth the very heart and reins.</hi> And how can it be expected, that People who thus bear themſelves on high, ſhould make any good improvements in Religion? Or, that they ſhould perfect Holineſs in the fear of God, who deſpiſe even the outward Beauty of it? How can it be expected, that they ſhould receive the Influences of Grace, who ſhut their Boſoms (as it were) againſt them? That they ſhould be truſted with a Divine Treaſure, who carry themſelves as if they were rich e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, and had need of nothing? Or, that they ſhould be bleſs'd with the Dew of Heaven, who are inſolently ſupine, <pb n="73" facs="tcp:106212:41"/> as if they had the Fortune of
<hi>Gideon</hi>'s Fleece, to be full of Water, whilſt the neighbouring Ground was dry. So proud People count others in compariſon; and yet thoſe humble Hearts that are a thirſt for God, and cry unto him like the parch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Land, are more receptive of Diſtilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from above, and much the more fruitful by them. God heareth their Cries; and, as a return of their Prayers, refreſheth them with increments of his Grace and Goodneſs; ſo that they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from Strength to Strength, from Vertue to Vertue, from one degree of Grace unto another.</p>
            <p n="2">2. SECONDLY, As an humble Mind prompts Men to be diligent and devout at their Prayers, ſo it inclines them to communicate often at the Altar; which is another means of Holineſs. Becauſe this Sacrament was of our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our's own appointment, and that too a little before he humbled himſelf (even to the Death of the Croſs;) becauſe he was pleas'd to inſtitute it for a ſtanding Memorial of his great Love to Mankind, in dying for all: And becauſe he ſaid, (pointing to the Cup) <hi>Do this, as oft as ye ſhall drink it, in remembrance of me.</hi> The Chriſtian Church hath in all times <pb n="74" facs="tcp:106212:42"/> held this Solemnity in the greateſt Eſteem and Veneration, as being a Chriſtian Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance in the ſtricteſt Senſe, and after a more peculiar manner; and ſuch was the Humility of Chriſtians (in the ancient Times eſpecially,) that for fear they ſhould not celebrate it often enough, they did it daily. And certainly, were our Humility as deep as theirs, our Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and Zeal as to this, would bear an equal proportion; as none would think themſelves to be above Ordinances, or without need of Ordinances, ſo as to ſlight this; ſo very few would hardly once omit it, being ſuch a Sacred and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn part of Chriſt's Religion, eſpecially conſidering how mightily the uſe of it promotes our Progreſs and Perfection in Vertue. Here we renew our Baptiſmal Vows: Here we repeat all acts of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification and Repentance: Here we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe our Faith and Hope with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt vigour: Here we enliven and extend our Charity to all Mankind: Here we are taken up with the Contemplation and Adorations of God: Here we exert all thoſe Spiritual Graces, which God gives us upon our devout Prayers. So that were this Ordinance religiouſly and conſtantly uſed, according to the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal deſign and purpoſe of our Saviour, <pb n="75" facs="tcp:106212:42"/> nothing could conduce more to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent and future Happineſs, than this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Myſtery, ſo perfective it is of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Vertue. The lowly in Heart can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but think themſelves obliged to be frequent Attendants at the Lord's-Table; what neglects, what contempt ſoever Men of unſubdued Spirits may be guilty of, People of an humble and truly Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Diſpoſition, make a Conſcience of this their Duty, and are afraid of viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſuch an expreſs, ſuch a plain Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; eſpecial of living in the habitual and ſcandalous violation of it. They conſider the infinite Love of the Lord Jeſus, who gave himſelf for them; how equal it is, to expreſs here their Thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs to him; how pleaſant, as well as frail the Duty is, and what infinite dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference there is between This Cup, and that which our bleſſed Saviour drank of for us in his Agony, and upon the Croſs. They think of thoſe Bleſſings which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Piety of every devout Soul, and are ſenſible of their want of them. They impatiently deſire the Pardon of all their Sins, and that Supply of Grace, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the Holy Spirit refreſheth the Hearts of all Worthy Communicants. And when the Solemnity is tranſacted, their daily care is to order their whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation <pb n="76" facs="tcp:106212:43"/> ſo, that they may not have recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Grace of God in vain. Theſe are genuine Fruits of Humility; and they all ſhew, how effectually this ſingle Vertue ſerves to carry on the great Ends and Purpoſes of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. THE Third thing I mentioned as a means of Holineſs, is Inſtruction. For, how ſincere ſo ever our Hearts may be, our Underſtandings are ſubject to ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Miſtakes and Errors, that good Guides are very neceſſary to inform us; tho' ſome think they do not need them at all. This is no other than Pride of Heart; nor do any ſtand in ſuch great need of skilful and honeſt Guides, as thoſe who think they are able enough to guide themſelves. <hi>Seeſt thou a man wiſe in his own conceit? There is more hope of a fool than of him,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov.
26. 12. Such a Man hearkeneth to himſelf; and being in the hands of ſuch a weak and flattering Tutor, no good Proficiency can be expected from him: He will ever be crooked, becauſe he grows, leaning every minute on the left-ſide. 'Tis hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poſſible ever to ſet ſuch an unlucky piece of a Man right, without ſuch a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle as in our Saviour's time cured the Blind and the Lame. His Knowledge <pb n="77" facs="tcp:106212:43"/> and Perfection, are ſo great in his own Eyes, that the pretending to rectifie Faults is interpreted, either as Ignorance that is inexcuſable, becauſe he is known no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; or, as Malice and ill Nature, for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to fix a dark part there, which he thought ſplendid; which way ſo ever it be taken, the proud Man thinks himſelf diſgraced; he is therefore affronted, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is above Reproof or Advice: And thus the means of making him bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and wiſer are quite fruſtrated. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for our Progreſs and Perfection in a Chriſtian courſe, it is a moſt neceſſary Rule, which St.
<hi>Paul</hi> gives us all to go by; <hi>Let none think of himſelf more highly than he ought to think; but think ſoberly.</hi> An humble Mind is tractable and docil; for the very Notion of Humility includes a mean and ſlender Opinion of One's own ſelf, and conſidering thoſe Commands, that
<hi>in honour we ſhould preferr one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> Rom. 12. 10. and eſteem each other better than our ſelves, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1. 3. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be more agreeable to a Spirit of true Humility, than to hearken to thoſe, whoſe Place and Office it is, by God's ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment, to direct and inform us, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when the Holy Scripture is their Rule; and to ſubmit to all thoſe means of Proficiency for which the Scriptures <pb n="78" facs="tcp:106212:44"/> themſelves were written, whether it be Doctrine. or Reproof, or Correction, or Inſtruction in Righteouſneſs; that the good Man may be perfect, throughly fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed unto all good Works. <hi>Let the righteous ſmite me, it ſhall be a kindneſs; and let him reprove me, it ſhall be an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent oil, which ſhall not break my head,</hi> ſaith the holy
<hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> Pſalm 141. 5.</p>
            <p>THE reſult of this whole Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is, That if Men expect ever to make Improvements, ſo as to be wiſe unto Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, it is abſolutely neceſſary for them to mould their Hearts into an humble, ſoft, and ductile temper: To caſt out that ſcornful, diſdaining Spirit, that ſets up it ſelf againſt God; to lay aſide all that ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceit, which every where hinders the advancement of true Religion; and to entertain ſuch modeſt Opinions of their own Abilities and Endowments, as are ſuitable to the condition of poor, ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſighted, infirm Creatures, that without Light and Help from better Hands, and eſpecially from God's, could never arrive to a true ſtate of perfect Happineſs. In our travels towards it, nothing can be of greater uſe to us, than an humble, plaint, and manageable Diſpoſition.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:106212:44"/>
            <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>The Uſefulneſs of Humility, in reſpect of the many Evils it preſerves us from.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE next thing to be conſider'd is, what an excellent Preſervative a Spirit of Humility is, from divers Evils and Inconveniencies, which are apt for want of it, to fall out and gall us in this our Chriſtian Progreſs. Theſe Evils and Inconveniencies are hardly to be num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred: But yet I conceive, an humble Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit helps (at leaſt, in a very conſiderable meaſure) to preſerve us from them all, by theſe following means.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. BY governing and moderating our inordinate Deſires.</item>
               <item>II. BY guarding us from divers hurtful Sins, which pride of Heart leadeth Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple unto.</item>
               <item>III. BY teaching us to make good uſe of the Diſpenſations of Providence.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:106212:45"/> 1. FIRST, By governing and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating our inordinate Deſires. There is hardly a worſe Plague, than a craving and greedy Appetite after the things that are in the World; which St. <hi>John</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſheth into three ſorts, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 16. <hi>The luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eyes, and the pride of life;</hi> that is, Pleaſure, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit, and Honour. An inordinate deſire of theſe things, doth not only come from an evil Principle, but alſo is of ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry evil Conſequence; becauſe it cannot be anſwer'd. Such a Stomach is always craving; and the Wretch that condemns himſelf to the ſlaviſh office of feeding it, cannot with all his drudgeries ſatisfie it; for, inſtead of being filled, it ſtretcheth daily. From theſe boundleſs Deſires pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed a world of moral Evils, which tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Mankind, and diſorder the ſtate of humane Affairs, as Envy, Murmurings, Uncharitableneſs, Strife, and innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſorts of Injuſtice and Oppreſſion: Of all which, none are more apt to be guilty than proud Men, <hi>who enlarge their deſires as hell, and as death, that cannot be ſatisfi'd,</hi> as the Prophet tells us,
<hi>Hab.</hi> 2. 5. Indeed this doth neceſſarily follow; for thoſe inordinate Cravings being both bred and cheriſh'd by the vaſt Opinion
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:106212:46"/> Men have of their own deſerts, they muſt needs think themſelves very hardly uſed by God himſelf; and, conſequently, grudge, and grow impatient, trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and vexatious, if their Merits be not rewarded according to that eſtimate which they themſelves take of them. Nor is ſuch a Reward poſſible to be given; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe whatever their Condition is, ſtill there is ſomething or other in it, which anſwers not expectations. Moderate Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity can bear no manner of proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the unmeaſurable Opinion and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite of a proud Perſon; and therefore it cannot poſſibly ſatisfie him, becauſe the Enjoyments he hath, fall ſo very ſhort of what he thinks he ſhould have. And if God be pleaſed to heap up the things of this World upon him in great abundance, neither doth this pleaſe the vain Wretch ſo as to ſatisfie him to the full, becauſe the opinion of his Merits ſtill ſwells, as his Fortunes grow. His ſingular Acquiſitions he takes as ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of his ſingular Deſervings; and as an argument and ſign of ſomething more behind which he ſhould, and is to have yet; till the Ambition reſembles <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>'s <hi>the Great,</hi> who could not be ſatisfi'd without getting the whole World, nor indeed <hi>with</hi> it: Tho' he had over-run <pb n="81" facs="tcp:106212:47"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:106212:48"/> ſo great a part of it, yet he cry'd for madneſs that there were no more Worlds for him to Conquer. Now, every one may
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> what Miſchiefs come from ſuch wicked Tempers, and the World has e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y day too great reaſon to lament them. They pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y ſhew, That to be of an humble
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ind, is not only a very neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, but an excellent Bleſſing too; that which keeps One from many hurtful Exorbitances, and makes him uncapable of annoying, of being a grievance to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and others: Having a mean Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of his own Worth, he is therefore contented with his outward Fortunes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he thinks them greater than he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves: He is ſatisfi'd with what is need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and that is but little in compariſon, becauſe Nature requires not much, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Vanity creates an Appetite after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things, which might better be ſpar'd, becauſe they are over-charging. And tho' a Man's particular Condition and ſtate of Life does call for more than what is juſt proportionable to the neceſſities of Nature, yet the moſt chargeable ſtations are a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ded with much Exceſs; and many Expences ſhould be retrench'd, which are merely thrown away upon Luxury and
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>utter. Many great Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>niencies and Evils might eaſily be
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:106212:48"/> avoided, would Men but ſuffer their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent Ambition to ſhrink, and their Minds to be govern'd by a Spirit of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility. And, after all, the Laws of it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire us, whatever our outward Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Circumſtances are, to repoſe our Cares in God's Boſom, where all humble Men think them ſo ſafely lodg'd, that there can be no room in their own Breaſts for thoſe tumultuous Deſires, which ſet the World in an uproar: Without acting againſt their own friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Principle, they cannot but reſt in Chriſt's Promiſe, that <hi>all theſe things ſhall be added unto them,</hi> Matth. 6. 33. that is, all the neceſſary things of this Life; and to vex the World and our ſelves about more, is only to be mad to no purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. SECONDLY, Beſides the Advantage an humble Mind yields us by governing and regulating our Deſires, there is this additional Happineſs by it, That it guards us from many hurtful Sins which Pride of Heart leads People to. This is ſuch a fruitful, teeming Vice, that there are not many Sins but what are nearly related to it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Envy, Wrath, Contentiouſneſs, Singulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Intractability, Vain-glory, Avarice, Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoriouſneſs, Affectation of Power, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers other Vices, are either the immediate <pb n="84" facs="tcp:106212:49"/> Iſſue, or the Kindred of This, and all are ſet on work to ſupport it. Any one may ſee how fatally it operates in under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining and ruining the common Comforts of humane Life, together with the Peace and Intereſts of all Societies, whether they be Civil or Sacred. It is Pride of Heart that denies Obedience, that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynts Families, that oppreſſes and tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizes over a Neighbourhood, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbs Kingdoms, that divides Churches, that levies Wars, that forms and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains heterodox Opinions, that violates Order, and (as a ready way to all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Miſchief) that ſtops Mens Ears againſt honeſt and faithful Counſels, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are in their own Thoughts wiſer and better than others, and count it a diminution to be directed. Did Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility take its due place under our Roofs, theſe various Evils would ſoon be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd;
<hi>Hagar</hi> and her Iſſue would be quite caſt out of Doors, or at leaſt, ſecur'd from giving diſturbance. The firſt work of Humility is to mould our Hearts into an obſequious, pliable and pacifick Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.
<hi>With the lowly is wiſdom,</hi> ſays <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> Prov. 11. 2. He means that Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom which is from above, which is pure, peaceable, gentle, eaſie to be intreated, full of Mercy and good Fruits, <hi>without
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:106212:49"/> Partiality, and without Hypocriſie,</hi> as St.
<hi>James</hi> deſcribes it, <hi>James</hi> 3. 17. The truth is, were nothing elſe to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd, but the preſent welfare of Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, an humble Diſpoſition is of ſuch vaſt uſe for the procuring and preſerving of it, that if we might ſuppoſe a Community to conſiſt of the wiſeſt Men that ever were in the World, and that they were to find out and agree amongſt themſelves upon ſome one thing that ſhould be moſt advantageous for the Whole, they could not pitch upon any thing more Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial, more conducing to every One's Good, than the univerſal Practice of this admirable Vertue, which is the ſubject of this Diſcourſe: It diſpoſes Men of all Degrees and Ranks, whether Superiors, Inferiors, or Equals, to behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſo in their reſpective Stations, that Mankind could not chuſe but be very happy even in this Life, were this ſingle Vertue ſincerely practis'd by all, as it ſhould be: It diſpoſes all Governors <hi>to condeſcend to thoſe of low eſtate,</hi> Rom. 12. 16. <hi>To ſhew themſelves in all things pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns of good works,</hi> Tit. 2. 7. To be Miniſters and Servants to the reſt, <hi>even as the Son of Man came not to be miniſtred un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, but to miniſter,</hi> Matth. 20. 27, 28. It diſpoſes ſuch as are to be govern'd, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:106212:50"/> in Church or State, to be <hi>ſubject to the higher Powers,</hi> Rom. 13. 1. To be <hi>ſubject to Principalities; to obey Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates,</hi> Tit. 3. 1. <hi>To ſubmit themſelves to every Ordinance of Man for the Lord's ſake, whether it be to the King as Supreme, or unto Deputies that are ſent by him, for the puniſhment of evil-doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 13, 14. It diſpoſes People that ſtand upon the ſame Level, and are of the ſame Degree, to be
<hi>kindly affectioned one to another in brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly love, in honour preferring one another,</hi> Rom. 12. 10. <hi>Not to do any thing through
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>rife or vain glory, but in lowlineſs of mind, each to eſteem other better than themſelves,</hi> Phil. 2. 3. <hi>To be at peace among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to warn them that are unruly, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort the feeble-minded, to ſupport the weak, to be patient towards all men,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5. 13, 14. In ſhort, the Office of Humility is to caſt out of us the very Offal of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature, to cure us of all imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, ſurly and perverſe Humours, to ſooth and ſoften our Tempers, to animate us with a condeſcending, complaiſant and gentle Spirit; to make us tractable and eaſie, candid and ſweet, benign and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gracious, as it becomes thoſe whoſe mutual Neceſſities require them to ſtoop to each other, to relieve each other, to <pb n="87" facs="tcp:106212:50"/> bear with each others infirmities. And what a happy World would it be, were we all thus minded! Thoſe Vices which annoy and infeſt Mankind, would hardly be ſo much as heard of; to be ſure the miſchievous Effects of them would not be felt ſo as to diſorder all Affairs, and to throw People into ſuch fits of Rage and Diſtraction, as if the World were nothing but a great Hoſpital of Luna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A Spirit of true Humility would be a Sovereign Cure of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe many Evils which the fooliſh Pride of Men naturally brings upon us. And if it ſhall pleaſe God, for particular Reaſons, to ſuffer at any time ſome untoward Accidents to happen, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ich are not immediately and directly of our own
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ſing, an Humble Mind will help us to make ſuch a whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome uſe of them, as to turn that into good Diſcipline, which to fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>dious and intractable Tempers is a very p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>re; which is the laſt Argument of the great uſefulneſs of this Vertue. Among theſe <hi>Accidents,</hi> we may reckon Domeſtick Misfortunes, diſappointments of Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Miſcarriages in Friendſhip, loſs of Liberty, decay or want of Fortunes, and the like, contingent Preſſures, which to <pb n="88" facs="tcp:106212:51"/> Men of unſubdu'd Minds are things very heavy and <hi>grievous to be born.</hi> But
<hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> has rightly obſerv'd, That as <hi>Bees ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Hony out of the drieſt and pricklieſt Herb,</hi> ſo Good Men may draw ſomething that is proper and beneficial for them out of the ſharpeſt Misfortunes: There are no tryals, but what will yield a kindly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, where Art and Induſtry undertakes Improvements: And if Men would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply their minds to this Divine ſort of Chymiſtry, they might at once ſublimate their Natures, and their Delights too, tho' it be by <hi>Fire</hi> ('tis a Proverbial expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> uſes, denoting ſome Difficulty, 1 Cor. 3. 15.) It may be hard perhaps at the firſt, but <hi>Time</hi> and
<hi>Aſſue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi> will help all Men to draw good out of any Evil: Nor are any ſo well prepar'd for it, as Men of humble minds; becauſe idivers things will ſink into their thoughts, which the Hearts of others are too big and too hard for: As, That no Man ought to be maſter of the World, or of his own Fortunes; but that we ſhould rather make our minds pliant and ſuitable to our Condition, whatever that is. If it be Retirement we are confin'd to, the beſt way is to turn it into an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity for Speculation; as,
<hi>Socrates</hi> Philoſophiz'd in Priſon, and <hi>Plato</hi> betook
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:106212:51"/> himſelf to cloſe Studies, when he had fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len under the hatred of <hi>Dionyſius;</hi> And thus Knowledge and Wiſdom might be the Extract of ſuch misfortunes. Again, the World, for great Reaſons is ſubjected to variety of Chances, as Conſort does conſiſt of great diverſity of Notes, which yet ſerve altogether to make Harmony, tho' ſome by themſelves are flat and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant: And why (faith the Humble Man) ſhould the courſe of things be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd for our ſakes, when our Betters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us have had their turns too, and when conſtant Experience ſhews us, that every thing is ſickle and liable to changes, and that the World is no other than a Scene, that for a time pleaſes, but ſoon deceives the Eye; and the conſequent of this Meditation is, That we ſhould ſet our Affections on things above.</p>
            <p>AGAIN, notwithſtanding this diverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and uncertainty of Affairs, if People would but make juſt Compariſons, they might eaſily find, that the meaſure of their Wants bears no proportion to the greatneſs of their Enjoyments. But this is a great fault, That they over-look ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Bleſſings which are under their Eye, and turn their Thoughts looſe and fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitive after ſome little thing that is loſt; <pb n="90" facs="tcp:106212:52"/>
               <hi>Like Children</hi> (ſays <hi>Plutarch</hi>) <hi>who, when a ſingle Toy is taken from them, cry and roar for that, neglecting all other things, which may be of greater value.</hi> 'Tis pity that Men ſhould out-live the Innocence of Childhood, and retain its Follies: If they were govern'd by a Spirit of true Humility, they would make ſuch a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious uſe of thoſe Wants which they count great Miſchances, as to be thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to God, that they are not greater nor more.</p>
            <p>FURTHER yet; ſuppoſe One's Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes to be great indeed, an humble Mind will direct him to conſider whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther other Mens do not equal, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps exceed them: Few indeed take ſuch an eſtimate of them, becauſe they do not create ſuch an acute and home-pain, as the little Thorn which is in One's own Fleſh. But we ſee Afflictions are every where; and ſince they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all Mankind, Humility teaches us to take it for our Comfort, that we are not ſingular; and, inſtead of Murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to expreſs our Gratitude by Works of Charity and Compaſſion to our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours: This is to make a good uſe of God's Diſpenſations; and to all this we are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by an humble Mind.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:106212:52"/> AND yet, laſtly, there is one thing more, which I ſhould not forget or omit; and it is, That we ſhould ſet our Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on things above, not on theſe earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly matters. I have often thought on the Philoſopher's Notion, <hi>That the readieſt way to be rich is, not to enlarge One's E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, but to limit and pinion the Deſires:</hi> And this is the ready way to be happy alſo, to keep our Minds from roving, and to confine them to the things which are at home before us. When Misfortunes diſquiet us, the great fault is within our ſelves, becauſe we want much of the Stoick, as well as of the Chriſtian, and place Felicity, not in the Practice of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, but in outward foreign Acquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And this is the reaſon that we are ſo troubled about them, and dejected when we miſs them; whereas we ſhould rather apply our Minds to that one thing neceſſary, which is always ready at hand, and never to be taken away without our own conſent.</p>
            <p>HUMILITY prompts us to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove our Spiritual State by the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations of God in every mortifying Condition; to grow Wiſer or Better by them, to become the more Meek, the <pb n="92" facs="tcp:106212:53"/> more Patient, the more Devout, the more mindful of our whole Duty to God and Man.</p>
            <p>AND if we be careful to anſwer the Ends of the Divine Providence to us af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this humble manner, tho' the things which the World thirſteth after fall to a low ebb, we ſhall have Waters e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough within our own Ciſterns to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh our Souls, till we get to thoſe Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of Pleaſure, which are at God's Right-hand for evermore.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:106212:53"/>
            <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>The Suitableneſs of Humility to the Mind of Chriſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HAVING conſider'd the great Uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of this Vertue in ſeveral Reſpects, as a very powerful Argument to inforce the Practice of it, I ſhould now put an end to that part of this Diſcourſe, but that there remaineth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind yet one Conſideration more, which ought to be the moſt affecting and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, becauſe it is to be drawn from the great Exemplar of all Holineſs, the Lord Jeſus; whoſe own Humility is a Pattern which he ſeems to have ſingled out from the reſt of his Vertues, for the more pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar imitation of his Diſciples. Leſt the Grandees of the World, the Mighty and the Noble, ſhould account this Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue an unmanly Habit, and look upon it with a diſdaining Eye, as a thing infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely beneath them, the Son of God was pleas'd to Dignifie it with a ſingular Honour, and to make it Glorious by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robing himſelf with it, and by expreſſing his own great Eſteem of it to the very laſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:106212:54"/> THESE three things ſhew the ſtupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous Nature of his Humility: 1. His wonderful Incarnation. 2. His outward Condition of Life. 3. His dying upon the Croſs.</p>
            <p n="1">1. FIRST, His wonderful Incarnation. In the Second
<hi>Chapter</hi> of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> where the Apoſtle does with ſuch Earneſtneſs and Zeal con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure us to be humble-minded, he makes uſe of Chriſt's own Example, as the moſt operative and irreſiſtible Argument; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe antecedent to his Conception in the Holy Virgin's Womb, he was a Divine Perſon, actually having the Divine Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, really ſubſiſting in the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, full of the Divine Majeſty, and of all the Glories which are Eſſential to the Deity. <hi>In him dwelt all the fulneſs of the God-head Bodily,</hi> (that is, truly, really, and ſubſtantially) as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks,
<hi>Col.</hi> 2. 9. This is the meaning of thoſe words, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 6. Chriſt <hi>being in the form of God, thought it no robbery to be equal with God,</hi> (meaning, by Identity of Nature.) Notwithſtanding which moſt glorious State, he emptied himſelf, taking the form of a Servant, being made in the likeneſs of Men; for that is the literal exact ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:106212:54"/> of the words, <hi>Verſe</hi> 7. This was moſt aſtoniſhing Humility! Deity and Manhood are things ſo vaſtly diſtant, and the Diſtance between the Perfections of the one, and the Infirmities of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is ſo infinite, that the Son of God's Condeſcention in taking humane Nature upon him, is impoſſible to be expreſs'd, or comprehended. God's being manifeſted in the Fleſh, is one of thoſe Myſteries which Angels themſelves deſire to look into; ſtooping and bowing down, to pry into it, as the <hi>Greek</hi> word ſignifies, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 12. Where the Apoſtle alludes to the golden Cherubims upon the Ark, which hover'd
<hi>with their wings over the Mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeat, with their faces one toward another,</hi> Exod. 37. 9. When the Power of the Higheſt over ſhadow'd the Virgin, ſo that God became Incarnate, a humane Body was prepar'd him, that he might be in a fit ſtate to tranſact the Mediator's Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, which he had undertaken between his Father and Mankind. This was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a neceſſary part of the Divine Oeco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomy, to bring about the great Ends of the <hi>New Covenant.</hi> But yet the Son of God's ſubmitting to the vile condition of Humanity, is his ſubjecting himſelf there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to the natural Weakneſſes, Wants and Paſſions of humane Fleſh, was a far <pb n="96" facs="tcp:106212:55"/> greater act of Humility than when he humbled himſelf to Death; which yet the Apoſtle reflected on with ſuch Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. For a Man to die, is the conſequent of Nature; and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the death is, it is no ſuch wonder, as for God to be made Fleſh. This was ſuch a reconciling of Extremes, as could not be brought about, but by ſtepping down to the very loweſt degree of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inanition and Abaſement.</p>
            <p n="2">2. AGREEABLE hereunto was the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequent Condition of his Life, from the Womb to the Grave: All along ſo hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in every Reſpect, that the World might eaſily ſee his Intentions were, to baniſh all Pride out of the World, and to ſhew what a deſpicable thing humane Glory is in the account of God, whoſe own Glory conſiſts in the adorable Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of his Nature. To be entitled to ſuch mean Parentage, to take up with ſuch poor Fortunes, to be born in the Stable of an Inn, to be wrapp'd in the courſeſt Faſhion, to be laid in a Manager; to appear in ſuch an abject, deſpicable Condition, and to make it One's choice too, few (if any) of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Race would ſtoop to this, were their Lots at their own diſpoſal; and yet this was the Condition <pb n="97" facs="tcp:106212:56"/> which the moſt bleſſed Son of God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignedly took upon himſelf. Eight Days after his Nativity he ſubmitted to Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion, which was an argument of Mens Hereditary Pollutions, as well as the Seal of God's Covenant, with the
<hi>Jews:</hi> And by humbling, himſelf to the bloody ſtroke of the Knife, he ſhew'd, that tho' he was perfectly Innocent, yet he took on him the guilt of our Sins, as well as the ſhame (I had almoſt ſaid the ſcandal) of the extreameſt Poverty. St. <hi>Luke</hi> tells us, that he was ſubject to his Parents, <hi>Luke</hi> 2. 5. And the Tradition is very Ancient, that as he grew up, he wrought together with his reputed, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his Manual Occupation, tho' he could have fed his Mother and him by Miracles; but he did no Miracle till he was thirty Years old, and then thoſe Works were for the Confirmation of his Doctrines, and to prove his Divine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority: And after
<hi>Joſeph</hi>'s death (which, it's thought, was a conſiderable time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he began to Preach) 'tis believ'd that he us'd the Trade alone for his own and his Mother's ſupport; making Yokes and Ploughs, (ſays <hi>Juſtin Martyr</hi>) for which reaſon he was afterwards call'd, not only <hi>the Carpenter's Son,</hi> but <hi>the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penter,</hi> Mark 6. 3. As he was firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal'd <pb n="98" facs="tcp:106212:57"/> to Shepherds, ſo his Retinue after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards conſiſted of Fiſhermen, and ſuch like humble People, whoſe Meanneſs the better fitted them to be Examples of what he ſaid in his Sermon on the Mount, <hi>Bleſſed are the poor in Spirit, for theirs is the Kingdom of God,</hi> Matth. 5. 3. Indeed the Labours of his Hands ceas'd as ſoon as he enter'd on his Miniſterial Office: Then he liv'd by the Hands of others; which manner of living, tho' it was grounded upon an eternal Principle of Juſtice, becauſe <hi>the work-man is worthy of his meat,</hi> as he ſaid himſelf, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10. 10. yet in him it was an expreſſion of great Humility, becauſe he took all Miniſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to him as things precarious, even from the hands of thoſe who confeſs'd him to be the Son of God, the Lord of all: And at the ſame time when his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities requir'd him to make uſe of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, that he might for ever diſgrace all inordinate love of it, he thought that vile Perſon the propereſt to carry the Bag, who was a Thief and a Traitor. His whole Life was a conſtant ſtate of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, having not (of his own) where to lay his Head, after it was lifted up out of the Manger; nor was that poor reſting place his own neither. His patient bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Aſperſions and Reproach (the uſual <pb n="99" facs="tcp:106212:57"/> conſequents of a needy Condition) was a further argument ſtill of the great Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility of his Heart. High Stomachs are apt to be ſtimulated to that degree by one ſharp treatment, that ſometimes no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can allay, but a glut of Revenge; life it ſelf falls a ſacrifice for it; and a little detraction is too often made the Price of Blood. When the Lord Jeſus was revil'd, he did not at all revile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 23. but endur'd before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand Crucifixion in his Name: A Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton and a Wine-bibber, a Friend of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans and Sinners, a Samaritan, a Daemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niack, an Inſtrument of <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verter of the Nation: Theſe and the like Calumnies were Prefatory to that ſpightful Libel on the Croſs, <hi>This is the King of the Jews;</hi> and yet he bore all theſe Reproaches with the ſame Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Evenneſs of Mind, wherewith he bore the ſolemn pompous Mockery of the Reed and Purple Robe; formalities intended, not to inaugurate, but to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie him. 'Tis true, theſe (tho' very great) Indignities, did neither wound his Fleſh, nor hurt his Skin; and ſo in that reſpect were more tolerable than the Buffettings, the Scourgings, the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronary Thorns, which were a part of the Epilogue. This was ſuch a ſtrange Form <pb n="100" facs="tcp:106212:58"/> for the Son of God to take upon him, that <hi>Pilate</hi> himſelf, tho' he knew nothing of his Divinity, ſhew'd him to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as an amazing Spectacle, <hi>Behold the Man,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>John</hi> 19. 5. His ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to ſuch ſhameful Scourgings and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacerations exceeded his ſtooping down to the Baſon of Water, to waſh his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Feet, before he was apprehended: And yet that was an act of Humility, which our Saviour himſelf intended, as an Eminent Example for the very greateſt in his Church to follow; that they ſhould do as he did unto them; becauſe <hi>the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant is not greater than his Lord; neither he that is ſent, greater than he that ſent him,</hi> John 13. 15,
16.</p>
            <p>AND yet Thirdly, There is one thing behind ſtill, which was more than this; and that was his preparing a Lavatory for the whole World, by pouring out not Water only, but Blood too, and that upon the Croſs. St.
<hi>Paul</hi> mentions this as the moſt ſignal and ſtupendous Act of Humility, that he ſubmitted even to Crucifixion; which was not only the moſt Cruel, but the moſt Opprobrious kind of Puniſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:106212:58"/> AMONG the <hi>Jews</hi> a particular Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction went along with Suſpenſion, tho' the Criminal did not expire and die by it, but was expos'd upon a Gibbet, after he had ſuffer'd death ſome other way. For the Law of God gave them no Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to take any Man's Life by this ſort of Puniſhment. It only impower'd them, after they had ſtoned or ſtrangled a Malefactor, to hang his breathleſs Body up for ſhame and example ſake; and that Ignominy was inflicted only upon Blaſphemers, Idolaters, and the like. It was a ſign that ſuch Criminals were un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a particular Curſe; <hi>for he that is hanged, is accurſed of God,</hi> ſaith the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, <hi>Deut.</hi> 21. 23. This his Suſpenſion was not the cauſe, but the ſign of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accurſed, a token of the Malediction, an argument that he was deteſted by the God of Purity; that he was look'd upon as one not fit to tread upon the Earth, and therefore was hang'd up in the Air, leſt he ſhould defile the Land; and thence was to be thrown under Ground, in all haſte, the very ſame day, as an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Creature, that deſerv'd preſently to be remov'd out of the Peoples view. <hi>If a man have committed a ſin worthy of death, and he be put to death, and thou hang him <pb n="102" facs="tcp:106212:59"/> on a tree, his body ſhall not remain all night upon the tree, but thou ſhalt in any wiſe bury him that day;</hi> ſo the Law runs, <hi>Deut.</hi> 21. 22, 23. And ſome learned <hi>Jews</hi> tell us, That even the Tree on which ſuch a Malefactor was expos'd, was to be bury'd with him; and ſo the Stone wherewith he had been ſtoned, or the Sword where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he had been cut off, or the Napkin wherewith he had been ſtrangled, all was to be put into the Earth with him; and all this to ſhew, what a vile and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable thing he was in the account of God. Now by this the wonderful Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the Lord Jeſus appears, that he was pleas'd to ſubmit to that reproach and ſhame which was due to thoſe, and to thoſe only, who were particularly cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Had the Ignominy been all his Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering; had he not undergone the Pains, the Torments, the Death of the curſed Tree, his condeſcending to take up the Opprobrious part was without Parallel, and beyond all poſſibility of Example, conſidering the Innocence of his whole Life, the Dignity and Greatneſs of his Perſon, and his own voluntary ſuſcep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the moſt Infamous Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:106212:59"/> AND yet this is an additional Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, That it was the Ignominy of the <hi>Croſs;</hi> which was a Roman Inſtrument of Death and Shame, diſtinct and different from thoſe that were ordinarily in uſe among God's People; nay, an Inſtrument which had a peculiar Ignominy belonging to it. The Law of God equally reach'd all Men that were obnoxious to the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty: The <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> had a Power of bringing them all indifferently under the Malediction of the Gibbet: But among the <hi>Romans</hi> Crucifixion was a <hi>ſervile Puniſhment</hi> (as 'twas often call'd) a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachful Death appointed for the moſt foeculent part of Mankind, chiefly for Slaves, and more eſpecially for ſuch of them as ran away from the ſervice of their Lords, or plotted their Lord's ruine, or privily carried Information againſt them to the Magiſtrate. Fugitives, Traitors, Sycophants, and ſuch infamous, abject Villains, were wont to be executed upon Croſſes, as Dog; too ſometimes were. Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry rarely did any Free man of <hi>Rome</hi> ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer after that manner, unleſs he was found to be a Robber, an aſſaſſine, or a Forger of Deeds. In ſhort, it was ſuch a baſe, diſgraceful Puniſhment, that the firſt Chriſtian Emperor <hi>Conſtantine the Great,</hi> 
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:106212:60"/> took away the further uſe of it, becauſe the Saviour of the World had ſuffer'd the ſhame of it in his Perſon. Lord! what a low ſtep of Condeſcenſion was This? That He, who was in the form of God, cloath'd with Majeſty and Honour from everlaſting: That He, who thought it no Robbery to be equal with God (it was a Dignity which he had a Natural Right unto) that He ſhould not only conceal this his Greatneſs, and appear in the ſhape and faſhion of a Man, but ſhould moreover take on him the form of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, the moſt contemptible Man, and at laſt ſubmit to the Puniſhment of the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt and moſt proffigate Slave! No Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der can exceed or come near this; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it be, that ſinful wretched Man ſhould be proud, when God himſelf was pleas'd to be thus humble.</p>
            <p>ONE would think, that if haughty People would but reflect with one Eye upon their own ſtate, and with the other behold the moſt Holy
<hi>Jeſus,</hi> they could not but be abaſh'd to find ſo abſurd a diſſimilitude; themſelves glittering like ſo many Morning-Stars, with a borrow'd Light; and the Sun of Righteouſneſs wading in an Eclipſe all along from his firſt Riſing to his Bed. 'Twere ſtrange,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:106212:60"/> if ſhame did not cover their Faces at laſt; if a Compariſon ſo very unequal were not enough to baffle a fooliſh Vice; if this alone were ot of ſufficient force, not only to ſupplant its Credit and Intereſt in the World, but to put it out of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance alſo. As there never was any Sorrow, ſo never was there any Humility like his, for Quality and for Degree too: Nor indeed is any ſuch proportion ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected of us; tho' according to humane Reaſoning, our Meaſure, as to this, ought (if poſſible) to exceed. The Son of God could not but know his own Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Excellencies: He could not but be conſcious of the infinite Glories of his Divine Nature, and of the Perfections of his Humanity too, by means of its Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatical Union with the Deity. Upon this account, had he ſet himſelf out, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his true, intrinſick Worth, all the Splendor in the World had been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely ſhort of his juſt Due. But his Buſineſs here was not to appear as the Son of God, but to act as a Mediator, as our Subſtitute and Proxy. Accordingly, as he put on our courſe Clothing, ſo from the Manger to the Croſs he wrap'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf up in ſuch a mean Diſguiſe, as was ſuitable to the great Deſign upon which he came out of his Father's Boſom. When <pb n="106" facs="tcp:106212:61"/> he ſaid to his Diſciples, <hi>I am lowly in heart,</hi> he ſpake as the Son of Man, that was not to make a pompous ſhew of the Glory he had from everlaſting, but was to live in an obſcure Condition, to end his Life with Contumely and Diſgrace, and throughout the whole courſe of his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inanition, was to act and ſuffer below his Great Self, beneath his Dignity. In all this he was a charming Pattern to his Followers, that we ſhould learn of him to ſtep low, and to walk in that lowly manner, which, tho' it was beneath him, is very fit for us; anſwerable to things of our low ſize, very ſuitable to Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, whoſe firſt Principles are Duſt and Clay, and whoſe fall would have ſunk us lower by far than into our original Earth, had not the Son of God humbled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo, as to come down from Heaven, and to deſcend into Hell too for us. In him, Humility was a Degradation; in us, it is a ſtanding upon our own proper and due Level: Which makes the Example carry the greater force, becauſe it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes to us, not any ſort of Condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſtrictly and rightly ſo call'd (much leſs ſuch Condeſcention as was in the Lord of Life and Glory) but ſuch low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs of Heart as is proportionable to our true Quality and Deſerts; and, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:106212:61"/> agreeable to the Laws of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice.</p>
            <p>I told you before, That Humility con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in a fair and equal Opinion of One's own ſelf, according to his exact Rate and intrinſick Value: And ſuch an Opinion muſt needs be very mean and low, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if we take a true eſtimate of what we really have, and of what we really are, we cannot find in our ſelves any thing conſiderable, ſetting our Demerits and Guilt aſide; to be ſure, nothing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable enough to out weigh, or balance that Guilt. So that every touch of Pride is ſo far the exalting of One's ſelf above meaſure, which is therefore the more Criminal, becauſe it is a direct Affront to the Saviour of the World, whoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathomable Humility was intended for an everlaſting Law, to exact of Mankind the profoundeſt Submiſſions, ſince he, the Son of God, was pleas'd to ſet ſo great a Price upon the Duty, by becoming a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedent to us in his own moſt Sacred Perſon.</p>
            <p>AND now, what ſhall we ſay more to encourage or oblige us to the Practice of it? A Vertue ſo graceful in its own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo deſirable for it ſelf; a Vertue <pb n="108" facs="tcp:106212:62"/> that is juſtifi'd upon ſo many Principles of common Reaſon; a Vertue ſo adap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to our great Neceſſities; a Vertue ſo inſtrumental towards our greateſt Good; a Vertue ſo productive of all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriour Peace and Complacency, ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and uſeful for our growth in Grace, ſuch a ſecurity and defence againſt the Malignity of outward Accidents: Laſtly, a Vertue ſo Divine and Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for its near Relation to the only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of God, the Author and Finiſher of our Faith: This ſo excellent a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection carries with it ſuch preſent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, as are not to be exceeded but by the actual Poſſeſſion of that moſt bleſſed State which is as yet in futurity: The truth is, Humility of Mind is a very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Preparative for it. The Lord Jeſus, who came down from Heaven, knew beſt what Vertues and Diſpoſitions of Soul are neceſſary for us, in order to our happy being there. He has not given us ſo many Precepts in vain, nor are his Commands only to try and exerciſe our Obedience. Nay, the Duties he exacts of us are not purely Conditions neither, things fix'd by the mere Pleaſure of God, without which we <hi>ſhall</hi> not be happy. We <hi>cannot</hi> be truly happy without them; without them our Nature is not capable <pb n="109" facs="tcp:106212:62"/> of the Felicities which are above. They are therefore both neceſſary Conditions, and ſuitable Qualifications too; proper, genuine and kindly Preparations to fit and diſpoſe us for a Heavenly ſtate: And of theſe noble Qualifications, an humble Temper is one; it has a direct and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Tendency to fit us for that Place, where there has been no room ſince <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifer</hi>'s Apoſtacy (nor ever will be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain) for
<hi>Lucifer</hi>'s Vice, the damn'd O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal of Strife, Paſſion, and Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
            <p>A lowly Heart is fix'd and ready for the Works in Heaven, to admire and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore the Father of Spirits, and to fall down proſtrate before him; to glorifie him in the bleſſed Choir of Angels; to bleſs him for our being written in the Lamb's Book of Life; to praiſe him for being counted worthy of the leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Glory; to rejoyce that others have their ſhare of it alſo; to triumph for being found at the Feet of God's Saints, as <hi>Ignatius</hi> the Martyr wiſh'd he might be found in Chriſt's Kingdom at the Feet of St. <hi>Paul;</hi> to joyn with all the Spirits of juſt Men made Perfect, in a Life of everlaſting Harmony; to live on to everlaſting Ages in the raviſhing En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainments <pb n="110" facs="tcp:106212:63"/> of a ſerene and delightful World, in a fix'd and unchangeable ſtate of Reſt and Peace, of Order and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, of Joy and Love, continually ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company'd with <hi>Hallelujah's</hi> and <hi>Hoſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah's,</hi> and the profoundeſt Adorations: Theſe will be our Works in Heaven when it ſhall pleaſe God to bring us thither, and we endeavour our ſelves to go. And all theſe Works Humility of Mind does naturally ſerve to fit and diſpoſe us for: Which ſhews, that we cannot take a more Religious and Prudent courſe now, than to work our ſtiff and ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Hearts into an humble Temper, and to apply them to the conſtant exerciſe of thoſe things which help at once both to expreſs and to increaſe it. For as all Habits are acquir'd by the daily repetiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſingle acts, ſo are they confirm'd and increas'd by it.</p>
            <p>THIS, as well as other Vertues, grows by degrees, by our uſing our ſelves to the familiar Practice of it. The more we exerciſe acts of Humility, and the more frequent thoſe acts are, the more humble do our Minds become: He that is lowly, will thereby be the more low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtill; due Expreſſions are both the Signs of an humble Diſpoſition, and the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:106212:63"/> Inſtrumental Cauſes of its Increment. For which reaſon I ſhall not enlarge this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, by directing you, under a diſtinct particular Head, to the proper means of Humility (tho' it would be a very Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical Method) but for the greater bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, ſhall chuſe rather to proceed to that which I propos'd as the Third and laſt General, <hi>viz.</hi> To ſhew after what manner we are to expreſs this great Chriſtian Vertue; which, I preſume, will ſerve inſtead of all, as arguments and tokens of Humility, and as means of it likewiſe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <pb n="112" facs="tcp:106212:64"/>
            <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>How Humility is to be expreſt, as by ſerving the Honour of God.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. NOW the firſt and nobleſt Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a lowly Heart is, to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it ſelf to thoſe things which are for the Honour of God. If it be the part of all humble Men, in honour, to preferr one another,
<hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 10. certainly no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be ſo neceſſary and proper for them, as to ſeek God's Honour, to do the things that are for God's Honour, and to preferr God's Honour before and above all. This is a moſt genuine act of Humility, becauſe we are infinitely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him; derive all from him, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend every minute upon him; as the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Author of our being, the ſole Arbiter and Diſpoſer of our Fortunes. Upon this account, to do the things which are for his Honour is very natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral to an humble Soul, poſſeſt with a ſence of his Glory and Excellencies, of his Dominion and Authority over all, and of the inexhauſtible Riches of his Goodneſs and Love to Mankind. And <pb n="113" facs="tcp:106212:64"/> as this is an argument of Humility, ſo it is a good means to amplifie and improve it. For the more we are concern'd for God's Honour, and the more we intend it, the more we muſt needs think on him, and the more ſenſible ſtill we muſt needs be of the reaſons of this our Duty to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him.</p>
            <p>HE is hereby the more before our Eyes; his Perfections hereby appear e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day to us the more Glorious; the vaſt diſtance between his infinite Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and us poor contemptible Creatures, begets in us ſtill the greater Reverence; his Power ſtrikes us with the more piercing awe; the Conſideration of his All-ſufficiency aboundeth the more; and the ſence we have of his Mercy, Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Truth increaſeth daily. In ſhort, the more we entertain our Souls with Contemplations of God's Greatneſs, the more we find our ſelves obliged to honour him; and the more we ſtudy to do that, the lower are our Souls apt to ſink under the due apprehenſion of our own meanneſs. Now, for the better ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing our ſelves as to this matter, we muſt note, That there are divers ways of ſerving God's Honour; at preſent I ſhall mention only theſe Five.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:106212:65"/>
               <item> I. BY aſcribing unto God all the Good we have.</item>
               <item>II. BY making him ſuch humble Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns, as may in ſome meaſure teſtifie our Obligations to him.</item>
               <item>III. BY devoting our ſelves to his Worſhip.</item>
               <item>IV. BY giving our ſelves up to his Diſpoſal.</item>
               <item>V. BY depending upon him, and truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him, in reference to all Events: And by every one of theſe ways of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God's Honour, muſt we expreſs our Humility.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. BY aſcribing unto God all the Good we have. There is no ſuch Child of a Man, as he who becomes his own flatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; who is ſo full of himſelf, as if he were the Maker and Maſter of his own Fortunes. And yet the Folly would be the more pardonable, were it attended with the Innocence of a Child. But in this there is a mixture of Sacrilege with Vanity, becauſe ſuch Paraſites rob God of his Glory, to beſtow it at home. This
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:106212:65"/> is the ridiculous Sin of aſſuming Spirits, That they engroſs the Honour that ſhould be return'd to the Divine Being; <hi>they ſacrifice to their own nets, and burn in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe to their own drags,</hi> as the expreſſion is, <hi>Hab.</hi> 1. 16. That is, give themſelves the praiſe of all, either as the ſole, rightful Proprietors, or, at leaſt, as Partners and Sharers with God. <hi>Is not this great Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon that I have built, for the houſe of the kingdom, by the might of my power, and for the honour of my majeſty?</hi> ſaid that haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Prince, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4. 30. Anſwerable to which is the echo you may hear from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very proud Heart: Are not theſe the Perfections that I have wrought? Are not theſe the Excellencies that I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved? Are not theſe the Rewards that I have purchaſed? Nay, is not that the Heaven too, which I have merited and bought? When this Vice groweth ſo rank in the Mind, ſo high and ſtrong, it is a plain argument, that the Soil is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry bad, and that good Husbandry hath been wanting, ſince the evil One ſowed the Tare. An humble Heart is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily productive of all ſelf-denial: 'Tis the moſt indiſpoſed, moſt unapt thing in the World to exalt it ſelf, and eſpecially to magnifie it ſelf againſt the Lord, as the Prophet ſpeaks,
<hi>Jer.</hi> 48. 26. Becauſe <pb n="116" facs="tcp:106212:66"/> it is <hi>in him that we live, and move, and have our beings,</hi> Acts 17. 28. Becauſe the whole diſpoſing of the Lot is of the Lord, however it be caſt into the Lap,
<hi>Prov.</hi> 16. 33. Becauſe <hi>every good gift, and every perfect, is from above, and cometh down from the Father of lights,</hi> James 1. 17. Becauſe we all live (the very beſt and greateſt of us) upon God's Providence, and ſtand indebted to his Goodneſs for all that we enjoy, and for all that we hope for; it is a moſt natural act of an humble Soul, to aſcribe all we have, and all we expect to have, to him whoſe Mercy is over all his Works. <hi>Not unto us, O Lord, not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, but unto thy Name give the praiſe, for thy mercy, and for thy truth ſake,</hi> ſaid the
<hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> 115. 1. <hi>By the Grace of God I am what I am,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul.</hi> And again, <hi>Not I, but the Grace of God which was with me,</hi> 1 Cor. 15. 10. And again, <hi>By Grace are ye ſaved, through Faith, and yet not of your ſelves; it is the gift of God: Not of works, leſt any man ſhould boaſt,</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ. 2. 8, 9. Theſe are very humbling Reflections, that we are Debtors to God's Goodneſs, for all our Enjoyments; for thoſe Advantages which are moſt valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and excellent. And this affords us a ſure Rule to go by; on every occaſion to give God the Praiſe and Glory of all. <pb n="117" facs="tcp:106212:66"/> What-ever thoſe things be, which are ready to puff vain People up; whether they be natural Endowments of the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy or the Mind: Whether they be acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental Acquiſitions, ſuch as a plentiful Fortune, worldly Greatneſs, popular E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem, and the like: Or, whether they be moral Accompliſhments and Perfections, whereby we become wiſer and better than other Men: Still to look up to God as our Creditor and Benefactor, and with religious Baſhfulneſs and Modeſty to ſlide away from all danger of ſelf-aſſuming, to beat off every Temptation, and every riſing of the Heart towards it. Indeed it would be well for us, to cover and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal theſe things from our own view: But if we find that too hard a Task (as ſometimes it is) to blind and cozen our Eyes by ſuch an honeſt Artifice, we ſhould remember, That the Office of every hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Man is to look, not ſo much on his own things, as on the things of others,
<hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 4. that is, others that excel us. To compare our ſelves, not with our ſelves, or with thoſe behind us, but with ſuch as out-do and out-ſtrip us; and when we turn our Eyes homeward, to look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the black Feet, as well as upon the gawdy Plumes; this would be a proper way to make us ſink into a juſt propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <pb n="118" facs="tcp:106212:67"/> and to deſtroy all that Loftineſs, which at every turn is apt to ſhoot out of the Mind on a ſudden, like <hi>Jonah</hi>'s Gourd; which was ſtiff and ſhady for the time, but the leſs valuable, becauſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to be ſmitten with a little Worm. Any juſt Reflection is enough to ſpoil and ruine that high Conceit, which vain Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons entertain of their Accompliſhments and Perfections; becauſe many times they are but imaginary; and when they are real, the Honour muſt be given where it is due; namely, to that Supreme Being, who <hi>giveth to all men liberally, and upbraideth not,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>James</hi> 1. 5. 'Tis no reproach to receive at God's Hands: The only thing wherewith Men are upbraided is, That they arrogate to themſelves the Bleſſings they receive, as if their own Hands had created them. Therefore to expreſs your Humility, and at the ſame time to increaſe it, keep your Minds full of God; make him the Theme for your Meditations, that he may be the Object of your Fear and Love: Let the ſenſe of his Goodneſs abide, and dwell with you continually. Conſider what you are, by whoſe Grace and Bounty you are ſo; and what you have, which you did not receive; and in all your actions be ſure to manifeſt the great
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:106212:67"/> ſenſe you have of his Divine Providence, of whoſe Mercy alone it is, that you are not worſe than nothing. This is to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour God after an humble manner, and to expreſs your Humility indeed; to exalt him in your Hearts, and him only; to caſt down all Imaginations, and every high Thought before him; to make his Name and his Praiſe Glorious in that Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his, which the Devil would have you deſecrate, by ſetting up an Idol in God's room.</p>
            <p n="2">2. SECONDLY, Another way of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving God's Honour, and conſequently, of expreſſing the lowlineſs of your Hearts is, to make him ſuch humble Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns, as may in ſome meaſure teſtifie your Obligations to him Where there is a true and thorough ſenſe of that, the next natural Thought will be that Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Enquiry of <hi>David</hi>'s, <hi>What ſhall I render unto the Lord, for all his benefits towards me?</hi> Pſalm
116. 12. Conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that we derive all from him, and owe all to him, it is highly reaſonable for us to make ſuch Retributions, as are argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and ſignifications of his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Goodneſs over all, and of our daily Dependance upon him. This was the Ground and Original of thoſe Sacred
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:106212:68"/> Rites and Solemnities, which thinking Men in all Ages of the World found themſelves obliged to uſe, by the Laws of Natural, as well as Revealed Religion. The rearing of Altars, the offering of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, the building of Temples, the paying of Vows, the hallowing of Times, the ſetting apart of Lands, the preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Firſt Fruits, the ſanctifying of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the uſe of Muſical Inſtruments, and all thoſe great and coſtly Solemnities which were thought moſt ſuitable to the Divine Majeſty, and moſt proper to ſet forth the Honour of it; they were all inſtituted out of a juſt Senſe, and in hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Acknowledgment of God's Abſolute Right and Sovereignty over all. They were the beſt outward Returns poor Creatures could make him, for his inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſtible Goodneſs to Mankind; and as the Senſe of it increaſed upon the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgation of the Goſpel, ſo the Zeal of lowly Hearts increas'd with it. Their only Ambition was, who ſhould do moſt for God's Honour; and who ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect the nobleſt Monuments of Pious and Thankful Minds. From Age to Age Humility was ſedulouſly working; till, firſt in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and then in other Churches, ſacrilegious Hands laid hold on ſome of God's Propriety, to <pb n="121" facs="tcp:106212:68"/> maintain Voluptuouſneſs and Pride, and threw away a great deal, even of the Shew-bread of the Sanctuary among Dogs.</p>
            <p>IT would be in vain in this degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Age to tell Men, what they ſhould do, as to things of this Nature. But, God's Honour is to be ſerved ſtill; nor are we any more excus'd from Offices of Gratitude and profound Reſpect, than our Fore-fathers were. There are eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Laws of Reaſon, which oblige us to render all poſſible Acknowledgments to the Great Maker, Governour and Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer of all things; nor is any thing more becoming Men of humble Minds and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers. His great Name is ſtill to be had in Honour; his Day to be kept Holy unto him; his Word to be reverenc'd and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey'd; the Seals of his Covenant with us to be uſed ſo, as may be moſt for his Glory; his Houſe to be frequented as the Houſe of Prayer; and his Service there to be perform'd with that Gravity and Decorum, with that Order and Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, with that Fervour and Zeal, with that Devotion and Preſence of Mind, as becometh People that appear in the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of that infinite Being who is to judge us at the laſt Day, and to Reward <pb n="122" facs="tcp:106212:69"/> us all according to our Works. Had we all right Notions of God, and did we daily conſider what worthleſs, neceſſitous Beings our ſelves are; that wait upon God, as the meaneſt Animals do, that he may give us our Meat in due ſeaſon; that are troubled preſently, when God hides his Face; that die and return to our Duſt, when God takes away our Breath: Were nothing but this to be conſidered, the Power of common natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Conſcience would be enough to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble us into a readineſs of making ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributions of Gratitude, as I have now mentioned.</p>
            <p n="3">3. AND the ſame Power of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence would bring us daily upon our Knees, and lay us proſtrate on the Earth, to adore him, to praiſe him for the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his Majeſty, to implore his great Compaſſion, and to give him Thanks for the conſtant Operations of his Mercy; which is the third way of ſerving his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. By theſe acts of Worſhip we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare our belief, that God is a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excellent Being; of ſuch Perfections in his Nature, as render him an Object moſt worthy of all Adorations: By theſe acts we confeſs, that he hearkens to all our Addreſſes; that he is able to anſwer all <pb n="123" facs="tcp:106212:69"/> our Wants; that he is ready to receive our Invocations, and to fulfil our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires; and that our concerns are entirely in his Hand, and at his Diſpoſal. The ſence we have of his Omniſcience, Power, Goodneſs, Wiſdom, and Providence over all, gives life and breath to our Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; and therefore he ſaith himſelf, <hi>whoſo offereth me thanks and praiſe, he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth me,</hi> Pſalm 50. 23. Now, none are ſo kindly condition'd for all this, as People of lowly Hearts; becauſe they are moſt poſſeſt with the admiration of God's Excellencies; moſt apprehenſive of his All-ſufficiency; moſt ſenſible of their own Defects and Indigencies; moſt apt to betake themſelves to him, and to run under his Wings for Shelter and Protection. This therefore being ſo natural to humble Spirits, we cannot bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter expreſs this great Vertue, than by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting our Souls to the Love of God's Worſhip; by giving our Minds to it, by making it as Solemn as we can, by ſuch external acts of Reverence as are the ordinary ſignifications of a lowly Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition; and exemplary too in their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, that others may thereby learn how to glorifie God, as well as we. A careleſs and ſupine behaviour, as if the worſhipping of God were an indifferent, <pb n="124" facs="tcp:106212:70"/> nay, a trifling matter, a ſleepy Eye, an inflexible Body, and ſuch like anomalous, odd Figures which ſome People make, are as unſuitable in a Chriſtian Oratory, as changing of Money was in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and for this reaſon ought to be caſt out, becauſe inſtead of expreſſing a ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and low Opinion of One's own ſelf, they rather argue Men to have very mean and contemptuous Thoughts of God. <hi>O come,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, let us worſhip, and fall down, and kneel before the Lord our Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker.</hi> Due Notions of an Omnipotent Creator; a due remembrance of the Duſt, out of which we were formed, and into which we ſhall return; and due Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the Hand which hath kept us from dropping into it as yet: Theſe and the like humble Thoughts are enough to ſtrike us down into the moſt reverent and lowly Proſtrations.</p>
            <p>'TIS true, there is a voluntary Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity which carrieth an ill Character with it, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 18. But this is impertinently objected againſt the uſe of theſe exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal acts in the Worſhip of God, becauſe it is joyned there with the worſhipping of Angels. Such voluntary Humility is indeed criminal, when People addreſs themſelves to Angels, as the <hi>Ethnicks</hi> did <pb n="125" facs="tcp:106212:70"/> to Daemons, as to Mediators and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors for them to the Supreme Being, and out of a great awe and fear of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching immediately unto God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. This Humility is culpable: But this makes nothing againſt thoſe outward acts of Religious Adorations, which are directed to the Creator of all things. For ſuch acts are not properly voluntary; they are God's due, to which he hath an indefeiſable Right by having created the Body; and for that reaſon it is Idolatry to give them to a Creature, becauſe it is the giving away of God's Honour and Right; a Right founded upon an Original Law, which <hi>Adam</hi> and his whole Family brought into the World with them.</p>
            <p>TO argue therefore againſt ſuch ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn acts of Worſhip, from ſuch weak Topicks, betrays great affectation of Mind, a love of ſingularity and ſtubborn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; like that quarrelſome Temper that is in ſome, who lie ſtill upon the catch, and want only an opportunity of ſtarting a pretence. A Mind that is truly hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, truly conſcious and ſenſible of the vileneſs of ſuch a miſerable, ſinful Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as Man is, cannot uſe a more ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine Method of expreſſing its Senſe of this vileneſs, than by thoſe Reverent Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, <pb n="126" facs="tcp:106212:71"/> in the Solemnities of God's Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, which would be ſuitable, ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and juſtifiable, were they not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded.</p>
            <p n="4">4. BESIDES theſe ways of expreſſing our lowlineſs, there is yet a Fourth, <hi>viz.</hi> By giving our ſelves up to God's diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal. Reſignation is an inſeparable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of an humble Soul; nor is it ever ſo becoming and agreeable, as when we abſolutely reſign our ſelves up into the Hands of God. This is greatly to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him; becauſe it is a manifeſtation of thoſe Divine Attributes, wherein his Glory doth conſiſt. It is a confeſſion that he is a Being of uncontroulable Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, not bounded or govern'd, but by the Perfections of his own moſt bleſſed Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: That he hath an abſolute Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Authority over us, as over his own; and that he can exerciſe his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er when, and as he pleaſeth: That he is juſt in all his Proceedings, acting always according to the Equal Laws of his own Eternal and Infallible Reaſon. That he is moſt perfectly Wiſe in ordering all things according to the Counſel of his Will; and ſo tranſcendently Good, that he diſpoſeth Affairs in this World, in ſuch a manner as is beſt, and in ſuch a way
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:106212:71"/> as is moſt ſafe and proper to lead us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another World, where alone there is unmix'd Happineſs, and that Happineſs everlaſting. Theſe are the Religious Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of every humble Man that is rightly inſtructed: And upon theſe ſound Principles, he believes it his ſafeſt, and moſt neceſſary courſe, to throw himſelf at God's Feet, and under God's Hand, neither thwarting nor oppoſing his Will, nor murmuring at his Providence, but ſubmitting univerſally to his Commands and Oeconomy. For all ſuch ſtubbornneſs, and ſtrivings, ſuch repinings, and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and reluctancies proceed from Hearts that are lifted up and ſwell againſt their Maker; whoſe Wiſdom, Truth, and Goodneſs they call in queſtion, and in oppoſition to whoſe Pleaſure they ſet up their own Luſts and Paſſions; the ſturdy Vices of thoſe aſpiring Angels, who once made a War in Heaven, which end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed preſently in a total defection from the Father of Spirits. Therefore, that we may expreſs and increaſe that Humility of Heart, which the Saviour of Mankind hath with ſuch earneſtneſs recommended to us all, that he may ſtock and people Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with New Colonies, we muſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our ſelves unto God in all things.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:106212:72"/> FIRST, By reſigning up our Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, where he propoſeth matters to our belief. The only Enquiry to be made as to this is, Whether God hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed and declared thoſe matters? If that be once out of diſpute, we muſt acquieſce in the Revelation. How remote ſoever the things to be believed are from the reach of our finite Reaſon, and how ſeemingly impoſſible ſoever they may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, we muſt receive them upon the Credit of God's Veracity, becauſe he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Lye; 'tis inconſiſtent with the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of his Glorious Nature, to be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of deceiving, or being deceived. Humane Reaſon is neither fix'd, nor large enough to be the Standard of all Truth; nor can we avoid the guilt of a thouſand Errors, if we take nothing, but what holds juſt even meaſure with our finite Capacities. Let the Point be never ſo diſputable to our own thinking, this muſt decide the Doubt, God hath ſaid it, and required us to believe it, therefore it muſt be true.</p>
            <p>SECONDLY, We muſt reſign our Wills up, where God requires our Obedience. Becauſe his Commands cannot but be Righteous, Good, and Holy, as his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <pb n="129" facs="tcp:106212:72"/> is, they bring with them neceſſary Obligations; nor muſt our ſenſual Incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations carry it againſt God's Law, how ſtrongly ſoever the Biaſs that is in our own Nature may be drawing of us away from the Rule. In this caſe we muſt deny our ſelves, renounce our Animal Satisfactions, and follow the Will of the God of Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, tho' all our Intereſt and Pleaſures lie at ſtake. For, tho' God hath obliged himſelf to provide Neceſſaries for us, yet he is not concern'd to humour us: Nor is it our buſineſs to cram our Purſes, or to gorge our wanton Appetites, with the Honours and Luxuries they crave for, but to ſerve God; to <hi>ſeek the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God, and his Righteouſneſs. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he ſaith unto you, do it;</hi> as the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Virgin directed the Servants at the Wedding, when ſhe pointed to Jeſus, <hi>John</hi> 2. 5.</p>
            <p>THIRDLY, We muſt ſubmit unto God, by reſigning up our Perſons and Fortunes alſo to his Pleaſure, when his Providence ſhall call for that expreſſion of Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; let our preſent Circumſtances be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo mortifying. We muſt not think of ever returning into a
<hi>Paradiſe</hi> here be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; or, that the Lands we are driven out into will loſe their fertility of Thorne <pb n="130" facs="tcp:106212:73"/> and Thiſtles. The Sins we act, do help to renew and aggravate the primordial Curſe; and as long as we go upon ſuch prickly Ground, no wonder if we are made, for the moſt part, to ſmart, and ſometimes to bleed alſo. Yet God, who bringeth Good out of Evil, hath made this our way to the Celeſtial <hi>Eden;</hi> and a Thorn in the Fleſh ſerves to accelerate our courſe thither. We may be ſure God intends it to quicken us; and we ſhould the rather be contented with his order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of us, becauſe he is the only Wiſe Being, that knoweth what we moſt need, and what is moſt proper for us. Our Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings at the beſt are very ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſighted (all humble Men muſt needs think ſo) and our Deſires lean ſo auk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardly, towards an infinity of things which would hurt us, that were we to be chuſers for our ſelves, we ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of nothing ſooner than of our own options. 'Tis an happy thing, that we are all under God's Government and Care; and we may be ſure, that as long as by patient continuance in well-doing we ſeek for Glory, Honour, and Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality in another World, he chuſeth thoſe things for us, which our Neceſſities moſt require; and in the Faith of that we ſhould evermore ſubmit to his Wiſdom, <pb n="131" facs="tcp:106212:73"/> and learn, in what ſtate ſoever we are, therewith to be content, as that hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-minded Apoſtle was,
<hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 10.</p>
            <p n="5">5. HAVING proceeded thus far on the firſt Point, of expreſſing our Humility by ſerving God's Honour, there is but one Direction more for me to offer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I quit this Conſideration: And it is, That we depend upon him and truſt to him, in reference to all Events. This is an honouring of God for the ſame Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and upon the ſame Grounds I men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned before; becauſe by acts of this Nature we manifeſt our belief of his Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſcience, Wiſdom, Goodneſs, and the like glorious Perfections, which are the prop and ſtay of all our Hopes. By vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue hereof every humble Man finds it his beſt Wiſdom, to caſt all his Care on him, who careth for us all, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit himſelf to him in well-doing, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4. 19. For were ſuch Men left purely to their own Conduct and Forecaſt, they could not but act with tremulous Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, with many Doubts and Fears, with miſtruſtful Thoughts, and miſgiving Minds, becauſe they are ſo conſcious of their manifold Weakneſſes and Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. It is therefore very ſafe and ſuitable for Men of lowly Hearts, to
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:106212:74"/> leave all future contingencies to the Great Governour of the World; with ſuch confidence as is conſiſtent with Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility; and with a modeſt aſſurance, that all things ſhall work together for their Good. I confeſs it is ſcarcely poſſible, eſpecially for the more thinking and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacious ſort of Men, to be utterly unmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, unconcern'd in their Minds at the proſpect of Affairs, when they appear, tho' at ſome diſtance, with a melancholy Countenance, louring, doleſome Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which affecteth the Senſe with the appearance of a Storm, muſt needs make ſome impreſſions upon the moſt Religious Minds. But this is poſſible for us, and this we ſhould be very careful of, in all ominous and threatning Circumſtances, to act without fretting at the Diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of God's Providence, without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondency, without thoſe anxious and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate Solicitudes which undiſciplin'd, and unſubdued Spirits are ſubject unto. Becauſe there is an Almighty, All-ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent God that preſideth over the Univerſe; that obſerves all the Parts of it, and all Motions in it; that holds his Hand over the whole Series of Affairs; that fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees all Contingencies, and whatſoever is likely to happen; that governs and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects every thing ſo as may be beſt for <pb n="133" facs="tcp:106212:74"/> his own Glory, and for the Good of the whole World; that takes a more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Care of good Men; that is with them in all their Troubles, how great and how many ſoever their Troubles be; that ordereth their Afflictions as is moſt for their Advantage: Upon theſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples which are ſo clear and certain, we ſhould, with all lowlineſs of Heart, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe our ſelves into ſuch a ſtate of acquie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcence and ſatisfaction, in reſpect of all Events; as, to live ſtill in Hope (a firm and immovable Hope) of ſeeing the Goodneſs of God, who gives us all things richly to enjoy: To ſubmit to his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence; to cheriſh our Souls with the continual belief and conſideration of it; to be deeply affraid of nothing before us, but a bottomleſs Pit; to rely upon God's Mercy in doing the Works of our Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings. In a word, we ſhould humbly wait God's leiſure, to give us either thoſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry things we deſire, at his own time, and in his own way; or (which he never fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth to give) other Bleſſings, which he ſeeth far more profitable and neceſſary for us.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:106212:75"/>
            <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>How Humility is to be expreſs'd, by not making our own Eſteem the End of our Actions.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="2">2. HAVING thus provided for the Honour of God; we muſt in the Second place, beware of making our own Reputation the principal End of our Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>THIS is utterly inconſiſtent with an humble Mind, and with the Laws of our Religion: The only difficulty is, How to reconcile it with that of
<hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov. 22. 1. <hi>A good Name is rather to be choſen than great Riches.</hi> But this difficulty is incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable, if we diſtinguiſh, between a Good, and a Great Name; and between making it our ultimate Deſign, to feed a vain glorious Humour, and valuing it only as a means in order to an End which is truly Honourable.</p>
            <p>FOR the clearing of this Matter we muſt obſerve, That a Good Name is that <pb n="135" facs="tcp:106212:75"/> Eſteem which ariſeth from Actions that are Praiſe-worthy: Vertue is very lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Juſtice, Meekneſs, Charity, Sobrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the like, are things which we honour all Men for; nor is any one well eſteemed without them. By diſ-regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe Vertues Men ſupplant their own Deſign; and ruine their Reputation even when they think to raiſe it. But of all Vertues, Humility yieldeth a moſt rich Perfume, and that which <hi>is better than precious ointment,</hi> Eccleſ. 7. 1. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcend to Men of low Eſtate, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Offices, is a thing which carrieth its own Praiſe with it; and this is well called, an honeſt Reputation. Now ſuch a Name as this we are allowed to have, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is the neceſſary Reſult of good Actions, eſpecially when we have to do with People who have a due regard for Vertue and Religion. Nay, conſidering how uſeful it is towards the ſetting forth of God's Glory, we are obliged alſo to ſeek it in ſome meaſure. For hereby we are the more able to do good in our Generation; to inſtruct, to admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, to ſhew People their Duty, and their true way to everlaſting Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. The good things they ſee in ſuch Directors, and the good Opinion they have of them, ſerves t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ake their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monitions
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:106212:76"/> and Examples the more ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rative: Whereas nothing is more Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, than to diſcredit and abhorr thoſe whoſe improbity hath rendred them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly infamous; when their Names caſt a very ill ſavour, and eſpecially when the Stench is very ſtrong and ſtale too, every wiſe Man will be jealous of them; at leaſt, afraid and ſhy of liſtning to their Counſels. Hence it is, that we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to think on thoſe things which are of good report, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4. 8. Becauſe an honeſt Fame is ſo neceſſary to make us ſerviceable to God, and uſeful to the World in our reſpective Callings. And hence it was, that ſuch care was taken in the firſt Ages of Chriſtianity, of intruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe with Sacred Employments who were Men of honeſt report, <hi>Acts</hi> 6. 3. Men of good Report among them that were (as yet) without the Church, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 7. That the uprightneſs of their Lives, and the honeſty of their Reputation might help to bring unbelievers into it, and be a means of promoting and carrying on the great Ends of Religion. Upon this account, it is not only an unrighteous act in it ſelf, but an injury to the Church too, and great Impiety towards God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, to defame others, and eſpecially thoſe whom God hath ſet apart to ſerve <pb n="137" facs="tcp:106212:76"/> him in any Publick Station: To reproach and rifle them of their good Names, hath a direct and immediate tendency to eclipſe the Glory of God, which never ſhines more than when the Hearts of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are brought in Obedience to the Truth. And for the ſame reaſons every innocent Perſon is bound in Conſcience to defend, as well as to ſeek, his honeſt Reputation, by all fair and juſtifiable Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods; becauſe it is a matter of ſuch mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in its Conſequences. A clear Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample whereof we have in St. <hi>Paul,</hi> when ſome endeavoured by falſe and unjuſt Accuſations to render his Labours in the Church at <hi>Corinth</hi> unſucceſsful; tho' he was ſo humble as to confeſs the Crimes of his former Life, with this modeſt Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbole, that
<hi>he was the chiefeſt of ſinners;</hi> yet, when the Honour of God, and the Good of Mens Souls came to be concern'd in his Reputation, that he might conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue an Inſtrument of advancing both, you ſee by 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11, and 12th. <hi>Chapters,</hi> how zealous he was to redeem his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, by clearing himſelf from thoſe foul Aſperſions; tho' he was conſtrain'd to do it by magnifying himſelf, contrary to his uſual Cuſtom, and againſt his own Mind: Indeed, he there calls his boaſting, <hi>Folly;</hi> and himſelf, a <hi>Fool</hi> for it; not that the <pb n="138" facs="tcp:106212:77"/> thing deſerved that hard Character (his Circumſtances at that time conſider'd) but, either becauſe he thought his Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries would count it Vanity; or, becauſe it looked like Vanity, and in Fact would have been ſo, had not great and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Reaſons extorted from him ſuch Gloryings, and Commendations of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
            <p>THIS ſhews, That the Laws of Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity allow, and the Laws of Charity re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire every one, who is conſcious of his Innocence, to vindicate and reſcue his honeſt Fame, when it hath the hard fate, to ſuffer and bleed under the cruel Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of unreaſonable Men. The truth is Wounds of this kind are ſo deep and maiming, that common Nature is enough to juſtifie our endeavours to cleanſe and heal them; provided, that Revenge have no hand in the Operation, to retort the Blows, and that the Methods uſed be on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſanatory.</p>
            <p>BUT, tho' a fair Eſteem be valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, yet we muſt be careful of two things:</p>
            <p n="1">1. THAT we deſire no greater ſhare of it, than what will enable us to be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable <pb n="139" facs="tcp:106212:77"/> to God and Men, in our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Callings. There is (as was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved) much difference between a good and a great Name. This we muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of ſeeking, or of being pleaſed with; becauſe it proceedeth from Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and helpeth ſtill to encreaſe it; like Thirſt in a Dropſie, which ſprings from the Diſeaſe, and feeds it too, by being gratified it ſelf: A return, which in that caſe ſhould not be made to ſuch a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. A deſire of being called every where <hi>Rabbi, Rabbi,</hi> is as inconſiſtent with an humble Mind, as the Ambition of a troubleſome Prince, that would enlarge his Dominions, and carry his Glories to the ends of the Earth; when his greateſt Honour ſhould be to do good at home in his own Country. An honeſt ordinary Repute, ariſing from the conſcionable performance of our Duty, within the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of a private Station, is far more ſuitable to a Chriſtian Temper, than all the Luſtre and Fame that is acquired by high reaching, and rather than be guilty of ſuch vain Affectation, we ſhould covet the Solaces of a quiet Obſcurity, and imitate <hi>Saul</hi> when he modeſtly ran among the ſtuff, to hide his Head from the ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did burthen of a Crown, 1
<hi>Sam.</hi> 10. 22.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:106212:78"/> 2. 'TIS true; a good Name is apt to grow up to an unexpected pitch; and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver more, than when we think by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcentions to lower it, and make it ſhrink; therefore we muſt be very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, Secondly, that it be not the <hi>End</hi> we aim at, be it greater or leſs: This is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly vain glory; when a Man hath a ſtrong and greedy Appetite after popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Applauſe, as a thing very deſirable: Nor is any thing more contrary to a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Humility, than a vain glorious Humour, an Ambition of <hi>appearing</hi> Great in the World, and of being thought worthy of all Deference and Eſteem. <hi>I receive not honour from men,</hi> ſaid the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Jeſus, <hi>John</hi> 5. 41. And they who make this the Scope and End of their Actions, deſerve not the Character of his Diſciples. Such as have a mean and ſlender Opinion of themſelves, muſt needs be contented (at leaſt) if others have the ſame Opinion of them too: He that wanteth this Diſpoſition of Soul, is not humble indeed, but only ſeems to be ſo; like the <hi>Phariſees</hi> of old, who went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with lugubrious and dejected Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenances, as if they were the humbleſt Men in the World; yet all this was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Art, and Affectation of Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity.
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:106212:78"/> If they faſted, they disfigured their Faces, that they might appear unto Men to faſt. Oh! What mortified Saints were they! If they gave Alms, the Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet preſently ſounded, to gather People to a ſhow, that they might have glory of Men, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>THEREFORE that there may be room enough for Chriſt in your Hearts, be ſure to caſt out the <hi>Phariſee,</hi> neither looking after humane Praiſe, nor valuing it any more than a ſlight puff of Air, which to day may yield a flavour, and to morrow noiſomeneſs. Whether it be through ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, or diſhonour, <hi>ſeek the Kingdom of God, and his Righteouſneſs:</hi> Let this be your buſineſs and deſign, to pleaſe God, and to do your Duty, whatever be the reſult of it, whether the favours, or the frowns of Men. Be careful to do the things which are honourable and praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy; and if a fair Name follows, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard it only as a Perquiſite that falleth in by the bye. And accordingly make uſe of it, as an accident dropt into your Hands, for your better aſſiſtance and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement in the proſecution of Pious and Charitable Purpoſes. This is indeed the only good reaſon we have, to deſire to be well eſteemed, and well ſpoken
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:106212:79"/> of, that thereby we may be the better a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to do good in the World, and that God may be the more glorified by us.</p>
            <p>A laudable Character is a mighty ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage and help in order to theſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Ends; for thereby our Principles paſs among Men with the fairer Credit; our Counſels carry the greater Authority, and our Reprehenſions make the deeper im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions upon the Minds of People who have a good Opinion of us: And by theſe means the deſigns of Religion are the better, and the ſooner anſwer'd. <hi>Whether therefore ye eat or drink, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ye do, do all to the glory of God,</hi> ſaith St.
<hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 31. Unto this end Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility prompts us to direct all our Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and when Men make their own glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry either a Subſtitute inſtead of God's, or a Competitor with it, it is an ill ſign of ſuch a Spirit, as did once ſet up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Majeſty of Heaven; but met with ſuch a fatal turn, as preſently drew on the Chains of Darkneſs: An everlaſting warning to us not to aſpire, not to ſeek our own Greatneſs; not to move in any Sphere, but by humble ways of ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viency, for fear of Giddineſs and ruine. Self-exaltation, which unbecame Angels, and was ſo ſinful in them, is far more
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:106212:79"/> intolerable in ſuch Worms as we are. God knows, the brighteſt of us is but a Gloe-worm; and the Rule before us is this, <hi>Let your light ſo ſhine before Men, that they may ſee your good Works, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie your Father which is in Heaven.</hi> If the little Luſtre about us doth not ſerve to direct others in the Paths of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs and Peace,
't were better ſuppreſs'd; like the old Veſtal Fires at <hi>Rome,</hi> which (as ſome tell us) burned well enough, as long as they were kept under Ground, and free from Air. Oſtentation is perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, not only to the Soul, but to it ſelf. To be ſeen of Men, and to make that our Aim, is the ready way to loſe our Credit while we pretend to ſeek it; and to get nothing at laſt, but the Name of vain Perſons: And ſo we miſs the Mark, by making our own ſelves the End. And the truth is, 't is pity but it ſhould be ſo. The Vice I now ſpeak of is ſo fooliſh, that it ought to carry a Rod to puniſh it ſelf with.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <pb n="144" facs="tcp:106212:80"/>
            <head>CHAP. X. <hi>How Humility is to be expreſs'd by ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging our Faults.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="3">3. BUT to forbear courting our own Praiſe, is not all we are to do to expreſs our Humility. It is, Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the office of every humble Man, to own and acknowledge his Faults. Tho' it be a modeſt Vertue, yet it is not ſo baſhful as to be aſhamed of confeſſing Miſcarriages, where the guilt is real. The reaſon of this lieth in the Nature of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility; which being a mean and low Opinion of One's ſelf, makes the humble Perſon apt to look continually upon the viler part, and to make that known, which he diſcovers there. It was the true cauſe of St.
<hi>Paul</hi>'s repeated Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: The conſcience of his guilt would not permit him to conceal his Crimes; but moved him upon all occaſions to tell the World, how he had perſecuted the Church of Chriſt; and waſted it; and to declare himſelf the chief of Sinners. It was the Rule in thoſe days, and that which Chriſtians moſt readily obſerved,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:106212:80"/> 
               <hi>Confeſs your faults one to another,</hi> James 5.
16. This filled the Church with as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny humble accuſers of themſelves, as there were Penitents and Converts; they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed and ſhewed their Deeds, as 'tis ſaid of thoſe at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> Acts 19. 18. St.
<hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi>'s Books of Retractations and Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons do plainly ſhew us, what a lowly Spirit prevailed in his time. There need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed then no other Remonſtrances, but what extravagant or deceived Men drew up againſt themſelves: And we of this Age might have hopes of bringing the Tempers of People into ſome Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the Primitive Rule and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, could we perſuade Men once to be ſenſible wherein they do amiſs. But, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſs! Chriſtianity (inſtead of Pride) is fallen to ſuch a low ebb, that many will not endure to be told their Faults; but Advice is interpreted as Diſgrace, and Reproof as Scandal. The reaſon of this is latent within; becauſe ſuch Men are ſwollen with ſo great a Conceit of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as if they were in an impeccable and infallible ſtate. Hence it is, that they love Flatterers, and very few, if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, but Flatterers, becauſe they are firſt their own Paraſites. The Vice in their Breaſts is in confederacy with that at the Elbow; and both combine to abuſe <pb n="146" facs="tcp:106212:81"/> them with Courtſhip, which they are willing to take, not as Complement, but Juſtice. 'Tis, indeed, a reproach to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature, that any Man can be ſo degenerate, as to practiſe the baſe and wicked Arts of Adulation. Yet, in the obſervation of all Men, nothing is more common, eſpecially where ſome ſordid Ends may be ſerv'd by it. <hi>Plutarch</hi> in his excellent Book concerning the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between a Flatterer and a Friend, tells us, That
<hi>when</hi> Dionyſius <hi>the Tyrant was in a fit of ſtudying Philoſophy, his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace was crouded with Geometricians, that filled it with Duſt, to draw Schemes and Figures in: But as ſoon as the fit was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and</hi> Dionyſius <hi>betook himſelf again to Luxury, all on a ſudden they that were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout him left their Philoſophy too, and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Drunkards.</hi> As that great Moraliſt obſerves, Flatterers will adapt and ſuit themſelves to any Humour; eſpecially if they be ſerious Paraſites, which are the moſt dangerous of all. They will cheriſh, and comply with the very Vices of Men, and obſequiouſly follow them in their own way, tho' ruine be at the end of it. But the original Sin, the fatal cauſe of all this, is in proud and weak Men that love to be flatter'd. They hold out a Bait to the Sycophant, who <pb n="147" facs="tcp:106212:81"/> to keep himſelf from being lean, will be ſure to make uſe of it; nor has every one the bold Probity, to venture the worſt by telling Men their Faults; the hazard they run in ſuch a caſe is too ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent. <hi>Plutarch</hi> tells us again, but in another place, of <hi>Philoxenus</hi> the Poet, That being commanded by
<hi>Dionyſius</hi> to correct a Tragedy which he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, becauſe he diſliked it from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to the end, and obliterated the dull ſtuff, was preſently condemned to the Quarries. Proud Men will not endure to be thought to have done amiſs, or to be in an Error. How plain ſoever it be, it is a very hard matter to convince them, and the hardeſt of all to extort a Confeſſion from them. There is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivableneſs in their Temper; an odd propenſion to be ſoothed into the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of any Miſrepreſentations, eſpecially of themſelves; a Diſpoſition like that which God ſo complained of in the <hi>Jews, Jer.</hi> 5. 30, 31. <hi>A wonderful and horrible thing is committed in the land: The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets propheſie falſly, and the Prieſts bear rule by their means, and my people love to have it ſo.</hi> The Queſtion that follows there is very pertinent;
<hi>and what will ye do in the end thereof?</hi> For when once Men arrive to ſuch a pitch of ſtupid Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, <pb n="148" facs="tcp:106212:82"/> there is very little hope of them; becauſe the means of Reforming them are quite fruſtrated; Advice and Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion (the ordinary means of making People wiſer and better) are utterly loſt, perhaps ſcarcely offer'd, becauſe ſuch deceived Perſons ſcorn to think there is any need of them; and hereby it cometh to paſs, that many Vices, which ſhould be weeded out, thrive daily, and become Luxuriant. But where the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God hath wrought an Heart to a right humble Mould and Frame, there the Inclination is quite the other way; a proneneſs to think or to believe the worſt of One's ſelf. And becauſe the humble Man's great buſineſs is, to ſearch into himſelf, to underſtand and find out him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, he is not eaſily abuſed with falſe Notions. There is a Conſcience within, which deals freely and plainly with him; too ſevere a Judge to be bribed with ſmooth Inſinuations and words of Oil, as the expreſſion is, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 55. 22. Hence it is, that none is ſo ſenſible of his Miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, as he; none ſo ready to confeſs them; becauſe his Eye being ſtill over his flaws and defects, what he ſeeth amiſs in himſelf, he thinks it but juſt and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual to acknowledge: This is no more than what is agreeable unto Truth. <hi>My
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:106212:82"/> ſin,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, is ever before me,</hi> Pſalm 51. 3. And again; <hi>I will acknowledge my ſin unto thee, and mine unrighteouſneſs have I not hid,</hi> Pſalm 32. 5. And to the ſame purpoſe I obſerved before of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> That he proclaimed his Offences, as it were, from the Houſe-top: As he kept a faithful Regiſter of them, ſo he took hold of every opportunity, to open and ſpread it before the Eyes of all Men.</p>
            <p>THESE were true Arguments and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of Humility; and noble Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples for us all to follow, for the exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and increaſing in us this great Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Vertue. Have you been guilty of any direct Impiety towards God? Why, with the loweſt Proſtrations confeſs the Sin unto him, implore his Mercy. Was it an act of Violence? An act of Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion? An act of Injuſtice, in any ſort, or to any degree? Why, tho' Men commonly count it a Shame and a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour, yet it is a kind of Modeſty, which of all things doth moſt become the Forehead of a Chriſtian, to own the Wrong, and to make Amends, or (at leaſt) to ask Pardon for it. In theſe and the like caſes we ſhould not ſuffer Pride to get the upper hand of us; or,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:106212:83"/> to make us ſo hardy, as to perſiſt, to carry a ſtiff Neck, to juſtifie or palliate thoſe things, which the Laws of Religion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire us to expoſe. Sins of this nature affect the Conſcience with too great a guilt to be ſmother'd; God and Man ſhould know it; and, rather than any humble <hi>Zacchaeus</hi> will hide his Injuſtice, he will firſt climb up into a Sycamore-Tree, and then venture into a preſs, that he may make Proclamation, <hi>Behold, Lord, the, half of my goods I give to the poor; and if I have wronged any man by falſe accuſation, I reſtore him four fold,</hi> Luke 19. 8.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <pb n="151" facs="tcp:106212:83"/>
            <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>How Humility is to be expreſs'd by doing all good Offices, tho' ſeeming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mean, and by ſubmiſſion to our Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="4">4. THIS excellent Diſpoſition of Soul will prepare us to give a Fourth expreſſion of Humility, <hi>viz.</hi> By doing all the good Offices we can, how mean and inferiour ſoever they may ſeem to Men of haughty Eyes. To ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour the poor Fatherleſs; to comfort the forlorn Widow; to ſtretch out the Hand to the needy; to lend it to the Blind; to ſympathize and pray by a ſick Bed; to miniſter in Priſons and Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retto's; to treat Enemies courteouſly; to ſhew Reſpect to the moſt Vulgar, the moſt unfortunate part of Mankind: Theſe and the like acts of deference are look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon with a diſdainful Eye by ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>percilious Men, who think themſelves privileg'd from ſuch trivial Offices, by the quality of their Character, or the loftineſs of their Station. And yet the
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:106212:84"/> Lord Jeſus ſtooped down to the waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Diſciples Feet; nay, thoſe very Feet that were now running ſwiftly to ſhed his Blood; which aſtoniſhing Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample ſhews, that the moſt lowly Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations are far from beneath us, who ſtand indebted to each other in the Bond of one common Nature, and are allied by the Contract of a common Guilt too. If he, the moſt Bleſſed and Glorious Son of God, came not to be miniſtred unto, but to miniſter; Good God! What Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices can be ſervile enough for Wretches, whoſe baſe Extraction, and much baſer Crimes render us unworthy to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, either Sons, or Servants? <hi>Mind not high things, but condeſcend to men of low eſtate,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle,
<hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 16. He calls that Condeſcention, which in ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Speech might be called Due Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution; an intercourſe of Juſtice, which ought to paſs between Man and Man, conſidering that we all ſtand upon the ſame Ground, equally involved in the ſame Neceſſities, mutually indebted by reciprocal Obligations, and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd only by the Pageantry of the World, which gilds one Muſhrome, while another is paſt by, and a third ſtruck down. All conſiſt of the ſame ſtuff; of the Earth, Earthy: And tho' <pb n="153" facs="tcp:106212:84"/> ſome be fairer and larger than the reſt, yet the leſſer may have more intrinſick value, if in ſuch things there be any va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue at all. <hi>In lowlineſs of mind let each eſteem other better than themſelves,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> Phil. 2. 3. That is, in their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons towards them, ſhew others that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference and reſpect, and miniſter to them ſo, as if they were better; as indeed they may be, in ſome reſpect or other, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the proudeſt think. All have not the ſame gifts; at leaſt they have not the ſame proportion and meaſure the moſt contemptible Man hath, wherein he doth excel, even as the Foot hath Abilities, which the Eye wanteth. Therefore that command,
<hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 10. That <hi>in honour we ſhould preferr one another,</hi> is bottom'd upon great reaſon; becauſe in every one there is ſomething which is preferrable; to be ſure an humble Man will find, in thoſe of the loweſt Rank, this or that which deſerves preference.</p>
            <p>AND from this Fountain all acts of Charity, Goodneſs, and Condeſcention do naturally flow; becauſe how mean ſoever the Offices may appear and ſeem to be, a lowly Heart will think them a ſort of Debt, which he is obliged to pay thoſe, who upon ſome account or other,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:106212:85"/> and for ſome Faculties and Endowments, excel him, and are much his Betters. It is the Nature of Humility, to take from it ſelf, and to beſtow that Reſpect and Eſteem it parts with, any where ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than at home: And if we would all be once perſuaded to apply our Minds to the hearty love and practice of this ſingle Vertue, what admirable effects would it not produce? The moſt ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary works of Love would not be grudged. The meaneſt of our fellow Creatures would be within every One's reach, and under every One's care. We ſhould ſoon learn to be ſo Affable, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, Courteous, Friendly, Charitable, Compaſſionate, and Aſſiſtant unto all (eſpecially to all of the Houſhold of Faith) that a more effectual courſe could not be taken to make our own and other Mens Lives happy, and to mend the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of this World, where we ſee dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch Viciſſitudes and Misfortunes. If Humanity conſtrains us to lift up an Aſs, or an Ox out of the Pit; I am ſure humble Minds would not permit us to let any of thoſe for whom Chriſt died, to lie long in a loſt or a fallen con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="155" facs="tcp:106212:85"/> 5. NEXT to this Expreſſion of Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, a Fifth will naturally follow; which is, to behave our ſelves after a ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive and dutiful manner to thoſe, whom God hath ſet over us in Church and State. For, if it be a neceſſary act of Humility, to do kind and reſpectful Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices to all our equals, it muſt be much more neceſſary to pay Honour and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to ſuch as are exalted into a ſtate of Superiority and Power. Therefore St. <hi>Peter</hi> links theſe two things, <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Humility,</hi> together, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. 5.
<hi>Likewiſe ye younger, ſubmit your ſelves unto the elder;</hi> yea, all of you be ſubject one to another; and be cloathed with Humility. As there are in Heaven ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Degrees of Glory, ſeveral States of Saints, and ſeveral Orders of Angels, ſo hath God conſtituted on Earth different Ranks of Men, in condeſcention to the Neceſſities of the World, where the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts of Societies cannot poſſibly be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved without Government and Laws; and, conſequently, without the ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thoſe who are in a ſtate of Subor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination. Such People cannot expreſs the Humility of their Hearts more ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsfully and directly for the Publick Good, than by an entire Compliance with <pb n="156" facs="tcp:106212:86"/> things eſtabliſh'd, where the Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is not repugnant to Laws Divine. For
'tis Pride that is the great Troubler of the World, the common Peſt and Grievance, the domineering, ſurly, reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Vice that diſturbs the Peace of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and breaks that Order and Unity on which the Safety and Welfare of all Communities doth depend. That over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weening Conceit which Men have of their own Worth, believing themſelves to be wiſer, and better, and more deſerving than others, doth naturally make them ambitious of Ruling, and impatient of being Ruled; and whatever the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences and Acceſſories may be, 'tis the Affectation of Superiority and Power that is the Principal Cauſe of thoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders, which render the Lives of Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Miſerable, and turn the Condition of Affairs into a State of War. <hi>O that I were made Judge in the land,</hi> ſaid <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 4. His deſign was upon the Throne, and the Artifices he uſed to ſteal the Peoples Hearts, were nothing but ways of ſtepping up into it. His Promiſes, that he would do them Juſtice; and his Popularity, in putting forth his Hand to ſuch as did him Obeiſance, his embracing and kiſſing them: All this ſawning Addreſs was to ſerve his own <pb n="157" facs="tcp:106212:86"/> Ambition, and nothing but a Preamble to his ſetting up his Standard in <hi>Hebron.</hi> Seldom is the Civil Peace diſturbed, but Ambition blows the Trumpet, to gather Male-Contents, of the ſame Temper with their Leaders; and when the Paſſions of an united Multitude are fired by one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Principle, the Proſpect is as terrible to the State, as that was to the <hi>Roman</hi> Army, when <hi>Hannibal</hi> forced in upon them two thouſand Oxen, with combuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble matter flaming upon their Heads. Pride is the great Incendiary, that heady and diſobedient Principle; and the Yoke being ſhaken off, Confuſion and Anarchy, and infinite variety of Miſchief muſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of courſe.</p>
            <p>THE ſame Spirit of Diſobedience, which raiſeth Commotions in the State, operates in the Church too; and there in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed more fatally, becauſe animated with a great (tho' miſtaken) Zeal for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and
<hi>Lucifer</hi> there transforms him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into an Angel of Light.
<hi>Diotrephes</hi> lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to have the preeminence, 3 <hi>John</hi> 9. and this Ambition of Mind made him ſo hardy as to oppoſe the Authority of St.
<hi>John. Simon Magus,</hi> the firſt that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted the Chriſtian Faith, did it for fear of loſing or leſſening the Eſteem he had while he was yet a Sorcerer. He <pb n="158" facs="tcp:106212:87"/> gave out, that himſelf was ſome great one, and deceived People into a belief, That he was <hi>the great power of God,</hi> Acts 8. 9, 10. To preſerve his Credit he would have bought the Gift of Miracles; and, ſeeing it was not to be ſold for Money, to ſupport his great Name he turned A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtate, and the Ring-leader of Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates; oppoſing and exalting himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all that was called God, or that was Worſhipp'd; ſo that as God he ſate in the Temple of God, pretending him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that he was God, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 4. In after-times aſſuming Spirits became He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks, that they might be in the Head of a Sect, and build themſelves Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, tho' upon the Ruines of God's Sanctuary. And in our own days the ſame Spirit ſtill worketh in the Hearts of the Children of Diſobedience, who ſet up Fancy againſt Truth, private Reaſon againſt Divine Revelation, and ſeparate Parties againſt Government and Order. The bottom of all this, is Pride; becauſe Men ſwollen with that Diſeaſe, think it beneath them to be dictated unto; would be thought more Knowing, and more Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly than others; and love ſingularity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it makes Men always talk'd of, and ſometimes venerated. And tho' for all this ſome Arguments are pretended, yet <pb n="159" facs="tcp:106212:87"/> the Diſputation is maintain'd not ſo much for Truth, as for Victory. Pertinacy will ſtill hold, what Singularity before inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and ſuch as coyn new Opinions, will be ſure for their Credit ſake to make them as currant as they can, to juſtifie the ſtamp they once ſet upon them. By this means poor credulous People are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed with falſe Notions, which by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees make an impreſs upon their Minds, not only of the Falſhood, but of the Vice too from which the Error came; ſo that in a ſhort time Spiritual Pride grows Popular, and ends in Schiſm; which inſtead of curing the Humour, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flames it, and canonizeth a Sin which God threw out of Heaven to be damned eternally.</p>
            <p>THEREFORE we cannot give a plainer and better Expreſſion of our Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, than by rendring Honour and Subjection to whom it is due; and to the utmoſt extent, which the Laws of God will admit of. I am far from pleading for an implicit Faith; a blind Obedience that will neceſſarily bring us in danger of the Ditch, if we ſhould truſt barely (as ſome are taught to do) to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of our Leaders. At all times we ſhould be careful of theſe Four things.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:106212:88"/> 1. FIRST, Not to ſtart Opinions out of a Principle of Oppoſition to our Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours. For it is an ill ſign, when Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have an itch in their Ears to hear their Governors hardly ſpoken of, and an itch in their Hearts to contradict and thwart them. This can proceed from nothing but from Opiniatry, and a ſtrong Preſumption in them, that they are fit to be Dictators; and it looks as if they had a mind to raiſe themſelves a Name by treading upon Authority; a thing which we are not to Trample on, but Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence.</p>
            <p n="2">2. SECONDLY, In thoſe Points which are of a doubtful Nature, we ſhould pay great Reſpect and Deference to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church we belong to. For every humble Man muſt think it much eaſier for one or two to be deceived, than for a thouſand; eſpecially when it is the Office of ſo many to inquire more particularly after Truth, and their Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities are more probable to find it out. They muſt be very ſtrong Reaſons that can warrant Men to depart from a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd Opinion: Yet it is not always, Reaſon, but for the moſt part Affectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that gives the incouragement; a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire <pb n="161" facs="tcp:106212:89"/> of being taken notice of, by ſtepping out of the way from the reſt, who think it more adviſable and ſafe to follow the beaten Path. For Men to diſtinguiſh themſelves by Singularity, and to ſet up Private Judgment againſt Publick Defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions, is to tell the World, that they have more Sence and Underſtanding than others, and that their own Conceits are better Standards of Truth, than a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that can be found in the Sanctuary. In ſhort, where ſome particular Perſons differ in their Sence from the Church in general, private Sentiments ſhould be managed with all poſſible Modeſty. Theſe Opinions are not to be judged of by the Poll, becauſe Error is too often Popular; yet conſidering, how great an hand Pride is apt to have in all Diſputes, and how much eaſier it is for private Men to be miſtaken, than to retract, we ſhould evermore obſerve that Law of Humility which the Apoſtle hath laid before us, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. 22. <hi>Haſt thou Faith? Have it to thy ſelf before God:</hi> That is, whatever a Man's Perſuaſion be as to things Diſputable, he ought to keep it ſo private by himſelf, as not to make it an occaſion of Diſturbance or Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="162" facs="tcp:106212:90"/> 3. THIRDLY, When Authority re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires things that are Innocent in their own Nature, we ſhould expreſs our Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility by complying with thoſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. In this caſe too 'tis Pride that makes Head againſt Order; a ſtiff Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new in the Neck, that hinders Men from ſtooping to that which Laws Divine and Humane have made their Duty. Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity teacheth us to be Pliant and Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; to be Tractable, Yielding and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequious: And, I think, as to this we need no plainer Directions than what our moſt humble Lord gave his firſt Diſciples, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.
2, 3. <hi>The Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees ſit in Moſes ſeat; and therefore what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they bid you obſerve, that obſerve and do.</hi> The Rulers he ſpake of, were for the moſt part very wicked Men, and ſcandalous Hypocrites; which was the Ground of the following Caution, <hi>Do not ye after their works, for they ſay and do not.</hi> And yet conſidering that in their Authority they ſucceeded <hi>Moſes,</hi> who had his Authority immediately of God, they were to be obeyed in all Commands that were lawful. This Rule is applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to all Caſes now, where things which are not really Sinful are impoſed by thoſe who have the Government of us.
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:106212:90"/> They ſit in Chriſt's Seat; they derive their Authority from Chriſt, as he did his from his Father; and for that reaſon their Innocent Directions are to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, whatever their Perſonal Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or Quality of Life may be: And therefore when you are directed by ſuch as ſit in the Seat of the ſcornful, to hold off, and to diſobey; if the matters enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed be not evidently repugnant to the Will of God, you may be ſure that the Interdict is not from Chriſt, and that it is only humour, or ſtubbornneſs, or ſome ſuch evil thing, that gives the caſting Voice againſt Authority.</p>
            <p n="4">4. FOURTHLY, There are ſome ſet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us, whoſe Addreſs to us we may not ſo well call Mandatory, as Inſtructive. Tho' the Authority they are veſted with be after an eſpecial manner Divine, yet it muſt be adminiſtred in an humble way, and they that have it muſt be Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Humility, as the Son of God himſelf was, who gives them this Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. See what he ſaid to his Apoſtles, <hi>Matth.</hi> 20. 25, 26,
27. <hi>Ye know that the Princes of the Gentiles exerciſe domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over them; and they that are great, exerciſe authority upon them. But it ſhall not be ſo among you; but whoſoever will <pb n="164" facs="tcp:106212:91"/> be great among you, let him be your mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter; and whoſoever will be chief among you, let him be your ſervant.</hi> And yet, ſuch Servants as they be, they muſt be ſubmitted to in their Miniſtrations; for ſo our Lord ſaith elſewhere; <hi>He that heareth you, heareth me: And he that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me; and he that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſeth me, deſpiſeth him that ſent me,</hi> Luke 10. 16. Contempts of this nature do not only reflect upon God, but are grounded too upon contumelious Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of him, and proceed from Hearts that ſwell and are lifted up againſt him. The Probationary Atheiſt begins with efforts at the Pulpit, and goes on by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees to a perfect hatred of God, and of Religion, and of the Miniſters of Chriſt for God and Religion ſake. 'Tis the Spirit of <hi>Lucifer</hi> that worketh at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom; a ſecret Principle of Averſion and Enmity to all that is Good and Holy. Therefore to expreſs our Humility as we ſhould, we muſt obey them that have the Rule over us, and ſubmit our ſelves to thoſe that watch for our Souls, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 17. Which St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls in another place, <hi>knowing them which labour among us, and are over us in the Lord, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh us; and this, for their works ſake,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.
12, 13. Becauſe 'tis God's <pb n="165" facs="tcp:106212:91"/> Work they are about, God's Buſineſs they are upon; and ſo, the Obedience paid them in the diſcharge of their Office, is carried on to God, and terminates in God, for whoſe ſake it is that the hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Perſon hath a regard to one as vile, or viler than himſelf. This is an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a lowly Heart, and the proper, ready way to make it more lowly ſtill; to receive the Doctrines they deliver us from the Mouth of God; to lay up in our Minds the things ſpoken; to ſet our Souls upon the Conſideration of them; to give ear to Inſtruction; to lay hold on every opportunity of being inſtructed; to follow wholſome Directions; to take even Reproofs with meekneſs, with an aptitude and willingneſs to be reformed; and for all this, to have continually pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared and open Hearts.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <pb n="166" facs="tcp:106212:92"/>
            <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>How Humility is to be expreſs'd, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contented with ſuch things as we have.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="6">6. BECAUSE I am deſirous to draw this whole Diſcourſe to a full Point, I ſhall take notice but of two Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions more of Humility, which are as Conſiderable and Neceſſary as the reſt. And that which comes next to my Hand is in <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 5. That we <hi>be content with ſuch things as we have.</hi> Covetouſneſs, which the Apoſtle there cautioneth us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, is inconſiſtent with a Spirit of Humility, becauſe it is always attended with a diſtruſt of God's Providence, and with a ſecret averſeneſs to ſubmit to his Will; and is very uſually too a ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient Vice to Pride; a Slave and Drudge to toil for the ſupport of it. It is the taking away, or detaining of what is not One's own; or, an inordinate deſire of that which he hath no right unto. And the great reaſon why Men reach out their Hands to wreſt <hi>Naboth</hi>'s Vineyard
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:106212:92"/> out of his, and are greedy of laying Field to Field, and do ſuch other acts of Oppreſſion, as are contrary to the Laws of Religion and Nature; the reaſon I ſay, of this Injuſtice is, becauſe Men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend thereby to lift up themſelves the higher in the World; they rob, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen, and over-reach in order to their Advancement; and that they may be the more conſpicuous, by ſtanding upon an heap; tho' Wrath and Vengeance be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it, to blow up all at laſt. Men of humble Minds had rather ſtand on low Ground, to be hid in a Multitude; for ſince the Lord Jeſus was pleas'd to be numbred with Tranſgreſſors, a poor ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Man need not care what his Lot is, and among whom he chanceth to be reckoned. Whatever his Station be,
'tis better than he deſerves. This one hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Reflection ſhould be enough to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade us, in what condition ſoever we are, therewith to be content. But beſides this, there is in every humble Soul an aptitude to conſider, that God is the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Rector of the Univerſe; that no part of it is out of the reach of his Eye, or out of the verge of his Providence; that he always acteth according to the Laws of his own infinite Reaſon, and as it is beſt for his Creatures; that he aſſigneth <pb n="168" facs="tcp:106212:93"/> to every Man his Lot and Place; that he is the only competent Judge to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, what is proper for every Man, and what a Man himſelf is fitteſt for; that he taketh a due Care of every one, and provideth ſuch things for him, as are moſt ſuitable to his Quality and Calling; and that ſuch as ſeek him ſhall want no manner of thing that is good, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 34. 10. Theſe Principles are deeply rooted in all lowly Hearts, that are right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prepared to ſubmit to the Will, and to depend upon the Promiſes of God; and the genuine Product of them is this, that 'tis our beſt courſe to commit our ſelves to God's Diſpoſal, and to be ſatisfied with his Providence and Determinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: I am ſure this is infinitely more Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming and Advantageous, than to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Repining and Craving, as thoſe hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mourſome People are, who by taking falſe Meaſures of themſelves think, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is done for them, to fall ſhort of their Merits; and grudge if they be not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, when by ſtretching their Deſires continually, they render themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable of being filled. Therefore to expreſs our Humility, we muſt carefully learn theſe three things.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:106212:93"/> 1. TO have as mean an Opinion of the World, as we have of our own ſelves. The reaſon why Men covet the things of this Life with ſuch Greedineſs and Ambition is, becauſe they think Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to conſiſt in Riches and Greatneſs, and thoſe to be the happieſt Perſons, who have the largeſt ſhare of them. Now this is a moſt groſs miſtake, an argument of a childiſh and little Mind. For ſuch outward Enjoyments are for the moſt part inſtruments of Sin; and then they are the moſt unfortunate Men, that carry ſuch edg'd Tools in their Hands. The greater they be, the more able they are to do themſelves and others miſchief, and the more ready many times to do it. Vanity, Luxury, and a leud Life, are too often the ſad Conſequents of a plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Fortune; and when the loſs comes to be felt which ſuch expenſive Vices bring, Injuſtice and Rapine commonly follows next, and Repriſals are forced from defenceleſs Innocence. <hi>Do not rich men oppreſs you, and draw you before the judgment-ſeats?</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>James</hi> 2. 6. If Men have the Grace, to make a better uſe of God's Bleſſings, yet the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of them yields no more real Comfort, than what People of an Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour <pb n="170" facs="tcp:106212:94"/> Claſs are bleſt with, who have Air, and Food, and Cloths, and Reſt, as well as the moſt Proſperous. There may be in a Palace more Splendour and Gaiety; but this affords no more ſolid Felicity, than Moon-ſhine doth warmth. In this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect the humble Cottage may have much the advantage, where the ſleep of a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring man is ſweet, ſaith <hi>Solomon, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</hi> 5. 12. whether he eat little or much, he eats with an appetite that needeth not the ſtudies of an Epicure, or the Arts of <hi>Apicius.</hi> And the drinking his own ſweat is a preparative for more delightful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhments, than the niceſt Creatures can pretend to, who abuſe the Fruit, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking any ſhare of the Works of the Vineyard. Thoſe Pleaſures which Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Nature univerſally thirſteth after, run commonly in low Channels; the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed part of Mankind go away with them; to be ſure with as great a portion of them, as the moſt craving men can have; and 'tis in vain to look for Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs any where below, but in the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Virtue; particularly this. Virtue, Contentedneſs of Mind; without that, and for want of that alone, <hi>Haman</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was unhappy amidſt all his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours; all availed him nothing, becauſe he was ſo diſcontented to ſee <hi>Mordecai</hi> 
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:106212:94"/> the
<hi>Jew</hi> ſitting at the King's Gate, <hi>Eſth.</hi> 5. 13.</p>
            <p n="2">2. HAVING poſſeſt our Minds with low Thoughts of the World, we muſt, in the next place, ſhew our Humility, by being ſatisfied with things neceſſary. My meaning is not, that we muſt deſire no more, than what is juſt enough to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port Nature. For there are many things which One's Vocation, Quality, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Life calleth for, beſides what Nature requires for its maintenance. The Neceſſities of Princes, and great Men, are more and greater, than what ordinary People can pretend. And ſo it is throughout all inferiour Ranks and Orders of Men; according as their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies and Charges are, and according as their Degree and Condition is, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Providence of God hath placed them, ſo are their Neceſſities; theſe riſe or ſink in proportion to the other. The ſhort of the matter then is this, That when God hath made competent Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for us, anſwerable to our Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſuitable to that Place, Degree, and Station, wherein he hath been pleaſed to diſpoſe of us, we ſhould command our Deſires, and keep them from run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning out, and from roving abroad after <pb n="172" facs="tcp:106212:95"/> things ſuperfluous. If ſuperfluities fall into our Hands of themſelves, we are to diſpenſe them where they are needful, and as it is moſt for the Glory of God, and for the good of our Brethren. But our Appetites muſt not be ſo inordinate, as to crave for more than what we want our ſelves; and when thoſe Neceſſities are anſwer'd, we ſhould be ſatisfied and thankful. 'Tis Pride that makes Men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatiable; becauſe they think they never have as much as they deſerve: And this is its condemnation, That it quarrels with God for that he doth not humour us, and for not gratifying our Luſts, tho' he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally ſupplies our real Wants. It is a very true Obſervation, That none are ſo querulous, ſo greedy, ſo reaching after more, as thoſe to whom God hath been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry open-handed, and who have moſt reaſon to give Thanks, inſtead of Complaining; like ſqueamiſh Stomachs, that nauſeate the wholeſome Proviſion which is before them in abundance, and long for Rareties which are out of the way: A plain ſign, not of Want, but a Surfeit; and of a Diſeaſe within which needs a Phyſician rather than a Purveyor. Humble Men are glad of that which is within their reach; and make themſelves Happy in the enjoyment of it, becauſe they take <pb n="173" facs="tcp:106212:95"/> it as a Doal that God ſeeth to be fitteſt for them, tho' it be not a
<hi>Benjamin</hi>'s Meſs, nor the miraculous Portion of Quails and Manna. A competency is beſt; and few can think they want that, if they be not ſo partial, as to make their own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable Appetites, Judges in the caſe: An upright Conſcience will tell them, that they have at hand what is for their Neceſſity, and for their Delights too. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed God doth not rain down his Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings upon ſome, as he doth upon others; but the reaſon is, becauſe great Plenty would not be ſo good for them: The Soil in ſome places is ſo odd, that much watering would produce little but a crop of Nettles; things that would bring ſmart and hurt. Such is the Temper of ſome Mens Hearts, that were they as Great and Powerful as they could wiſh, there could be no tolerable living near them, and very ſlender hopes of their own li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving well in another World; ſo apt are many to make an ill uſe of the Riches of God's Mercy. 'Tis therefore an act of his Wiſdom and Goodneſs, to keep thoſe low, whoſe exaltation would be fatal: But as for the neceſſary Accommodations of Life, he provides thoſe for all; and gives them opportunity and means of ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering every day as much as will ſerve
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:106212:96"/> their turn, if they be not ſuch ſluggards, as to need the Ant for a Monitor. 'Tis not Nature, but Luxury, that complains for not being fed; and the Mother of that is Pride; which is like the Horſe-Leach we read of, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30. Whoſe two Daughters (that is, the two Forks of its Tongue) are always craving, Give, give; ſucking on, till the ſanguine Creature drops down through abundance, but not through ſatiety. Our real Neceſſities are not hard to be anſwer'd, if we would confine our fugitive Deſires, and ſuffer our ſelves to be in a Paradiſe, by being contented with what may be daily brought to our Doors, by the Bleſſing of God upon our honeſt Induſtry. Food and Cloths no Body needs want; and that is as much as the very greateſt can have; and more than they carry into another World with them: And why ſhould not every lowly Heart be pleaſed to have the ſame Portion; in having the Belly and the Back provided for as well, tho' not with the Vanity of ſumptuous and gorge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Furniture? That plain and humble Man, the Father of the Twelve Tribes, as he was Journying towards
<hi>Haran,</hi> was an Emblem to all that travel towards the Land of everlaſting Reſt. He paſſed on with a poor Staff in his Hand; and at
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:106212:96"/> 
               <hi>Bethel</hi> he took of the Stones he found there, and put them for his Pillows, and lay down upon them to ſleep: And in the morning, he ſet them up for a Pillar, and pouring Oil upon the top of it, he vowed a Vow, ſaying, <hi>If God will be with me, and will keep me in this way that I go, and will give me bread to eat, and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to put on; ſo that I come again to my Father's houſe in peace; then ſhall the Lord be my God: And this ſtone, which I have ſet for a pillar, ſhall be God's houſe; and of all that thou ſhalt give me, will I ſurely give the tenth unto thee,</hi> Gen. 28. Here was Gratitude, Simplicity, and Religion, mixed with the Modeſty of a truly hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Mind; the thing he asked for, was Bread and Raiment: And conſidering what an Improvement Chriſtianity is of Nature, this ſingle Example renders St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Exhortation the more binding,
1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6. 8. <hi>Having food and raiment, let us therewith be content.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. IN order thereunto we ſhould learn yet a Third thing; namely, not to make envious Compariſons between our own Condition, and the ſtate of thoſe who are Superiour to us. This is a great cauſe of Mens Diſſatisfactions and Murmurings, not that themſelves want, but becauſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <pb n="176" facs="tcp:106212:97"/> have a more liberal allowance. The Original of this, is Pride, which makes Men look a-ſquint upon thoſe above them, wiſhing themſelves in their Place, or at leaſt in a collateral Line with them; and thinking it hard meaſure, that their Station and Fortunes are not greater; and all this upon a vain ſuppoſition of their own, that they are as deſerving as the beſt. This is to direct Providence, and to ſet up againſt it; than which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be more inconſiſtent with a Spirit of Humility. For they who have a mean Opinion of themſelves, muſt needs think they are well uſed, if they have any room aſſigned them by the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, tho' it be the lowermoſt Seat; and are obliged to acquieſce in his Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, becauſe we are not our own chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, and the leaſt expreſſion of Favour from God, is not Debt, but Kindneſs and Grace. We ſhould be careful there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to take our Lot as it falls; and to look upon it, not as Partiality but Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom in him, when he keepeth down one, and ſetteth up another. He is the only competent Judge of what is fitteſt to be done; and the reaſons of his Providence are always Great, tho' we cannot peep through the Veil to ſee them at every turn.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="177" facs="tcp:106212:97"/> IN all his Proceedings he hath a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the Beauty, Order, and Stabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his whole Creation, and to the Good of every part. And as this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers a neceſſity of conſtituting different States and Conditions amongſt Mankind, that one may be ſubſervient to another, and that all may be ſubſervient to his Glory; ſo it requires us with all Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity to be contented with that Place and Condition, which God in his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom thinks to be moſt proper for us. This is the true way of husbanding God's Diſpenſations ſo, that we may be hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py under them, how obſcure ſoever our Sphere, and how ſlender ſoever our For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes are, if compar'd with theirs, whoſe Pomp ſome have the Vanity and the ill Nature to grumble at.</p>
            <p>FELICITY doth not reſide only in ſtately Manſions; nor indeed can it have acceſs to them, unleſs a lowly Heart be ready there to give it entertainment. It hath its abode with Contentedneſs, where-ever that dwells, tho' within a little Door, under a low Roof, with plain Diet, and in an homely Dreſs. It is a contented Mind that makes one hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py indeed; and ſo, every one may be <pb n="178" facs="tcp:106212:98"/> happy at home, if he will. 'Tis but bounding his extravagant Ambition, and being ſatisfied with his daily Bread, and the thing is preſently done. And this an humble Heart teacheth us to do; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Bread we have is of God's gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving. We pray for it daily, or, at leaſt, we ſhould; and becauſe it is God's Hand that reacheth it unto us, we ſhould bleſs him over it: And when we receive it with Thankfulneſs, and Comfort, and pleaſure of Mind, a dinner of Herbs is much better Fare, than the ſtalled Ox, that is ſacrificed to the Luſts of the vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuous and proud Wretch.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <pb n="179" facs="tcp:106212:98"/>
            <head>CHAP. XIII. <hi>How Humility is to be expreſs'd, by keeping an Even Temper in a State of Proſperity.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="7">7. THE laſt Expreſſion of Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which I ſhall mention, hath more peculiar reference to thoſe whom God hath bleſs'd with a flouriſhing Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. Humility is God's way to Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour; and to ſit down in the loweſt Room is to be capable of Advancement at God's Hands, who
<hi>exalteth them of low degree,</hi> as the humble Mother of our Lord ſaid,
<hi>Luke</hi> 1. 52. And when God is pleaſed to do this, we ſhould expreſs our Humility, by keeping an Even Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in a proſperous State. To ſhew how well-pleaſed God is, when People dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently follow the Works of their lawful, tho' it be a mean Calling; the firſt two Kings that were ſet ſucceſſively upon the Throne of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> were advanced, by God's own Directions to that great Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity from ordinary Employments;
<hi>Saul,</hi> as he was ſeeking his Father's Aſſes; <pb n="180" facs="tcp:106212:99"/> and <hi>David,</hi> as he was feeding his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Sheep. Which is an argument, that poor Beginnings are not any ſlurr; 'tis vanity and ſuperciliouſneſs, that is both the Crime and the Infamy, which too frequently follow a ſtate of Exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 'Twas the Vice which coſt
<hi>Saul</hi> his Credit, Crown, and Life. By what we read of him, before his advancement he deſerv'd the Character of a modeſt and humble Perſon: But Promotion, which makes a great Man, too often ſpoileth a good one; eſpecially when he is moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted high, not by gradual aſcents, but by a quick and unexpected lift. It preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly turn'd <hi>Saul</hi>'s Head; ſo that firſt he u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped <hi>Samuel</hi>'s Office; then acted againſt God's own expreſs Command, in ſparing the <hi>Amalekites;</hi> then grew ſowre, ſullen, envious, ſpightful, falſe, and outrageous, (which I ſuppoſe is meant by the evil Spirit from the Lord, that troubled him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi>
16.) And at laſt departed from God, to conſult a Pythoniſs: So that, as things fell out accidentally, through the Fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſs and Corruption of his own Heart, it had been better for <hi>Saul</hi> to have remained ſtill among the Aſſes. Indeed this Inſtance with all its Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances is ſingular. But yet 'tis no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>common thing to obſerve, That it is a
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:106212:99"/> very hard matter for ſome to bear up againſt their own Proſperity; and that the danger of their being loſt is the ſame with what a little Pinnace is in, when driven impetuouſly with too great ſail in the Head; eſpecially if it wants Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſt. This abuſe of Proſperity proceeds from a three-fold cauſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. FIRST, From a degeneracy and ſordidneſs of Diſpoſition; which, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be purely Natural, or Accidental, and for want of liberal, ingenuous Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, we need not diſpute. Every days Experience ſhews, That none are ſo hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and aſſuming as thoſe of baſe Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals; Trifles made lately of an ugly ſort of Clay, which no Art can bring to a due Temper, nor any thing Reduce, but a ſtroke from the Potter's Hand that formed them. The Perſonage, whom good Breeding and Quality makes Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious, diſtinguiſheth himſelf from the dirty Swain by his kind, courteous, and endearing Behaviour. Tho' his Fortunes grow, his Mind is kept prun'd and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred from running out into thoſe Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riances and Inequalities, which, without due care, all are ſubject to; eſpecially ſuch whoſe Root is in a Dunghill. That Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Mentz (Willegis)</hi> whoſe <pb n="182" facs="tcp:106212:100"/> Father was a poor Carpenter, did a very becoming act in hanging his Houſe with repreſentations of Saws and Axes; that he might be ſure, not to forget whence he had been hewn; and might preſerve himſelf the better from being elated by his ſurpriſing Dignity. Men ſhould be very watchful over themſelves when their Fortunes ſwell, leſt their Hearts ſwell with them. For then is the great Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; and then the Honour and the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue appears to admiration, when they govern themſelves with ſuch a ſtrict Hand, as to be always of a Piece; the ſame condeſcending Men, as when Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity and Wants made them crouch; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually as obliging, as when they ſtood in need, and courted thoſe whom a Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of Vanity would be apt, without great care to make them afterwards de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. THIS unevenneſs of Temper, and ſhameful Diſparity between the Man and himſelf, proceedeth, Secondly, from pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable Imprudence.
'Tis a ſign of a weak Head, when a Vertigo takes it upon the top of an Hill: There is ſome Defect within, in the Intellectual as well as Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Faculties; ſomething is wanting, which ſhould poiſe the Mind, and keep it ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:106212:100"/> when our Condition grows and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to a conſiderable pitch. To think we can be ſo high, as to be above all, and out of the reach of all, is a very fooliſh Imagination; for we are ever in danger of one another, and always ſtand in need of one another; and one time or other the loftieſt find it ſo: And ſuch inequalities of Temper, as Grate in a proſperous Condition, as they are more diſcernible and offenſive, ſo they expoſe vain People the more, firſt to Envy, and then to Ruine at the next fair opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. For the ſtate of this World ever was, and ever will be mutable; the Ground we ſtand upon is very ſlippery; nor are any more commonly tripp'd up, than thoſe that think they have ſure footing.
<hi>Pride goeth before deſtruction; and an haughty ſpirit before a fall,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov. 16. 18. His own Father had found much of this, after his advancement to the Throne; he ſaid in his Proſperity, he ſhould <hi>never be removed;</hi> God, as he thought, had of his Goodneſs made his Hill ſo ſtrong, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 30. 6. But he ſhews us himſelf in the very next words, what a vain and weak Conceit this was: <hi>Thou didſt turn thy face from me, and I was troubled.</hi> Nothing is more uſual than to ſee ſuch Viciſſitudes and Turns in the
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:106212:101"/> World; and many times Fortune is moſt perſidious to thoſe, who take occaſion by its Liberality to be falſe to others, and to deceive themſelves too with vain and fooliſh Confidences of their own. Such Cheats fall fatally, and the more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally for having been ſo; and commonly where they tumble, they lie unpitied. Theſe things wiſe and thinking Men will conſider in time, while the Bleſſings of God are in their Hands, and will carry them with ſuch Evenneſs, and Caution, and true Generoſity of Mind, that all good People may have reaſon to wiſh, they may never drop out of Hands that uſe them ſo well.</p>
            <p n="3">3. BUT after all, this unevenneſs of Temper I now ſpeak of, proceeds not ſo much from ſome foulneſs and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections in Nature, as from a wicked Abuſe of God's Grace, which is given Men to rectifie what is amiſs in them. There is in it a mighty touch of the Devil, who once ſet up againſt the moſt bleſſed God, becauſe he found himſelf a very glorious Creature. It is from ſuch a Spirit, that the greater and higher Men are in their outward Eſtate, the prouder too they are in their Minds. They take their Acquiſitions, not as Gifts and Boons, <pb n="185" facs="tcp:106212:101"/> but as Rewards, and as Payments in part of a great Debt. This muſt needs be the ſecret Principle ſuch elated People go upon; that all they have is a due; and but a pittance neither, in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of what they ought to have, and are very fit for. Hence it is, that their Pride increaſes with their Enjoyments. They conclude, that their ſingular Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages are only in Conſideration of their ſingular Deſerts; retributions of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; and as theſe are larger and larger, ſo is the Admiration of themſelves grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and greater ſtill: And then it is no wonder, if Men who are poſſeſt with ſuch lofty Notions, look down Diſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully upon all below them; becauſe they take meaſures of themſelves and others by Events, and Providential Succeſſes. They look upon theſe as clear Arguments and Determinations on their behalf, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they believe that God ſideth with them, and allots them the upper-hand, by reaſon that he too thinks them to be really better than their Neighbours. Now theſe are very dangerous Conceits, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are bottomed upon <hi>Lucifer</hi>'s Sin, and evidently lead proud Men to the very ſame Fate. Therefore we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not give better or plainer Expreſſions of our Humility than by keeping our
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:106212:102"/> Minds down, and by doing ſuch acts as argue them to be ſtill in a ſubdued Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, however it ſhall pleaſe God to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alt us. A ſtate of Greatneſs adds a vaſt Luſtre to this Vertue; or, rather creates a Luſtre in it, which makes it the more Admirable and Exemplary. It is then moſt Charming, when we cloath our ſelves with it in defiance of all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperity: Nor was <hi>Solomon</hi> in all his Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry arrayed like one ſuch little one. For this I appeal to the common Senſe of Mankind, whoſe daily Obſervations ſhew us, That there is no ſuch glorious Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as Humility; eſpecially when it keeps its former place in the midſt of flouriſhing Circumſtances; when no Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement can be powerful enough, to tranſport Men to an indecent Diſtance; nor to bring with it a techy Temper, or a ſupercilious Look; nor to make them forſake thoſe kind Offices, which they were ready for in a low Station.</p>
            <p>THE more becoming and admirable this Vertue is, the greater care is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of us to preſerve and keep it in all Conditions; but more particularly in a proſperous State, when the World ſmiles upon us, and fallacious Fortune attempts by Careſſes and Flatteries to ſteal away
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:106212:102"/> our humble Hearts from us. Then we ſhould uſe the greater Caution, becauſe the danger of loſing our ſelves is then juſt at hand. 'Tis no hard or uncommon thing, for People to carry themſelves in an humble manner while their Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is low. The difficulty is, how to act with the ſame Mien when Honours and Riches increaſe. In ſuch caſes Peoples Minds are naturally apt to be puffed up, eſpecially thoſe who are of ſmall Value, People of little Senſe, and of leſs Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. 'Tis very uſual for ſuch, when their Affairs begin to glitter, to be full of ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admiration, and to be carried away with Vanity. Nay, ſome are ſo weak, as to think it proper for them to affect State; tho' it ſits very aukwardly, and ill upon them; is very unſuitable to ſuch little things; and makes them as ridiculous, as Trappings of Gold do a Mule, or an Aſs. If therefore our Fortunes grow, we muſt be ſure to ſet the ſtricter Watch over our own Minds; we muſt preſently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide againſt all danger of a Flatus with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that may make our Brains giddy; and beware of every thing that may tempt us to put on a ſcornful Brow, or an imperious Temper. Indeed, the more God is pleaſed to multiply his Bleſſings upon us, the more humble we ſhould be. <pb n="188" facs="tcp:106212:103"/> And this I take to be the ſafe, infallible Rule to go by in ſuch a caſe, ſtill to lower our own Minds within, the more God exalts us without: For fear we ſhould not be able to poiſe Affairs ſo, as to keep the Scales even enough, to make our Hearts the Over-balance to caſt the one Scale, by ſinking and being depreſt, as theſe our external Acquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons riſe in the other. To be the more Self-denying for living Great; to be the more Charitable, Beneficent, and Open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>handed for being Wealthy; to be the more Cautious and Tender, for being Powerful; to be the more Devout and Holy, for being Proſperous; to be the more Innocent and Juſt, for having a plentiful Meaſure of God's Goodneſs; to be the more Condeſcending, for being High; to be the more Affable, Courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Obliging, Meek, Peaceable, and Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to be intreated, for having the more Advantages, the more Abilities and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of doing thoſe things which are Praiſe-worthy: Theſe indeed are tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Noble Expreſſions of a lowly Heart.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="189" facs="tcp:106212:103"/>
            <head>The CONCL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>SION.</head>
            <p>HAVING now diſpatch'd thoſe things which in the beginning of this Diſcourſe I promiſed to conſider, I ſhall conclude all with an humble Addreſs to my Readers, to do their part in making ſuch a Chriſtian Uſe of what hath been ſaid, as may be for their own real Good: The great End which I had at firſt in my Eye, and that which ſhould be the rather anſwer'd, becauſe it is of the quickeſt diſpatch, as well as of very near con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern. To write Diſcourſes is not ſo eaſie, as to make a good Uſe of them, if Men would apply the Zeal of Honeſt and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Hearts to do it: Which, methinks ſhould not be wanting where they are ſure before-hand of this Advantage, that <hi>their labour ſhall not be in vain.</hi> Neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry indeed it is; abſolutely neceſſary in order to our everlaſting Happineſs in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother World. For we muſt not be ſo fooliſh as to think, that God will drag us to Heaven againſt our Wills; or, that he will give us a Portion of Bliſs there, if we be indiſpos'd and unprepared for it. The Practice of Religion and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue ſerves to make us meet and fit for <pb n="190" facs="tcp:106212:104"/> what we are to do among Saints and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels: And this particular Vertue I have been treating of, is a principal Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Soul, that we muſt carry thither with us. Beſides, no other Vertue is or can be more neceſſary to make us happy in ſome meaſure here. There is ſuch a cloſe connexion of This to divers other Vertues, and of all, to Happineſs, that our Duty is in the very Practice of it a Reward; nor is it poſſible for us to be miſerable, no not in this Life, but by our acting Hoſtilities againſt our ſelves; and ſuch Hoſtilities too, as none but Fools would deſire to gain a Victory by, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is a Conqueſt over our own Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licities. This Vertue, for inſtance, Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, brings with it a kind of Heaven up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth: It is attended with ſuch Faith in God, with ſuch Submiſſion to his Will, and with ſuch Dependance upon his Truth, Mercy, Power, and Goodneſs, that a compos'd and happy State of Mind muſt needs attend it too; ſo that by trampling upon this Vertue, People do really deſtroy their own Comforts; and what-ever proud Men think, they have no ſuch Enemy, as the Satan in their Breaſts. Hence it is, that Humility is ſo often extoll'd, ſo often commanded, ſo often encouraged by various Promiſes <pb n="191" facs="tcp:106212:104"/> throughout the Scripture; becauſe God ſeeth it to be ſo infinitely Inſtrumental to our own Good.</p>
            <p>THIS renders the Conſideration the more melancholy and lamentable, that a Vertue which would be a common Bleſſing, is ſo great a Rarety. For, if we take a ſtrict view of thoſe Evils, which imbitter Mens Lives, and ruine the Peace in Church and State, which would make them happy, we ſhall find, that they all or moſtly proceed from an epidemical Principle of Pride, which gives thoſe ſturdy Vices both birth and maintenance. When
<hi>Hagar</hi> had the Inſolence to deſpiſe her Miſtreſs, no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that the <hi>Egyptian</hi> brought forth a wild <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> whoſe Hand was againſt every Man, <hi>Gen.</hi> 16. 12. Such a trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome off-ſpring naturally deſcends from an imperious Parent: And 'tis ſuch another Original that thoſe outrageous Sins come from, which infeſt us to this day, both within our own Walls, and abroad in the World. A too great and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grown Conceit of One's ſelf, doth by a Phyſical Influence diſpoſe him to think it very hard to be adviſed, harder to be commanded, and the moſt intolerable di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution to obey. Hence proceed Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents, Murmurings, Impatience, Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs, <pb n="192" facs="tcp:106212:105"/> deſires of Innovation, contempt of our Superiors, reviling of Magiſtrates, affectation of Power, and divers other Wickedneſſes, which prepare Men to caſt off the Yoke, and to bring on innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſorts of Rapine and Oppreſſion, which are always the certain Conſequents of avowed Diſobedience.</p>
            <p>WERE a Spirit of Humility ſuffer'd to prevail in the World, it would ſoon bring with it ſuch a compos'd, peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, and harmonious ſtate of Affairs, as would make Private People, and Publick Societies as happy, as they could wiſh to be on this ſide Eternity: And when a Vertue that is ſo excellent, is yet ſo ſcarce, it ſhews us to our ſhame what great Fools Men are; and what ſtupidity there is in ſome Natures, which can endure to be laugh'd at for being fond of a Vice, which was <hi>Lucifer</hi>'s Crime, and is now propagated on Earth only to be our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Plague.</p>
            <p>BUT having ſpoke already of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonableneſs and hurtfulneſs of Pride, I ſhall not draw you back to Meditations we have paſt from long ago, but cloſe all by deſiring you to look forward, to the end of it. There are two things <pb n="193" facs="tcp:106212:105"/> yet to come, that will ſtain the Pride of all Glory, as the Prophet ſpeaks, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 23. 9. I mean, Death, and Judgment. Theſe will give the laſt ſtroke to all our Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies; and the proſpect of them is enough to lay our Minds proſtrate, if our Pride be not like <hi>Alexander</hi>'s, whoſe Triumphs exalted him into the ſillieſt Fancy, <hi>That he was immortal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. O Death! How bitter art thou to a Man that ſitteth at Eaſe in his Poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? And ſo it muſt needs be to every vain Man that ſetteth himſelf in too rich a Chair of State. Tho' for that reaſon ſuch People think of nothing ſeldomer, than of dropping into the Grave, yet <hi>it is appointed unto all men, once to die,</hi> Heb. 9. 27. And when that Meſſenger comes to execute its Commiſſian, no Riches can Bribe it off, no Grandeur can keep it at a Diſtance, nor can any Arguments perſuade to uſe Reſpect. It will ſtrike all with an impartial Hand, lay all of us down in our primordial Duſt, and there give Prince and Peaſant an equal Portion. There no diſcrimina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is made between High and Low, when once all are laid down. The haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Head, the long Arm, the thick and
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:106212:106"/> heavy Finger, has there the very ſame fate, with the Hand that once hung down, and with the feeble Knee; nor doth the Worm make any difference, between the pamper'd Fleſh, and that which was wont to be covered with Sack-cloth. Theſe are mortifying Meditations; and ſuch as have a direct tendency to hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble us all, would we daily conſider, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we are going; what a ſtate we ſhall all fall into at laſt; and how we ſhall be hudled together in one common heap of Duſt. Men generally ſtoop in their old Age: Nature thereby ſhews them, that they ſhould daily look down towards the Hole, that will ſhortly receive them, and that every day draws them, as it were, by a Magnetick faculty more and more towards it. And the oftner we think of this, the apter our Minds will be to bow down too; nothing being ſo pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful for the pulling down of vain Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, as the remembrance and ſenſe of our Mortality. For which reaſon I have now imitated the Cuſtom of the old <hi>Perſians,</hi> who at their ſplendid En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainments were wont to ſerve up a Death's-Head for the laſt Courſe, to put one another in mind, what they were to come to after all their Jollities. If this <pb n="195" facs="tcp:106212:106"/> was thought ſo uſeful a thing by
<hi>Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks,</hi> who looked not beyond the Grave; at leaſt had not thoſe Eyes which have been given Us by him who cured the Blind; 'twere ſtrange, if we ſhould not be much more powerfully wrought upon, who have a farther and clearer Proſpect; I mean, of a Judgment, which begins preſently upon our Diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution.</p>
            <p>IT is no great matter what becomes here of our Bodies: They do but go home to their Parent. The Duſt <hi>returns to the earth as it was; and the Spirit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns unto God who gave it,</hi> Eccleſ. 12. 7. To receive its Sentence at God's Hand, according to all it hath done in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. The Author of the Book of <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> would have us conſider before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand, what the End will be, when the Accounts of our Sins (and more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, of our Aſſumings) come to be caſt up. <hi>What then will the pride of men profit them? And what good will their riches, with all their vaunting, do them?</hi> Wiſd. 5. 8. The ſin which at firſt was with ſuch fury thrown out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, we may be ſure will never find any re-admiſſion thither. And therefore it <pb n="196" facs="tcp:106212:107"/> everlaſtingly concerns us, to caſt it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from us in time, becauſe it affects the Soul with a curſed Incapacity of ever appearing in the preſence of the humble Jeſus, to Reign with him, after all its Imperiouſneſs on Earth. A wicked Soul is utterly uncapable of this, by reaſon that its Inclinations and Diſpoſitions are utterly inconſiſtent with that State, which is the Portion of juſt Men now made Perfect. The ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e paſſing of Souls out of this World into the next, cannot poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly be enough to change their Temper. Death indeed gives them an outlet, into ſuch Places as are ſuitable and proper for them; but it doth not make an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire alteration of their Faculties and Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits; it is no ſuch Refiner, as to cleanſe what was polluted; Repentance, and Faith in the Blood of Chriſt muſt do that before we go hence, or elſe it will never be done. <hi>He that is unjuſt, will be unjuſt ſtill; and he that is filthy, will be filthy ſtill; and he that is righteous, will be righteous ſtill; and he that is holy, will be holy ſtill,</hi> Revel. 22. 11. Thoſe Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions and Qualities which Souls have at Death, they carry with them into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther World, and keep with them for ever: And ſo we may add, That he <pb n="197" facs="tcp:106212:107"/> which is proud, will be proud ſtill; and therefore cannot be fit for any Place, but where that Vice is puniſh'd, nor for any Company but the Devil and his Angels, that were firſt guilty of it. How light ſoever Men make of their evil Tempers, the end of them muſt be miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable; they have a neceſſary and direct tendency towards it; nor is there any way of preventing it, but by being new Creatures here: It is by acquiring new Natures, new Diſpoſitions, new Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Habits, which may make <hi>us meet to be partakers of the inheritance of the Saints in light,</hi> Col. 1. 12. Of thoſe Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, an humble Temper is one, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed one of the chiefeſt: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Promiſe of a preſent and future Reſt is made more eſpecially to this Vertue, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11. 29. <hi>Learn of me, for I am meek and lowly in heart; and ye ſhall find reſt to your ſouls. Which God of his Mercy grant unto us all for the ſake of that great Exemplar of Holineſs and Humility, Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <hi>Almighty and Everlaſting God, who of thy tender Love towards Mankind, haſt ſent thy Son, our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, to take upon him our Fleſh, and to ſuffer <pb n="198" facs="tcp:106212:108"/> Death upon the Croſs, that all Mankind ſhould follow the Example of his great Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility; mercifully grant, that we may both follow the Example of his Patience, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo be made Partakers of his Reſurrection, through the ſame Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Amen.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:106212:108"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
